We often hear that global warming, or climate
change, is at catastrophic levels and humans need
to take action to prevent destroying the planet.
But how serious is it really? Is there a biblical
way to approach this controversial
topic? Today on Creation Magazine Live
Welcome to the first episode of
season nine of Creation Magazine Live!
I'm Richard Fangrad. And I'm Matt Bondy. Now
when visiting churches CMI speakers often get
asked about climate change. That's not surprising
since we employ bible-believing scientists
and many Christians are looking for direction
on the issue by informed researchers. Now,
unless you've been living under a rock, the
issue that many are near hysterical about is that
atmospheric temperature is supposedly going up
because humans are producing too much carbon
dioxide. And if temperature goes beyond a
certain threshold it'll be catastrophic for life
on earth. That's called anthropogenic global
warming. Whoa can you say that one again? It's
anthropogenic, means man-made. Okay, man-made.
That leads to a key point that we
need to clarify here, it's not just
“is there climate change?” But, “are humans
to blame?” Two separate questions there. Now
this is a huge topic, and today we'll begin to
examine the issue from a Christian and scientific
perspective but we won't have time to
cover all the points this half hour so
we'll extend this topic to next week's show
too and address whether climate is changing,
if so, how drastic is it? Are humans to
blame? And, how should Christians respond?
Lots of questions. Almost all the content for
these two shows comes from a massive article on
our website by Dr Don Batten with contributions
from bible-believing scientists from all around
the world. Even with two half-hour shows
dedicated to this topic we're only summarizing
the main points. So for more details check out
that article at creation.com/climate-change
We're covering this topic because it has a lot
to do with worldviews. A view of the world,
an all-encompassing perspective on
everything that exists and matters to us.
A person's worldview represents his
most fundamental beliefs and assumptions
about the universe he inhabits. And
different worldviews will produce
different reactions and actions
to the topic of climate change.
Our Christian, or let's say biblical, worldview
compels us to revere the God of creation.
Some of the principles relevant
to today's subject are:
The universe and earth were created
through and for Jesus Christ.
The earth was also created for mankind.
We're called to be holy and
blameless in Jesus Christ.
Christ holds his creation together.
We are to worship the creator not the
creation, or Gaia, or mother earth.
Mankind is called to steward God's
creation. Yes Christians we affirm
that we have responsibility to look after the
environment. We're also compelled to consider
the poor and the general welfare of
our neighbors among other things.
Those are some of the basics foundational to
the Christian worldview that provide really a
starting point for understanding
this issue of climate change.
Building on from there we need to be mindful of
the real history of the world from the bible,
especially those events that would impact climate
change and the climate change debate. And we'll
contrast this history with the naturalistic
history and worldview where there is no God,
so everything came from nothing through
natural processes over billions of years,
humans are no more important than cows, or
trees, or cockroaches. Some claim that the
environment was fine for hundreds of millions of
years until a man came along and messed it up.
But in the biblical view from the beginning humans
were created to care for and rule over the earth.
Those are really different world views. Now,
another major historical event related to
climate change happened about 4 500 years
ago. Noah's flood covered the earth in water and
buried massive amounts of vegetation and animals
turning them into coal and other fossil fuels.
Nearly all of today's coal was formed from
the vegetation buried during Noah's flood the
huge amount of buried vegetation suggests that
pre-flood CO2 levels must have been very high
compared to today’s levels. CO2 is plant food.
Even secular geologists agree that ancient
Paleozoic CO2 levels were much higher,
like even 15 times more than they are
today. But there's no evidence that the
earth was cooked by this situation through a
runaway greenhouse effect. The much higher CO2
levels would boost plant productivity and
also allow for much more animal biomass.
Another key event to consider is that the
flood created ideal conditions for an Ice Age,
for a few hundred years following
the flood. These were both
catastrophic climate events. Since then there have
been comparatively minor fluctuations in climate.
Our environment is designed to be reasonably
stable as Genesis 8:22 suggests, “While earth
remains seedtime and harvest cold and heat
summer and winter day and night shall not cease.
Naturalists deny a global flood and claim
many ice ages over millions of years.
This is based largely on the Milankovitch theory
which suggests small wobbles in the earth's
orbit around the sun over long periods of time
resulted in slight differences in solar radiation.
But the small differences they propose
can't really create the massive changes
in the environment needed for an Ice Age so
instability is still built into the models.
Think about it: if a little change in
sunlight can cause a radical changing
climate, then a little change in greenhouse
gases like CO2 should maybe do the same.
So there's one of the bases
for climate alarmism, right?
Yes. If you believe that little changes produce
massive ice ages then little changes
in CO2 might very well cook the earth.
Another event to consider is that, yes, God
created everything very good originally,
but because Adam sinned creation is cursed
and is in a state of decay. Romans 8 says
that the creation was “subjected to futility”
and is currently in “bondage to corruption”.
But God promises to restore this decaying
creation turning it into the New Heavens
and New Earth where believers
will spend eternity with him.
The book of Revelation describes future events
and talks about this current earth in past
tense saying the first Heaven and the first
Earth had passed away. Christians have been
commanded to look after the earth, but our hope
is in something far better that's yet to come.
Naturalism doesn't offer a hope like that.
So you can see why naturalists might want
to over-emphasize or even distort the severity
of climate change. If you think this is earth
that's all we have, right? Or
Elon Musk, the CEO of SpaceX,
wants to make humans a multi-planetary species.
One of the reasons he wants to colonize Mars is
so that humans could survive an extinction event
on earth like World War 3 or climate change.
There's also a hints of Gaia worship among
some environmentalists who see humans as
evil for using up resources. They equate
that with ‘killing mother earth’. That is
a little bit different from naturalism
as it involves worshiping creation,
but it does still figure into
this whole climate change issue.
And finally, God is sovereign. He's
in control of history, and weather,
and all the creation guiding it to the end that
He's decreed, despite all attempts by humans to
control their destiny. He made us caretakers,
but we have a limited amount of control there.
For naturalists, if there's no God
and if humans are responsible for
destroying the environment then it's
assumed that only humans can fix it.
The climate change debate is largely dominated
by the world view coming out of naturalism, so
Christians need to be a little careful on one hand
not to reject the whole issue because of that,
and on the other hand not to blindly accept the
statements from climate change leaders. We need
to treat this issue with wisdom, and we'll
outline the foundation for that in a moment.
Did you know that the DNA code is itself
governed by another code known as the
epigenetic code? This physical and chemical
code determines which genes are switched on.
Changes in this code can greatly alter an
organism without altering one letter of its DNA.
For instance, scientists have managed to change
the coat colour in mice by feeding them a diet
that switches off certain genes. Epigenetics
poses new problems for evolution. For instance,
a group of animals with a camouflaged coat colour
might be favored in a particular environment. But
if this coat colour is due to epigenetics and
not the actual DNA code then the non-camouflaged
animals would be selected against in vain when the
epigenetic modification is reset by a diet change.
Natural selection is sent back to square one. The
field of epigenetics, therefore, creates problems
for evolution and strongly points to a master
programmer who invented the DNA and epigenetic
codes. To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
CMI needs your support. Give the video a
like, subscribe, and share the video on
twitter and Facebook. That's right. This shows
the algorithm that you appreciate the content.
You know bible-believing scientists
worked for months to gather the data
sifting through huge amounts of research on
climate change to produce the article on which
the show is based. The result was a 14 000-word
article at creation.com/climate-change and today's
episode summarizes some of that content. Now let's
learn about the science behind climate change.
How scientific is climate change? Here are five
considerations about how science works and how
this impacts the science of climate change. One
basic tenet of science is that it is testable.
The heart of the scientific method is that
hypotheses can be tested with experiments. After
doing a number of experiments the results allow
the calculation of a confidence in the conclusion
being true, and not just some random variation. A
probability of 95% is normally the lowest accepted
in science. So, in other words, it's okay if
one experiment in 20 gives a false result.
In climate science the observation is that
global temperature has been going up as
well as the level of CO2. The hypothesis
is that CO2 released into the atmosphere
by human activity is causing
the higher temperature.
The problem is that it's not possible to design
a repeatable experiment to test this hypothesis
because of the size, complexity, and uniqueness
of the system. After all there's only one planet
earth and it's rather complicated. So we're
left with conjectures and predictions. Applying
statistical models to the past temperature
data can generate a prediction for the future,
but the confidence limits are so wide
that the predictions are kind of useless.
And this approach can't say whether CO2 is causing
the change. So, the climate models that predict
a temperature response to CO2 have to be
deterministic. That is, they have to assume that
the inputs will determine the temperature. So the
assertion, based on these models, that CO2 causes
global warming is actually circular reasoning.
And that's a that's a big no-no in science.
The second point is that science cannot prove
theories to be true only false. Observing a result
predicted by a hypothesis that doesn't prove the
hypothesis as there may be other explanations.
So higher temperatures, for example, could be
the result of something other than CO2. But
if the data shows higher temperatures with lower
levels of CO2 that would disprove the hypothesis.
Number three: correlation doesn't mean causation.
So even if the CO2 levels and the temperatures are
both on the rise, it doesn't prove that one caused
the other. For example between June and December
of 2008, both the temperature in Calgary, Alberta,
Canada and the Toronto stock exchange decreased
dramatically. But no one has ever blamed the
stock market for the plunge in Calgary weather.
Oh that's it. No causation there. Number four:
science is often captured by a ruling paradigm.
A paradigm is a framework used
by default to interpret data.
For example, since mainstream science
is dominated by naturalism, conclusions
that include a creator or intelligent
designer are automatically excluded.
In climate science this can mean leaving
out explanations other than man-made CO2.
Number five: peer review lends
credibility to research but it
doesn't ensure truth necessarily.
There are many examples of failure
in the peer review process within climate
science, as well as other disciplines.
So you can see how the climate
change issue is quite complex.
We've just briefly outlined five things to
consider about how science works and some of the
challenges in applying good scientific
practices to the climate change debate.
Before that we looked at historical considerations
that would really dramatically impact how we
understand or prioritize atmospheric data. And
we began with outlining worldview considerations.
Okay so with all these considerations,
now let's dive into some of the data.
This is my favorite part here.
Since much of the debate revolves around CO2
emissions let's start there. In 1860 the amount
of CO2 in our atmosphere was approximately 285
parts per million, or 0.029 percent. As of 2020
it was 410 parts per million or 0.41 percent.
So that's just under a 50 percent increase over
160 years. And the current rate of increase
is about two parts per million per year.
Meanwhile the planet has warmed by
about 0.8 degrees celsius since 1880,
but half of this occurred before
any significant change to the CO2.
This graph shows both the man-made CO2
emissions and global temperature changes
from 1850 to 2010. The green line shows an
increase in man-made CO2, most of it since 1940,
you can see the black line shows fluctuations
in overall temperature. Now notice that the
rate of temperature increased from 1860 to 1880,
when there was relatively little man-made CO2,
is about the same as for the most recent period
when emissions were about 60 times higher. Also
note that there were dips in temperature at
times when CO2 emissions were still going up.
So the increase in temperature cannot
be entirely due to man-made CO2. That's
not to say it isn't a factor, just
maybe not the most significant one.
Human contribution to CO2 emissions by burning
fossil fuels accounts for less than five
percent of the total global carbon budget. Other
factors include things like changes in land use,
deforestation, volcanoes, CO2
released from the oceans as they warm,
the breakdown of organic remains, such as dead
wood in forests, and other factors like that.
And CO2 is just one of many greenhouse
gases in our atmosphere. These gases are
important for life on earth because
without them the average temperature
would be about 33 degrees
Celsius lower than it is now.
That'd be cold. Nearly all of the warming
effect is actually due to a powerful greenhouse
gas called, are you ready for this? Water vapor.
Only about 3.3 degrees of it is from CO2
man-made or otherwise. Yet it's CO2 that we hear
about the most. That's astounding isn't it? Water
vapor is a far more significant greenhouse gas.
And other greenhouse gases include methane,
nitrous oxide, chlorofluorocarbons.
It seems strange that water is often
left out of the climate change debate,
but it has a much greater effect on
temperature than greenhouse gases.
You know, maybe we should focus on reducing our
water vapor emissions. I'm not sure that'll work.
Even assuming all of the two parts per
million increase in CO2 is man-made,
it would take nearly 200 years to double
the level to 800. So why panic? Why panic?
That's actually a good question. Is
it really about following the science?
The climate change debate is dominated by
not just naturalism, but also humanism, and
neo-Marxism. Some of the rhetoric is more about
politics and philosophy than saving the planet.
Consider this statement from economist Ottmar
Endenhofer, an official with the Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change or the IPCC. He says,
“But one must say clearly that we redistribute
de facto the world's wealth by climate policy.
Obviously the owners of coal and oil will not be
enthusiastic about this. One has to free oneself
from the illusion that international climate
policy is environmental policy. This has almost
nothing to do with environmental policy anymore.”
And that's a mainstream, or is
becoming more of a mainstream,
viewpoint. A more radical activist Stuart Basden,
co-founder of Extinction Rebellion, he wrote this,
“And I'm here to say that XR, extinction
rebellion, isn't about the climate.
You see the climate's breakdown is a symptom
of a toxic system that has infected the ways
we relate to each other as humans and to
all life.” He goes on to say, pretty much,
that he's given up on fixing the climate
but the real problems include things like
white supremacy and class hierarchy. He says that
Extinction Rebellion is about fixing the system,
which essentially means destroying western
society. That's where they're going with this.
And some radical political parties have used
environmentalism to promote sweeping change
such as reduction of world population
and destruction of free markets.
This would lead to widespread poverty and, they
hope, would make folks more likely to vote for
neo-Marxist policies. Ironically the environment
has suffered in all Marxist countries to date.
One question for activists is why not
focus on the biggest CO2 contributors
like China and India? In 2018, for example,
China generated almost a thousand gigawatts
of electricity from coal. The United States
had 261 in Australia, for example, had 36.
China and India are planning hundreds
more coal-fired power stations.
Australia, for example, accounts for only 1.2
percent of the world's emissions. But like other
western nations they're targeted by activists
far more than China. It's not that western nation
shouldn't reduce emissions, but shouldn't the
protests be focused on the biggest offenders?
The U.S. has recently reduced emissions by
focusing more on natural gas, which emits far
less CO2 than coal. The IPCC the Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change identified nuclear power
as an important alternative, but it currently
generates only about 10 percent of the world's
electricity from just 440 reactors. It's both
green and relatively cheap over the long term but
most activists, they don't seem very interested
in it. So it's not just about ‘following the
science’. After the break we'll focus on some
other strange facts about climate change.
What sort of catastrophe would be required to
entomb over 120 species of marine invertebrates in
fine-grained rock? This is not just a hypothetical
question. In the Canadian Rockies over 120 species
of marine invertebrates have been found preserved
in a famous formation known as the Burgess shale.
Most of these animals were soft-bodied and many
are so exquisitely preserved that you can still
see the food in their stomachs. It appeared they
were buried and preserved almost instantaneously.
Moreover the creatures were apparently buried in
turbulent conditions because the fossils are found
dumped at a variety of angles relative to the
bedding. Fossil graveyards like this are found
all over the world collectively they point
to catastrophic flooding occurring on a
worldwide scale because the global flood
recorded in the bible actually occurred.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Help more people see this video. Give
the video a like, subscribe, and share
the video on Twitter and Facebook. This shows
the algorithm that you appreciate the context.
Climate change is a huge issue and it's
a big part of many people's worldview.
Thinking properly about our relationship with the
environment is important. That's right. That's why
sharing this video is important get it out there.
Get it out there. Let's get back to the show.
There seems to be some shady things going
on especially when there's money to be made.
For example, former U.S vice president Al
Gore is well known for promoting the need
to reduce our so-called carbon footprint,
yet his mansion uses about 21 times as much
energy as the average U. S. home. To offset
this he buys carbon credits. But he buys
them from companies that he founded to trade
carbon credits, companies now worth millions.
There's also something fishy about the infamous
hockey stick graph. The graph shows that after
a thousand year period of relatively stable
temperatures there was a dramatic spike within
the last century, particularly in the last
few decades. This is usually attributed to
the use of fossil fuels. However, this
graph has been shown to be fraudulent.
It doesn't record either the medieval
warming period or the little ice age
from the from the mid 1300s to about 1885. When
we add those back the graph should look more like
this, showing fluctuations in global temperatures
before any increase in man-made CO2 emissions.
It’s said that a picture is worth a
thousand words. Well, the image of
that fraudulent graph was a fear-mongering
tactic that influenced millions of people.
And the fear it produced motivated
people to vote in climate activists.
There's also a lesson from history here, and
that's that the world was better off when global
temperatures were warmer. Commenting on a TV
documentary about global warming anti-creationist
Ian Plimer said, “Groups like BAMOS and the
IPCC deny, minimize or ignore significant recent
climate changes that gave us the Roman Warming,
the Dark Ages, the Medieval Warming, and the
Little Ice Age. Both history and archaeology
show that in previous warmings temperatures
were far higher than at present. Populations and
economy thrived. Previous coolings led to famine,
depopulation and social disruption. History
shows that it's dangerous to ignore history.”
So, a little warmer is actually a little
better. It's clear that there are other
goals mixed in with the climate change debate,
right? It's not just about saving the planet
and ‘following the science’. There's outright
fraud. Now let's talk about the predictions
made by activists, including the IPCC and
compare them with the actual data. In the
1970s we were told, and many of you will remember
this, that we're heading for another ice age.
What scientists are telling us now is that the
threat of an ice age is not as remote as they once
thought. At weather stations in the far north
temperatures have been dropping for 30 years.
Seacoast's long free of summer ice are now blocked
year-round. According to some climatologists
within a lifetime we might be
living in the next ice age.
That didn't happen. Oops. But some of the
same experts who predicted global cooling
started talking about global warming. But,
again, those predictions didn't materialize,
so it's just called climate
change, it's just climate change.
For example, in 2008 Dr Tim Flannery from the
Australian government's climate change unit said,
“Just imagine yourself in a world five
years from now, so that would be 2013,
when there's no more ice over the arctic.”
In that same year Al Gore made a similar
prediction. That was the common view of the
mainstream climate scientists at the time. Now
the minimum annual coverage of arctic sea ice
has declined from a high of about 7.5 million
square kilometers in 1990 but
it was actually higher in 2020
than it was in 2012 at nearly 4 million
square kilometers. That's a lot of ice.
That's still a lot of ice. So the
predictions were way off. And,
by the way, the fluctuations in the
amount of arctic ice over time are
expected. This was especially true after the
post-flood ice age a few thousand years ago.
We said before that it's generally
agreed that the greenhouse effect
of a doubling of atmospheric CO2 means that the
temperature rises about 1.1 degrees Celsius.
So at the current rates it'll take about
200 years to double the CO2 concentration
resulting in another 1.1 degree increase. So
what's the big deal? What is the big deal?
The big deal is because climate models include
positive feedback or amplification mostly from
increased water vapor as a result of warming
oceans. The idea is that for the 1.1 degree
of warming caused by a CO2 increase alone,
the ECS or Equilibrium Climate Sensitivity
would result in a total increase
of between 1.5 and 4.5 degrees.
Okay. So how do the climate models
compare with the observations?
Well, predicting future temperature is
difficult. Even the IPCC noted in 2001,
“The climate system is a coupled
non-linear chaotic system,
and therefore the long-term prediction of
future climate states is not possible.”
Yeah but they went ahead anyway
using over 100 different models.
Yes. If the science is settled, as we often
hear, all you need is one. That should do
it. The one based on science. This graph shows
the many predictions from 102 models. The black
line represents the average. Notice all of the
actual readings from three different satellites,
the green, red, and blue lines, the
actual data, is much lower than any of the
102 models predicted, even though
CO2 levels went up. There's a fail.
No kidding. The models are simply wrong.
But wait there's more prediction failures.
Model predictions for ocean
temperatures were also wrong.
This graph shows the models in red compared to the
actual data from over 3 000 robotic instruments
floating all over the oceans
from 2004 to 2012. Another fail.
If positive feedback occurs from increased water
vapor there should be an atmospheric hot spot in
the middle latitudes at the tropics. Okay.
Again, note the models in red versus actual
data from satellites and weather balloons. None
of the data showed any hot spots. Fail again.
We're seeing a pattern here, right? Let's keep
going. Increased water vapor is supposed to
trap more of the incoming solar radiation, so
more warming. As sea surface temperature rises
there should be less outgoing radiation
from the earth but satellite measurements
show outgoing radiation is increasing, the
opposite of IPCC predictions. Yet another fail.
The data shows positive feedback isn't operating.
In fact, there's strong evidence for negative
feedback, probably resulting from enhanced
cloud cover reflecting the sun's radiation
back into space. When negative feedback is
taken into consideration the warming effect
of doubling atmospheric CO2 is only about 0.5
degrees Celsius. Nowhere near the 4.5 degrees that
some have predicted. Similarly, a comprehensive
study from a German company arrived at an ECS
of 0.7 degrees and also concluded that negative
feedbacks more than offset positive feedback.
The bottom line here is we don't need drastic
action to stay within the 1.5 degree target.
And, look, we're just getting started. Time's
winding down here, but we'll continue next week.
There are some very interesting
things we'll talk about then but
even now aren't you shocked by some of
the data that that we've presented here?
We used to hear about how ‘the science is
settled’, but we don't even hear that anymore.
The idea that increased CO2 is going to roast the
planet, that's just assumed to be a fact, right?
And if you don't believe it,
well, you're just uneducated,
or you're a ‘denier’, right? On
the same level as somebody who
believes that God created the earth about 6 000
years ago. You just don't understand science.
And there’s this notion that 97 percent of
scientists agree that man-made CO2 will cause
catastrophic global warming. Actually,
let's start with that claim next week.
Yeah, sounds good. Thomas and Alexander
will be hosting next week's show and
they can start with that. Now remember
Christianity is an evidence-based faith,
and science supports scripture see you next week.
Thanks so much for watching. Now once episode 2
is up we'll put a link in the description below
and that will provide another half hour of content
from Dr Don Batten's massive article. This is a
huge issue and there was so much content in
that article that we dedicated two episodes
and that's still not enough. You'll need to look
up the article at creation.com/climate-change
to get all the details.
Hey enjoy your reading and
we'll see you next week.