Only about 1% of
abortion decisions are the
result of rape, and
only 0.5% are from incest.
The vast majority of women seeking
an abortion engaged in sex voluntarily.
It's estimated 3
out of 4 sexual assaults are
not reported, but
that still doesn't justify
abortion on demand.
Please understand, rape is a terrible
and violent assault that no woman should ever
have to go through.
But in what other
scenario is it permissible
for a victim of a
crime to retaliate against
an innocent third party?
If someone beats
you up in a parking lot, no
one suggests you go
and punch your neighbor's
kid.
It used to be said,
"Two wrongs don't make a right."
Oddly enough, in 2000, an Elliott
Institute survey of
164 pregnant rape victims found
that 73% of them chose to give birth.
In 1981, Dr. Sandra MacHorn conducted
research of 37
pregnant rape victims in the US.
75-85% chose to
give life to their children.
Rebecca Kiessling
was conceived in rape and is
grateful she was not
executed for her father's
crime.
She says, "Whenever you identify
yourself as being pro-choice, or whenever you make
that exception for rape, what that really
translates into is
you being able to stand
before me, look me in the eye and say to
me, I think your
mother should have been able
to abort you."