To be or not to be. That is the question.
Is it really though? Who really
decides who lives or dies? A good
answer to that comes from Exodus
20:13, "You shall not murder."
If that's true, then can aborting a baby ever be
just a matter of choice? More on this episode of
Creation Magazine LIVE!
[Music]
Welcome to Creation Magazine
LIVE, I'm Alexander Osborne...
... and I'm Thomas Bailey. On June 24th
2022 the U.S Supreme Court made a landmark
decision in the Dobbs versus Jackson Women's
Health Organization case. This overturned the
notorious Roe versus Wade decision of 1973
which had abolished all state abortion laws.
Roe basically invented the notion that abortion
was a constitutional right and for decades
pro-abortionists celebrated this decision.
But Dobbs has had pro-abortionists reacting
vehemently at what they considered
to be a loss of freedom for women.
Some Christians have said we should commiserate
with those who are hurting from this decision.
Rather, at CMI we commiserate with the
approximately 63 million babies that were
killed in the U.S. over 49 years, along with the
many mothers who have regretted their abortions.
Between 2010 and 2014 there were an estimated
56 million abortions per year worldwide. Here
in Canada there were approximately a hundred
thousand per year in the same time period.
Canada's number has come down a bit in recent
years but anything higher than zero is too many.
Yeah that's right. Pro-abortionists
tend to focus on a woman's right to
choose what happens inside her body
but this completely misses the point;
which is whether the pre-born baby is a human
being. If so then he or she also has rights.
It's mind-boggling to think that ending
a human life could be considered a
matter of personal choice, like
choosing a career, or dieting.
Let's put some of the pro-abortion arguments in
perspective by applying the 'two-year-old test'.
Whenever there's a reference to a 'fetus'
substitute 'two-year-old'. For example,
it's the right of every two-year-old to be wanted.
We're not pro-killing
two-year-olds, we're pro-choice.
Unless you're prepared to adopt this two-year-old
you have no right to tell the
mother she should not kill her.
If we don't make it possible for
the mother to kill her two-year-old
safely then she'll do it unsafely and
possibly put her own health in danger.
That sounds shocking but you can
see the logic why should killing
a pre-born baby be any less monstrous
than killing a toddler, a teenager,
or an adult? They're all human beings
at different stages of development.
Other arguments include that the
pre-born child is just a clump of
cells. Or that embryos pass through various
evolutionary stages on the way to becoming
human. By that logic one might be aborting
a fish, or a reptile rather than a human.
But that notion comes from a long discredited
evolutionary argument based on fraudulent
drawings by Ernst Haeckel. While this idea may
still show up in an occasional biology text,
or online video, most evolutionists
know it's completely false.
Even if it were true the notion that an
embryo can be aborted while it's in a
fish or reptile state implies that it
becomes more valuable when it reaches
human form. This runs contrary to evolution.
But what about the so-called clump of cells.
Even the first fertilized egg has its own
unique DNA code that's distinctly human
and different from both parents. So, not the
mother's body. This new life will follow these
pre-programmed instructions to grow and develop
into a human baby and eventually a full-grown
adult. Science has shown that birth changes
where the child is not what the child is.
Psalm 139:13-14 reads. "For you formed
my inward parts; you knitted me together
in my mother's womb. I praise you, for
I am fearfully and wonderfully made."
I love it when science catches up with the Bible.
Yeah me too. Secular pro-life is run
by three atheist women who wish to
advance secular arguments against abortion.
They outlined their argument as follows:
number one the human zygote, embryo,
and fetus are all human organisms;
they are early developmental
stages of a human's life cycle.
Two: all human organisms are morally relevant.
Three: it's generally immoral to kill humans.
And four: bodily rights aren't
enough to justify elective abortion.
In 2019 PhD candidate Steve Jacobs surveyed
thousands of biology professors and found
that 96 percent of them believe life
begins at conception out of the 5577
biologists surveyed 85 percent identified as
pro-choice and 63 percent as non-religious.
Now Jacobs wasn't trying to support the
pro-life position instead he found himself
trying to explain how so many biologists
could be pro-choice while acknowledging
life begins at conception. He wrote,
"Philosophers such as Peter Singer and
Judith Jarvis Thompson have outlined
abortion defenses that recognize a
fetus' humanity, while also rejecting
the argument that fetuses have rights."
We'll look at both of those arguments later.
If not everyone believes it's wrong to kill a
human being just because he or she is human there
must be more to it. We'll explore more after this.
[Music]
How do fish survive in Antarctic waters without
freezing? The answer is that their blood plasma
has lots of anti-freeze protein that bind to
ice and prevent the crystals from growing,
and thus causing damage. Some evolutionists
claim that this is an example of evolution
in action because new DNA code has been
created that codes for the antifreeze
protein. But does this really support
molecules to man evolution? Anti-freeze
proteins are quite different from the complex
specific proteins found elsewhere in the fish,
or in our own bodies. They are simple proteins
which may have arisen through the duplication of
a digestive enzyme gene that lost its original
function due to mutations scrambling it. Even
though they fortuitously prevent ice crystals from
growing this is a very non-specific job that many
different random proteins could perform.
So, even though antifreeze proteins help
fish survive they don't explain how complex
specific proteins could arise by mutations.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
[Music]
Welcome back. We've been talking about abortion,
and we'll get into more of the science later.
First let's explore why murder is wrong.
If your worldview says all living things evolve
by random processes over billions of years then
it's logical to conclude humans are no more
valuable than chimpanzees, trees, or insects.
For the humanist humans are the highest form of
life and deserve the greatest amount of respect.
But God is higher than all creation and only He
gets to decide what is morally right or wrong.
In Genesis 9:6 God says, "Whoever sheds the
blood of man, by man shall his blood be shed
for God made man in his own image." Humans
are created distinct from other creatures
and killing a human is particularly serious
because it involves destroying an image bearer.
But then there's the fuzzy concept of personhood.
Wait humans are fuzzy?
No, persons.
But wait, aren't humans
and persons the same thing?
Apparently not everyone no one thinks
so. Peter Singer professor of bioethics
at Princeton University wrote, "Human babies are
not born self-aware, or capable of grasping that
they exist over time. They are not persons.
But animals are self-aware, and therefore,
the life of a newborn is of less value than
the life of a pig, a dog or a chimpanzee.
That's ridiculous. The idea is that biology
determines humanity, but personhood determines
worth. However, it's always been dangerous
to question the personhood of certain human
beings. Such thinking has led to things like
slavery in the Holocaust. In fact, in Canada,
at one time women were denied the vote because
they were not considered persons either. Yet
ironically some of the folks currently denying
personhood to pre-born babies or women. Ouch.
That sounds harsh but consider a common
scenario: a woman finds out she's pregnant.
Pro-abortionists would say she alone can choose
to abort or not because it's her body. If she
decides to keep the baby studies indicate she'll
probably make healthy choices during pregnancy,
like abstaining from alcohol. Great! But is it for
her own health or is she taking her pre-born child
into consideration? Did anyone consider the child
when she was deciding whether or not to abort?
If not, what changed? Did the baby become a
person because he or she is wanted by the mother?
The right to choose is often considered to be
in line with feminism as it empowers women.
Or does it? Susan B Anthony's newsletter, "The
Revolution", described abortion as child murder,
infanticide and feticide. Anthony's
friend Elizabeth Katie Stanton argued,
"When you consider that women have been
treated as property, it is degrading to
women that we should treat our children as
property to be disposed of as we see fit."
In our time the organization
Feminists for Life asserts,
"Abortion is a reflection that we
have not met the needs of women."
And abortion is not as safe for the mother as
we've been told. There's a risk of heavy bleeding,
infection, autoimmune diseases, regret, and
depression. And the complication rate for
chemical abortions is four times higher
than for surgical ones. There are risks
in carrying a child to term, but studies show
that women who have abortions have a much higher
mortality rate than those who give birth. And,
of course, abortion is never safe for the child.
In some countries more female babies
are aborted than males. In Genesis
1:27 God created both male and
female in His image. But in an
evolutionized world why not regard
girls as inferior and abort them?
There's also a higher abortion rate among
babies with mental and physical challenges.
In the UK 9 out of 10 women choose
to abort their child once they find
out he or she might have Downs. Denmark
is attempting to eliminate Down syndrome
by abortion. This is eugenics in action,
an idea spawned by evolutionary thought.
Back to personhood apostate minister
Joseph Fletcher proposed personhood
requirements like minimum intelligence,
self-awareness, memory, and communication.
But at what stage does a child become self-aware?
What is minimum intelligence, and who decides? If
memory is a criteria many elderly people suffering
from dementia could be considered not persons.
What about communication? Is a deaf mute
individual not a person? How about pain?
A 2010 study in the UK concluded that
pre-born babies do not feel pain in the
first 24 weeks. Others have disputed
the findings, but even if it's true,
could we then justify killing
someone who is under anesthesia?
Someone might say the early embryo doesn't look
human. But it looks exactly the way a human
should look at that stage. If human appearance is
a factor well that would mean protecting babies at
15 weeks of gestation. This is where Dobbs comes
in. As Mississippi's Gestational Age Act states,
"Except in a medical emergency or in the case
of a severe fetal abnormality, a person shall
not intentionally or knowingly perform ... or
induce an abortion of an unborn human being if the
probable gestational age of the unborn human being
has been determined to be greater than 15 weeks."
It's interesting they refer to an
'unborn human being' at 15 weeks.
Now if we could just get them to have the same
acknowledgment from the moment of conception.
Amen! At 15 weeks a baby is about the
size of an apple, with all his or her
organs. Baby is kicking, curling toes,
and moving his or her arms. Just about
all pregnancy guide books and websites use
the term 'baby', or 'child' at this stage.
Let's go back even further. At four
weeks the baby's eyes and limbs are
developing and his or her heart
can be viewed on an ultrasound.
At eight weeks the baby has distinct facial
features and fingerprints are starting to form.
A 10 weeks baby's brain is growing rapidly,
producing almost 250 000 neurons every minute.
At week 12 the baby can smile
and gender is identifiable.
Yes, ladies and gentlemen, gender is biologically
identifiable even in the womb. Here's a 4D
ultrasound image of a baby at 20 weeks. It's
no wonder that abortion on demand after 20
weeks is allowed in very few countries. Babies as
young as 22 weeks can survive outside the womb.
Justice Samuel Alito made it clear they were not
taking a position on the nature of the unborn,
merely interpreting the Constitution. However
we can learn something from earlier laws.
English laws from the 13th to 18th century
condemned abortion. In the 19th century
almost all states made abortion a crime at all
stages. When Roe was imposed 30 States still
banned abortion for any reason except to save
the life of the mother. When the Dobbs decision
came down about 16 States had trigger laws in
place to restrict or ban abortion as soon as Roe
was overturned. Clearly many people in the U.S.
have and still do consider abortion to be wrong.
But let's see what the Bible says. In Exodus 21:
22-24 we read, "When men strive together and hit
a pregnant woman so that her children come out,
but there is no harm, the one who hit her shall
surely be fined, as the woman's husband shall
impose on him, and he shall pay as the judge is
determine. But if there is harm, then you shall
pay life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth,
hand for hand, foot for foot, burn for burn, wound
for wound, stripe for stripe." So there was an
additional penalty if an unborn child was harmed.
Note the term 'children', not clumps of cells.
In the late first century Christian work "Didache"
says, "The second commandment of the teaching:
You shall not murder. You shall not commit
adultery. You shall not seduce boys. You
shall not commit fornication. You shall not
steal. You shall not practice magic. You
shall not use potions. You shall not procure
an abortion, nor destroy a newborn child."
God considers the pre-born child to be human
and worthy of his attention. In Genesis 25:23
God tells Rebecca, "Two nations are in your womb,
and two peoples from within you shall be divided;
the one shall be stronger than the other,
the older shall serve the younger."
Later God says to Jeremiah, "Before I formed you
in the womb I knew you, and before you were born
I consecrated you; I appointed you a prophet to
the nations." When we come back we'll address some
more arguments used by pro-abortionists.
[Music]
What do marine fossils on the top of Mount
Everest tell us about the biblical flood? Well,
we find fossils of marine creatures in limestone
near the summit which means that this area must
have been under the sea in the past. Everyone
agrees that the top of Everest was once under
the sea. However, many people did not associate
these rocks and fossils with Noah's flood because
they think there is not enough water to
cover the highest mountains. However,
they are not considering how the flood changed
the Earth's topography. The mountain ranges
formed at the end of the flood, with vertical
Earth movements towards the end of the flood
the mountains rose and the water flowed off the
continents into the newly formed ocean basins.
Indeed such mountains must have formed quickly
and recently otherwise they would have eroded
as quickly as they formed. That's why we have
marine fossils at the top of high mountains.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com.
There are so many contradictions
and just bad arguments used to
try to support killing pre-born children.
Yeah but so many people have bought into them, and
the result is: innocent people are being killed.
Help us get this information out far
and wide by giving the video a like,
subscribing and sharing the
video on Twitter and Facebook.
The more interaction the video
gets by doing those things,
the more the algorithm suggested to others.
And if more people see it hopefully
it will result in fewer abortions.
There's more bad argumentation to
refute so let's get back to it.
Now that we've established pre-born
babies are human from conception,
let's focus on some of the other
arguments put forward by pro-abortionists.
Years ago Judith Jarvis Thompson put forward a
hypothetical scenario: Suppose you wake up in
a hospital to discover that because you have the
same rare blood type your circulatory system has
been connected to that of a famous violinist with
a serious kidney infection. The hospital claims
you are now morally compelled to stay connected
until the violinist can function independently,
at least nine months. Thompson asked whether
you would feel morally obliged to go along. Her
point is that the right to a life of one person
does not override the right of another person to
choose what happens to his or her body. She argues
that even if we grant the humanity of the unborn
baby she has no ethical or moral right to the
use of her mother's body to sustain her life.
It's actually not a very good argument.
Francis Beckwith pointed out some ethical
problems in his book, "Politically Correct Death".
Number one: Thompson's analogy assumes all moral
obligations to offspring are voluntary. But both
parents have involuntary obligations because they
had sex knowing it could result in pregnancy.
Number two: Thompson equates volunteerism
with family morality which involves personal
obligations to our offspring
which we don't have to others.
Number three: the pre-born child has
a right to the mother's body because
he or she is dependent on its mother at
this stage of development and there's
no reason to deny that right if the
child is a human, as Thompson allows.
Number four: abortion is not simply withholding
treatment but is actually the killing of the baby.
In the analogy there's no guarantee the violinist
will die. But abortion is intended to kill.
Thompson's point is that a woman should have
autonomy over her body and everything in it,
even another human being. By that logic
a woman could continue drinking alcohol
knowing that the baby could develop fetal alcohol
syndrome. Who knows why someone would do that,
but then, why would someone deliberately
have a baby chopped up and vacuumed?
Terrible things can happen when fallen human
beings are in charge. Consider that your body
is not your own. 1 Corinthians 6:19-20
says, "Or do you not know that your body
is a temple of the Holy Spirit within you,
whom you have from God? You are not your own,
for you were bought with a price.
So glorify God in your body."
Thompson's analogy implies that unwanted
pregnancies are always forced on a woman.
Only about one percent of abortion
decisions are the result of rape,
and only 0.5 percent are from incest.
The vast majority of women seeking an
abortion engaged in sex voluntarily. It's
estimated three out of four sexual assaults
are not reported but that that still
doesn't justify abortion on demand.
Please understand rape is a terrible and
violent assault that no woman should ever
have to go through. But in what other scenario
is it permissible for a victim of a crime to
retaliate against an innocent third party? If
someone beats you up in a parking lot no one
suggests you go and punch your neighbour's kid?
It used to be said two wrongs don't make a right.
Oddly enough in 2000 an Elliott Institute
survey of 164 pregnant rape victims found
that 73 percent of them chose to give birth.
In 1981 Dr Sandra Makhorn conducted research
of 37 pregnant rape victims in the U.S.. 75 to
85 percent chose to give life to their children.
Rebecca Kiessling was conceived in rape and is
grateful she was not executed for her father's
crime. She says, "Whenever you identify yourself
as being 'pro-choice', or whenever you make that
exception for rape, what that really translates
into is you being able to stand before me look
me in the eye and say to me, 'I think your
mother should have been able to abort you.'"
What about abortion to save the mother's life?
This comes up when and there is an ectopic
pregnancy, meaning that the fertilized
egg has implanted outside the uterus,
such as the fallopian tube. Keep in mind
this is not a normal healthy pregnancy.
It carries serious risk for the mother.
But removing the ectopic pregnancy is
not considered an abortion. However, it
is a genuine life for life situation.
In this case the death of the child is accidental,
not intended. Knowledge of consequences that will
result from committing an action is not the
same as intending those consequences. It's
sometimes even possible to save the child
with emergency C-section and incubation.
By contrast, the intent of an abortion
is always to produce a dead baby.
When we come back: do pro-lifers really care about
the child?
[Music]
Many people think that Charles Darwin first
thought of the idea of natural selection.
However, others prior to Darwin described the
concept, although they sometimes used slightly
different terminology. For instance, Carl
Linnaeus, the creationist father of taxonomy,
wrote of a struggle for survival in nature.
Similarly James Hutton wrote about the concept
of natural selection. Probably the most
influential character was Edward Blythe,
an English chemist and zoologist who wrote
major articles on natural selection two
decades before Darwin published On the Origin
of Species. Darwin differed in trying to use the
concept of natural selection to promote
the idea of unlimited change. However,
modern studies of natural selection have
revealed that it is limited: it can only
select between variations that already exist.
It is incapable of producing the new genetic
information required for true evolutionary change
to occur, such as growing feathers on a reptile.
Natural selection is not evolution. To find out
more from Creation Ministries International visit
our website creation.com
[Music]
Welcome back. We've examined various
aspects of the abortion issue and
answered several pro-abortion
arguments. Here's another one:
If you were really pro-life you'd pay for
the upkeep of the child until he or she
reaches 18. If you're not prepared to do that
then you have no right to oppose abortion.
There are several reasons why this
argument doesn't work. If you see a
child being abused by their parents
do you call the authorities only if
you're prepared to raise him or her
into adulthood? Just because we can't
adopt every unwanted child doesn't mean
we shouldn't try to save their lives.
But suppose pro-lifers really
don't care about babies after
they're born. Does that mean it's
okay to let them be slaughtered?
Uh no. It's also rather melodramatic
and manipulative to say that anyone
who doesn't actively support a child's
welfare after birth must want that child
dead. If someone comes to your door asking for
donations for cancer research and you decline
does that mean you want everyone
with cancer to die? Of course not.
And the idea that pro-lifers are pro-birth
only is not even true. Pro-lifers are at the
forefront of care for mothers and babies. In
the U.S pro-life pregnancy counseling centers
outnumber Planned Parenthood abortion mills
over three to one. Yet those centers receive
little to no government funding while Planned
Parenthood receives 500 million dollars a year.
A pro-abortion group called Action Canada for
Sexual Health and Rights has complained that in
Canada there are more crisis pregnancy centers
than abortion providers including hospitals.
Sounds great! This group has
claimed that crisis pregnancy
centers are giving out false information.
But they haven't offered any real proof.
One objection they have is that some
of these centers offer ultrasounds
which they say can trick people into
believing they're a medical facility.
A gas station has an ATM but
no one mistakes it for a bank.
But an ultrasound could help a woman
realize her baby is not just a clump
of cells. That's right. And that may affect
your decision. Maybe that's the real objection.
One research paper indicated that pregnant
women who visit crisis pregnancy centers are
20 percent less likely to choose abortion than
those who don't. The study authors suggested
that this must be at least partly because
the centers lie to people. For example,
Naral Pro-choice America conducted an
undercover investigation in which they said,
"More than 67 percent of the locations
intentionally referred to the fetus as
baby and told our investigator she
was already a mother because she was
already pregnant." That's certainly a pro-life
perspective but it's also factually accurate.
Most pregnancy centers are upfront about
what services they do and do not provide.
The name alone 'Pregnancy Center' should
be a clue that their focus is on pregnancy
non-abortions. Oddly enough many offer
counseling for those who do choose an
abortion even though they don't perform them.
Meanwhile, it's been suggested that other
organizations tend to give the impression
that abortion is the only option. It's not.
Adoption is a great alternative for any
mother who feels unprepared to raise a
child but wants the child to live a happy
life. There are more couples wanting to
adopt than there are babies available. But
government bureaucracy makes it difficult.
Since Dobbs some corporations have started
offering to fly pregnant employees to states
where abortion is legal since it's cheaper than
paid maternity leave. Planned Parenthood doesn't
offer paid parental leave to its employees.
Perhaps they consider it a conflict of interest.
Wouldn't it be wonderful if governments and
employers put as much money into options that
help struggling moms look after their babies
as they do in helping them eliminate them?
We live in a sin-cursed world with
all kinds of problems like poverty,
and hunger. But we'll have a better
chance of combating those problems
if there are more bright young
minds around to work on them.
That's right. The unfounded accusation
that pregnancy centers give out false
information has given the government of
Canada an excuse to try and shut down
these centers. For a government
that calls itself pro-choice it's
odd that they would pursue measures that
would give pregnant women fewer choices.
It gets worse pro-abortion terrorist groups such
as Jane's Revenge have bombed and vandalized
some of these centers with slogans like, 'If
abortions aren't safe, then neither are you.'
For such groups the objective
is very clearly abortion rather
than care for the mother or the unwanted child.
Very sad. Some say it's all about a woman's right
to choose. But no one, man or woman, has the right
to end a human life. Laws are often designed to
restrict our choices from harming others. Laws
against drunk driving are meant to protect others
from possibly getting hurt, whereas abortion
always hurts a child, and sometimes the mother.
And most laws are based on a Biblical worldview.
But if evolution is true then there's no God, so
no objective moral authority. Instead anything
goes. Things like slavery and genocide become
a matter of choice. We might as well empty the
prisons and shut down the courts. Instead
we pray that everyone will come to realize
that pre-born babies are human and that
God loves them as well as their parents.
That's right much of the content for
this episode came from articles at
creation.com Visit the website there
and check out the many free articles
there. As well as you can get a free
magazine at creation.com/free-mag
And we'd love to hear from you. You can go
to the feedback section on our website and
you can submit a question, if you don't
find what you're looking for on the site.
We'll see you next week and remember,
Christianity is an evidence-based faith,
And science supports Scripture.
Wait wait don't go just yet. If you learn
something from this episode then others will too.
Share this video as widely as you can. And
if you haven't yet, click that like button
Leave a comment about what you found most
interesting or respond to other comments.
Those activities help push the video to
other people's feeds. Thanks for watching.