In 2019, PhD candidate Steve Jacobs
surveyed thousands of
biology professors and found
that 96% of them
believed life begins at conception.
Out of the 5,577 biologists surveyed, 85%
identified as
pro-choice and 63% as non-religious.
Now Jacobs wasn't trying
to support the pro-life position.
Instead, he found
himself trying to explain
how so many
biologists could be pro-choice
while acknowledging
life begins at conception.
He wrote,
"Philosophers such as Peter Singer
and Judith Jarvis
Thompson have outlined abortion
defenses that
recognize a fetus's humanity
while also rejecting
the argument that fetuses
have rights."
First, let's explore why murder is wrong.
If your worldview says all living things
evolved by random
processes over billions of years,
then it's logical to conclude humans
are no more valuable than chimpanzees, trees,
or insects.
For the humanist, humans are the highest
form of life and
deserve the greatest amount of
respect.
But God is higher than all creation, and
only He gets to
decide what is morally right or
wrong.
In Genesis 9.6, God says, "Whoever
sheds the blood of man by man shall his blood be
shed, for God made man in his own image."
Humans are created distinct from other
creatures, and killing a
human is particularly serious
because it involves
destroying an image-bearer.
But then there's the
fuzzy concept of personhood.
Wait, humans are fuzzy?
No, persons.
But wait, aren't
humans and persons the same thing?
Apparently, not everyone thinks so.
Peter Singer, professor of bioethics at
Princeton University,
wrote, "Human babies are not
born self-aware or capable of
grasping that they exist over time.
They are not persons.
But animals are self-aware, and therefore
the life of a
newborn is of less value than
the life of a pig,
a dog, or a chimpanzee."
That's ridiculous.
The idea is that biology determines
humanity, but personhood determines worth.
However, it's always been dangerous to
question the
personhood of certain human beings.
Such thinking has led to
things like slavery and the Holocaust.
In fact, in
Canada, at one time women were
denied the vote
because they were not considered
persons either.
Yet, ironically, some of the folks
currently denying
personhood to pre-born babies are
women.
Ouch.
That sounds harsh, but
consider a common scenario.
A woman finds out she's pregnant.
Pro-abortionists would say she alone can
choose to abort or
not because it's her body.
If she decides to keep the baby, studies
indicate she'll
probably make healthy choices during
pregnancy, like abstaining from alcohol.
Great.
But is it for her own health, or is she
taking her pre-born
child into consideration?
Did anyone consider the child when
she was deciding whether or not to abort?
If not, what changed?
Did the baby become a person
because he or she is wanted by the mother?