A reason often given for belief in evolution
is the apparent similarity between apes,
especially chimpanzees, and humans. What
do the latest scientific discoveries in
genetics tell us about this supposed
similarity? Do these findings support
the theory of evolution, or what the Bible
teaches? Today on Creation Magazine LIVE!
Welcome to Creation Magazine
LIVE, I'm Alexander Osborne
and I'm Thomas Bailey. In the 1970s
work began to compare the similarity
between chimps and humans in an
effort to support human evolution.
But it isn't enough to compare the morphology,
that is, the form and appearance, legs, arms,
face, and so on, a comparison really needs to
be made at the level of the genes and the DNA.
Based on early work comparing DNA a proponent of
evolution, Richard Dawkins, claimed that chimps
and humans are nearly identical at the genetic
level. In his book, "The Blind Watchmaker",
published in 1986, Dawkins claimed that humans
share 99 percent of our genes with chimps.
Dawkins claim of near identical genetic overlap
between chimps and humans was later called,
'the myth of the one percent', by John Cohen,
an evolutionary biologist in an article that
appeared in the journal "Science" in 2007.
Why was it a myth? There are quite a few
reasons. Firstly we'll need to realize
that his claim wasn't based on a letter by
letter comparison of the two sets of genetic
information. The technology to do that kind
of comparison didn't exist until the 1990s.
And even today it's challenging
to compare two long sequences
of DNA. Nevertheless a claimed
overlap of 98.5 percent became
the 'gold standard' among evolutionary
researchers and in the popular media.
But we now know that the original work comparing
chimp and human DNA had serious
flaws. Let's consider a few.
Number one: the first comparisons
between chimp and human genes used
only small snippets of DNA where it was
assumed that overlap would be found.
Let's use an analogy to understand
the issue. Pretend that you have
two different thousand piece puzzles and
you want to know how similar they are.
If you match the blue pieces together
you will find almost exact matches in
shape and color between some of
the pieces from the two puzzles.
But that isn't right. You have only
compared a small portion of the pieces.
So that's not a good indicator
of how similar the puzzles are.
And that is the problem. One study compared 97
protein coding sections of chimp DNA. But they're
more than 234 000 protein coding sections
in human DNA. So that's the first issue.
Number two, is that researchers didn't consider
major portions of the DNA
which they call junk DNA.
So-called 'junk DNA' is part of the DNA
supposedly left over from long ages of
evolutionary processes. But we now know
that there is no such thing as junk DNA.
So true. Recent studies have shown that the
areas of DNA between genes guide numerous,
complex regulatory functions. For example,
controlling the extraction of information
from genes for the creation of proteins.
Number three: it was discovered that the original
samples of chimp DNA were
contaminated with human DNA.
Wow! So there's evolutionary bias affecting
how the experiments are set up,
and now there's shoddy science.
Right. Even a breath of a lab
assistant can carry DNA and mix
with the sample being analyzed. This is
like someone mixing blue pieces from two
separate puzzles and comparing them to a
picture of one of the original puzzles.
Today proper DNA decoding requires
that rigorous clean room procedures
be followed. But the problem is even
worse. The fourth flaw in the research is:
an entire set of genetic information for
chimps didn't yet exist. So it was assumed
that the chimp DNA samples could be mapped
to portions of the human genetic information.
Think of the puzzles again. Let's say that
one puzzle, once complete, will show children
playing ball in the park under a blue sky with
puffy clouds. But you don't have the original
box with the picture, so you don't know yet what
the completed picture is supposed to look like.
But since there are lots of blue pieces
is you assume that they're for sky. So
you take out a different puzzle box
that has a picture of a blue sky with
puffy clouds but they're are over a
snow-capped mountain with forests.
Hold on! We know that using the
picture of the second puzzle as
a guide is not going to help
us assemble the first puzzle.
Yup, but that's what the original
researchers did. They assumed that
chimp DNA would be like the human
DNA when they made their comparisons.
So the original study that claimed a 98.5
percent overlap between chimps and humans
used a biased assumption the researchers assumed
that chimps and humans share a common set of DNA.
And that assumption was based on the belief that
chimps and humans evolved from a common ancestor.
That was quite a while ago. Let's
look at how things stand today.
A complete map of common human DNA
only became available recently. The
Human Genome Project was launched in 1998, but the
goal of providing data on the complete
genome wasn't achieved until May 2021.
That's a long time.
That is a long time. It took over 20
years of massive investment, effort,
and the participation of many countries and
labs to identify the core human DNA. And even
now the human genome information database
is being refined, corrected and updated.
A fully complete map of chimp DNA
doesn't exist yet. But a working
version became available only in 2018.
And as we'll see recent scientific work
indicates that humans are a completely
different kind of creature from any ape.
There's no support in the DNA for the claim
that chimps and humans evolved from a common
ancestor. Rather, an analysis of DNA supports
what the Bible states. In Genesis 1:24-25 God
tells us that he created land animals, which
included apes, by their kinds and then God
created human beings as an entirely separate
creation, as we read in Genesis 1:26-27.
Paul confirms this difference when he
states, "For not all flesh is the same,
but there is one kind for humans, another for
animals, another for birds, and another for fish."
After the break we'll let you know
how researchers arrived at today's
percentage match between chimps and humans.
Helium gas is renowned for its ability to diffuse
through materials quickly. Why is it then, that
we find an abundance of helium in certain rock
crystals that it has not managed to escape from
them? This has significant implications for the
dating of rocks using radioactive decay. That's
because helium is formed when some radioisotopes
decay. And, therefore, lots of helium suggests
lots of decay has occurred. Moreover, if lots
of decay has occurred it also suggests that the
rock is very old. However, nuclear physicist Dr
Russell Humphreys realized that lots of helium
trapped in the rock crystals that had not had
time to diffuse out means that the rocks were
actually young. Dr Humphreys concluded that
nuclear decay rates must have been dramatically
faster in the recent past. And that is why rocks
that are actually only thousands of years old
are commonly wrongly dated using radioisotope
decay as millions or billions of years old.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Earlier this century published reports based
on using advanced genetic decoding technology,
at the time, suggested that the overlap between
chimp and human DNA was around 98.5 percent.
That figure was wrong mostly because of
the four issues surrounding the research
that we just mentioned we have better
data today to use for a comparison.
That's right. In the past 10 years DNA
sequencing has advanced significantly,
enough to allow scientists to do a more
detailed comparison of chimp and human DNA.
Also scientists have begun
to create, from scratch,
the sequence of chimp DNA. Focusing
on their observations will hopefully
get around their assumption that it will be
similar to human DNA. And, sure enough, the
latest detailed decoding of chimp and human DNA
shows that the supposed 98.5 overlap is way off.
A report was published in 2018 by Richard
Buggs, professor of evolutionary genomics
at the University of London. He used the
new chimp genome data for comparison to the
human genome and his report created significant
discussion among geneticists because it stated,
"The percentage of nucleotides in the human genome
that had one-to-one exact matches in the
chimpanzee genome was 84.38 percent."
Whoa! That's quite different from 98.5.
Now some folks might not recognize the
word nucleotides used in the sentence
displayed. We'd better define that.
A nucleotide is a basic building block of DNA.
A nucleotide is composed of three molecules:
a phosphate, a sugar, for example, ribose,
and a variable nitrogen-based molecule. There
are four different types of nucleotides.
Think of nucleotides like alphabetic letters.
The four nucleotides are combined to make
words. Words are combined into sentences and
chapters, which are genes, and other DNA used
for regulating the operation of cells as they
manufacture new proteins and other molecules.
The human genome has about 3 billion nucleotides.
About the 2018 report you mentioned,
published by the evolutionist Richard Buggs,
it's significant that an independent
comparison of chimp to human DNA was
done recently by Jeffrey Tompkins. He earned
a PhD in genetics from Clemson University in
1996 and worked in the department of genetics
and biochemistry at Clemson. Tompkins used a
different method than bugs for comparing the
two sets of DNA and reports that he, "aligned 18
000 random pieces of high-quality chimp DNA
that were each on average 30 544 letters
long onto the human genome and several
different versions of the chimp genome."
He states that the aligned segments
of chimp DNA were on average only
84.4 percent identical to human
DNA, basically the same as Buggs.
Interesting, two different
approaches and similar results.
Yes. It can't be a coincidence that
Buggs and Tompkins independently,
using different methods of analysis, both identify
the degree of overlap to be around 84 percent.
So the original overlap proclaimed
by Dawkins of 98.5 percent is not
close to reality. As our knowledge about human and
chimp DNA has improved the degree of
possible genetic overlap has declined.
This raises an issue for those who believe
that chimps and humans evolved from a common
ancestor who lived a few million years
ago. That is, if there are three billion
nucleotides in the human genome then we can
estimate that 450 million nucleotides would
have been added or changed, for example
through mutations, if evolution occurred.
But that's absurd. It's impossible
that that that many changes wouldn't
have introduced serious genetic defects which
would have destroyed the evolving life forms.
Correct. Even a single mutation in DNA
can destroy the operation of molecular
machinery or create deadly genetic
diseases. And we'll talk more about
mutation rates in a few minutes and
the associated problems for evolution.
The more we learn about the complexity
of DNA, the more we realize that random
changes at the letter level are unlikely to
produce positive changes in how cells operate.
So for evolution to be considered
even remotely possible the gap in
the genetic overlap between chimps and
humans must be one percent or less. But
as recent studies have shown, the
gap is at least 10 times larger.
Let's pause for a moment.
Maybe you're wondering about
that 84 overlap and thinking, why is it that high?
God is an expert designer. He uses different
molecular components in multiple life forms.
God uses good design design features
modifying them slightly for use in
different creatures. For example, the
five digit or five finger design is
common in many creatures but modified.
It points to a single common designer.
If every animal was completely, totally different,
with no similarities, it would suggest
multiple designers, wouldn't it?
As we noted earlier, there are similarities
in the morphology, that is, the form between
chimps and humans. Both have two legs,
two arms, eyes, ears, teeth, and so on.
So, the underlying genes to produce similar
morphologies will likely be similar.
Another example: the protein molecule hemoglobin,
used to carry oxygen around our
bodies, is found in most animal forms,
and even in some plants. Thus the genes
that code for hemoglobin will be similar.
So we shouldn't be surprised
to find some overlap at the
nucleotide level where a protein
appears in more than one life form.
Absolutely. God knew what he was doing when
he designed the building blocks of life.
However the possible 84 four percent
overlap doesn't account for other
significant differences between chimps
and humans. These differences make it
impossible that chimps and humans
evolved from a common ancestor.
Let's consider some of the most significant
differences: orphan genes, chromosome count
differences, Y chromosome differences, gene
function differences, epigenetic differences.
In most higher level kinds of life there
are genes that may not be found in any
other life form. These are referred to
as orphan genes. These genes provide
information for creating unique proteins that
are needed by a particular group of organisms.
Comparisons have been made between the
genomes of chimps and humans. One 2011
study reported that there are 584 genes
found in humans that are not part of the
genomes for any primate family,
that is, apes, including chimps.
These genes are used to create specialized tissue
found only in humans. For example, orphan genes
code for proteins found in our brains, hearts,
livers, lymph nodes, lungs, male testes.
The existence of orphan genes is clear
evidence that animals and humans didn't
evolve from primitive kinds but they were
created fully formed during the creation week.
When we return we'll consider a few other
serious issues with the evolutionary
paradigm and the idea that chimps and
humans evolved from a common ancestor.
Evolutionists have long proposed that
nearly all our DNA 98 percent is junk,
that it has no function whatsoever. They claimed
this because evolution needs lots of junk DNA
for three reasons. Firstly, there are far too many
mutations which would cause our extinction, but if
nearly all of them occurred in junk DNA then they
are less of a problem. Secondly, if mutations,
accidental changes created us, then accidents
cannot create DNA with 100 function. This would
be unbelievable. Thirdly, if mutations created
us they must have occurred in lots of DNA that
had no function to allow lots of experimentation
without damaging the existing functions. However,
modern science reveals that nearly all our DNA
has a function, and this is a huge problem for
evolution. Creationist scientists doubted the
junk DNA idea all along. Although, because we
live in a fallen world they expected to find some
damaged DNA that might appear to be junk, but not
much. To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Today’s topic is an update on old information.
Yeah, and the old information convinced
people that evolution was true.
Help us get this information out far
and wide by giving the video a like,
subscribing, and sharing the
video on Twitter and Facebook.
The more interaction the video
gets by doing those things,
the more the algorithms suggest it to others…
…and if more people see it
…the more people will learn that humans and chimps
actually did not evolve from a common
ancestor, but were created by God.
There’s more, great, Bible-upholding
information coming so let’s get back to it.
On this week's episode we're
considering a claim made by
Richard Dawkins that chimps and humans are
99 percent identical at the genetic level.
Since he made that claim advances in decoding
chimp and human genomes demonstrate that the
genetic overlap is, at best, 84.4 percent, a
figure confirmed by two independent studies.
In addition, we considered a difference
which undermines the claim that chimps
and humans have a common ancestor: the
existence of hundreds of genes which
produce unique proteins in humans,
such as ones found in our brains.
Another challenge for the evolutionary
claim of common descent is the fact that
chimps and humans have a different number of
chromosomes. A chromosome is a package of genes,
like chapters in a book, where the book represents
the information in the entire genome. In the
human genome there are 22 base chromosomes shared
between males and females which contain an average
of about a thousand of the twenty thousand
protein encoding genes identified to date.
In addition there is a sex chromosome which
is different in males and females. Each base
chromosome is paired with a copy from each
parent. This pairing helps to eliminate
defective genes if there has been a mutation
in one of the pairs inherited from our parents.
Also, males have two different sex chromosomes
labeled X and Y females have
two identical X chromosomes.
So humans have a total of 23 pairs
of chromosomes for a total of 46.
Classes of animals have different numbers
of chromosomes and genes. For example,
donkeys have 62 chromosomes, and sheep have 54.
Chimpanzees and gorillas have 48 chromosomes.
Evolutionists have theories for how the 48
was reduced to 46 during mankind's supposed
journey from an ape-like ancestor. One
theory is called chromosome fusion.
Yes, but there's no empirical evidence showing how
this could have occurred without
destroying and evolving creature.
Slight problem! And chromosome has never been
found in normal, healthy cells but does appear
in cancerous cells, which generally leads
to serious, life-threatening conditions.
The difference in the number
of chromosomes between chimps
and humans is a real challenge for
evolutionists to explain. Another
challenge is the difference between
the male human and chimp Y chromosome.
Right. When scientists compared the
Y chromosomes they find significant
differences. One paper published in 2010,
in the science journal Nature, was entitled,
"Chimpanzee and Human Y Chromosomes are Remarkably
Divergent in Structure and Gene Content".
The geneticist Tompkins, commenting on this
paper, stated, "It becomes painfully obvious
that there is no evolutionary relationship
between chimps and humans that could have
possibly arisen over three to six million
years of speculated naturalistic processes."
If chimps and humans had evolved from a common
ancestor their Y chromosomes should be the most
similar since the gene means in the Y chromosome
are the most stable, having the least variation.
Another challenge for evolution.
That's not all there are more challenges.
There are differences between chimps
and humans that we mentioned earlier:
gene function and epigenetics. First,
recent research shows that genes have complex
interactions with other genes. These genes
work together to produce the developing
embryo. For example, a study in 2017
identified at least two genes that interact
to produce different skin colors in humans.
Second, cells receive epigenetic
information, that is, information above
the genes from outside the womb that affects
the development of the embryo. For example,
cells in a developing human can receive
information about atmospheric pressure
and make adaptations such as in the
lungs for living at high altitudes.
Amazing. The capabilities encoded
in DNA indicate that DNA comes from
the mind of the creator of life, and
we should declare with the psalmist,
"How great are your works, O Lord!
Your thoughts are very deep!"
Amen. There's yet another problem we
should address briefly: genetic entropy.
Right. Although genetic entropy doesn't deal with
genetic differences between chimps
and humans, it is important for any
consideration of the idea that chimps and
humans evolved from a common ancestor.
After Adam sinned death and decay
entered the world. Since then the
human genome has been decaying. Mutations
are being introduced into the genome with
every generation at an estimated
rate of 200 to 300 per generation.
Many of these mutations at the nucleotide
level are minor, like spelling mistakes,
and have no apparent effect on subsequent
generations. That's because God designed
DNA with error correction processes
that are applied during genome copying.
But some of these mutations cause
genetic diseases. There are over six
thousand known genetic diseases carried by
humans which can be transmitted to children.
Well-known serious ones include:
color blindness, cystic fibrosis,
Down's syndrome, muscular dystrophy, hemophilia,
sickle-cell anemia, and Tay Sachs disease.
Very sad conditions. Even lactose
intolerance can be a result of a
genetic defect, although it can
also be environmentally induced.
Dr John Sanford a retired professor of genetics
at Cornell University, with over 80 scientific
publications and 30 patents, has indicated
that the human genome is decaying.
Right. In about 300 generations from Adam
humans will not be able to produce viable
offspring. That's serious there have
been about 200 generations since Adam.
Because of genome decay it wouldn't be possible
for humans to have evolved from an ape-like
creature over two million years. The human
genome is deteriorating much too quickly.
Over that immense time thousands of
generations would have passed and so many
deleterious mutations would have accumulated
that humans and chimps wouldn't exist.
Let's not forget that the most significant
difference between chimps and humans isn't
in their genetics but that they
were created as entirely separate
creatures on the sixth day. And we'll
be back with more after a short break.
Did you know that the DNA code is itself governed
by another code known as the epigenetic code?
This physical and chemical code determines
which genes are switched on. Changes in this
code can greatly alter an organism without
altering one letter of its DNA. For instance,
scientists have managed to change the coat color
in mice by feeding them a diet that switches off
certain genes. Epigenetics poses new problems for
evolution. For instance, a group of animals with
a camouflaged coat color might be favored in a
particular environment. But if this coat color
is due to epigenetics and not the actual DNA
code then the non-camouflaged animals would be
selected against in vain. When the epigenetic
modification is reset by a diet change natural
selection is sent back to square one. The field
of epigenetics therefore creates problems for
evolution and strongly points to a Master
programmer who invented the DNA and epigenetic
codes. To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
On Creation Magazine LIVE this
week we've been considering the
significant differences between chimps and humans.
Even though their morphology appears
similar they are completely different
classes of creation that God placed on the earth.
We have considered recent scientific evidence
derived from studies conducted on the
genetic codes for chimps and humans.
The evidence indicates that there is no way that
modifications of the genetic information of a
supposed common ancestor between chimps
and humans could have produced the two
forms of life that we see today. Even if these
changes were to occur over millions of years.
So this recent scientific evidence destroys one
of the supposed supporting pillars of evolution
which was popularized by the writings
of Charles Darwin in the 19th century.
Darwin made a bold challenge in his book, "On
the Origin of the Species", "If it could be
demonstrated that any complex organ existed which
could not possibly have been formed by numerous,
successive, slight modifications, my
theory would absolutely break down."
But Darwin made this challenge in ignorance.
Yeah, let's consider some of
the things about the nature
of living entities that Darwin knew nothing about.
First he didn't understand genetics.
He published his book in 1859. Gregor
Mendel was doing his genetic
inheritance studies breeding
garden peas from 1856 to 1863 and
published his results in 1865.
Yeah, but his work was largely
ignored until about 1900.
Too bad. Second, Darwin had no clue about
cell complexity. Along with most scientists
of his day he thought that a cell was
simply an amorphous mass of protoplasm.
Today largely from recent research we know
that cells are highly complex factories for
producing the organic molecules that support
living entities. Each cell is far more
complex than any machine that humans
have designed or constructed so far.
Third Darwin didn't know about DNA
yeah it wasn't until the 1950s,
a hundred years after Darwin published
his book, that James Watson and Francis
Crick used advanced x-ray technologies to
decode the double helix structure of DNA
and began to expose the amazing amount
of genetic information stored in DNA.
So if Darwin had known what we know
today about the genetic complexity
which underlies living things he couldn't
have presented the challenge that any organ
could have been formed by numerous
successive slight modifications.
Right. It's impossible that the complexity in the
human body with over 200 different types of cells
and over 30 000 total genes could have arisen by
slight modifications from primitive life forms.
Chance mutations in DNA which supposedly diversify
and improve the fitness of living entities simply
don't occur. Rather, mutations cause the
loss or destruction of genetic robustness.
Many people today have been taught to believe
that all the life forms we see today are the
results of evolutionary processes that started
with a single-celled entity, and over a billion
years developed into complex multicellular
life. That's biblical and scientific naivete.
But they display the same naivete about the
complexity of the building blocks of life
that Darwin did. They simply don't understand how
much information is stored in the human genome.
The information in DNA is used to manufacture the
proteins and other molecules
used throughout our bodies.
But DNA amazingly also includes instructions
for creating different kinds of cells and
building the molecular machines which operate
inside of the cells, and the instructions for
operating the cellular machines. Without
doubt DNA declares: "Made by God".
What we've considered in this week's
episode confirms what the psalmist declares,
"I praise you, for I am fearfully and wonderfully
made. Wonderful are your works;
my soul knows it very well."
Amen. Much of the latest scientific
information presented in today's
episode has been derived from Jeffrey
Tompkins book, "Chimps and Humans A
Geneticist Discovers DNA Evidence that
Challenges Evolution", published in 2022.
If you want to explore the topics
we've considered today in more detail,
in particular how recent studies in
genetics support what the Bible declares,
you can access a large repository of articles
and media posted on our website creation.com
You can also purchase resources which
relate to the topics we've considered
today including "Dismantled - A Scientific
Deconstruction of the Theory of Evolution"
by two scientists Dr Robert Carter and Dr John
Sanford. Available as a DVD or via streaming.
"Genetic entropy" by the geneticist Dr John
Sanford. We mentioned this book earlier.
"The Mystery of our Declining Genes"
is a video of a talk given by Dr John
Sanford dealing with genetic entropy. It
is available as a DVD or via streaming.
"The Stairway To Life - An Origin of Life
Reality Check", by Change Laura Tan and Rob
Stadler. Tan received a PhD in Biochemistry
from the University of Pennsylvania and did
postdoctoral training in genetics at Harvard
Medical School. Stadler received a PhD in
medical engineering from the Harvard MIT
division of Health Sciences and Technology.
A description of the book on
our website creation.com states,
"From recently acquired insights into the
complexity of the simplest organisms Tan and
Stadler specify requirements for spontaneous
formation of life and evaluate the prospects
for natural processes to satisfy these
requirements. The Stairway To Life is a
thought-provoking inquiry that breaches the
final stronghold of spontaneous generation."
As we have demonstrated today, the Bible-believing
Christian, the person who not only believes
God's word, but uses it as a basis for their
worldview, how they view the world around them,
will find that facts of science beautifully fit
with Scripture and the Genesis creation account.
That's one of the reasons I love being
a Christian. With the Bible as the
foundation of our thinking observations
from science make sense. For example,
we read, "And God said, 'Let the earth
bring forth living creatures according
to their kinds - livestock and creeping
things and beasts of the earth according
to their kinds.' And it was so ... Then
God said, 'Let us make man in our image,
after our likeness." Humans and apes have
a common designer, not a common ancestor.
We'd love to hear from you. If this
show has helped you to understand more
about how the facts of science support the Bible,
drop us a note in the feedback section of
our website. Again, that's creation.com and
remember Christianity is an evidence-based
faith and science supports Scripture.
Wait, wait, wait, don’t go
just yet. If you learned
something from this episode, then others will too.
Share this video as widely as you can and,
if you haven’t yet, click that like button.
Leave a comment about what you found most
interesting, or respond to other comments.
Those activities help push the video to
other people’s feeds. Thanks for watching!