We said before that it’s generally agreed
that the greenhouse effect of a doubling of atmospheric CO2
means the temperature rises about 1.1 degrees Celsius.
So at the current rates it’ll take about 200 years to double the CO2 concentration
resulting in another 1.1 degrees. So, what’s the big deal?
The big deal is because climate models include positive feedback, or amplification,
mostly from increased water vapor as a result of warming oceans.
The idea is that for the 1.1 degree of warming caused by a CO2 increase alone
the ECS, or Equilibrium Climate Sensitivity,
would result in a total increase of between 1.5 and 4.5 degrees.
Okay.
Okay, so how do the climate models compare with the observations?
Predicting future temperature is difficult.
Even the IPCC noted in 2001,
“The climate system is a coupled non-linear chaotic system,
and therefore the long-term prediction of future climate states is not possible.”
Ah, yeah, but they went ahead anyway.
Using over a hundred different models.
So if the science is settled, as we often hear,
all you need is one.
Yeah that should do it.
The one based on science.
This graph shows the many predictions from 102 models.
The black line represents the average.
Notice all of the actual readings from three different satellites: the green, red, and blue lines.
The actual data is much lower than any of the 102 models predicted,
even though CO2 levels went up. There’s a fail.
No kidding. The models are simply wrong.
But wait,
There’s more prediction failures.
Model predictions for ocean temperatures were also wrong.
This graph shows the models in red compared to the actual data from over 3,000 robotic instruments
floating all over the oceans, from 2004 to 2012.
Another fail.
If positive feedback occurs from increased water vapor
there should be an atmospheric hot spot in the middle lattitudes at the tropics.
Okay.
Again, note the models in red versus actual data from satellites and weather balloons.
None of the data showed any hot spots. Fail again!
I’m seeing a pattern here, right?
Let’s keep going.
Increased water vapor is supposed to trap more of the incoming solar radiation
so more warming.
As sea surface temperature rises there should be less outgoing radiation from the Earth
but satellite measurements show outgoing radiation is increasing;
the opposite of IPCC predictions.
Yet another fail!
The data shows positive feedback isn’t operating.
No.
In fact there is strong evidence for negative feedback
probably resulting from enhanced cloud cover reflecting the sun’s radiation back into space.
When negative feedback is taken into consideration
the warming effect of doubling atmospheric CO2 is only about 0.5 degrees Celsius.
Nowhere near the 4.5 degrees that some have predicted.
Similarly a comprehensive study from a German company arrived at an ECS of 0.7 degrees
and they also concluded that negative feedbacks more than offset positive feedback.
So you know the bottom line here is:
we don’t need drastic action to stay within the 1.5 degree target.