When talking about climate change who is to
blame? Is it corporations, people in general,
or is it Christians? Is climate change even
an issue? ... today on Creation Magazine Live
Welcome to Creation Magazine Live, I’m Thomas
Bailey, and I’m Alexander Osborne. Last week we
started talking about climate change, summarizing
some of the points in a massive article entitled,
"A Biblical and Scientific Approach to
Climate Change", by Dr Don Batten who leads
our Australian office. Many bible-believing
scientists and researchers contributed to it.
We examined some of the data and we
looked at the influence of world views.
We discovered there are neo-Marxist
goals behind some of the climate agenda
and we looked at many failed
predictions of climate models.
Despite all of this we still hear that 97% of
scientists agree that man-made CO2 will cause
catastrophic warming. The underlying question
is can the majority of scientists be wrong?
Well actually, they can be, and they have
been many times in the past. Consensus science
isn't science. Science often progresses when one
scientist makes a new discovery that overturns the
consensus. But ignoring the history of science
for a moment, is there really 97% agreement?
See that figure comes from a 2013 paper that
examined abstracts of nearly 12 000 climate
science papers from 1991 to 2011. The conclusion
was that 97% of those who expressed an opinion
endorsed the idea that humans are causing global
warming. Based on that former President Obama’s
twitter account said, "97% of scientists agree
climate change is real, man-made and dangerous."
Dangerous? It sounds like it was
exaggerated a little bit. Yeah,
just a bit. The tweet was actually posted by
an activist group called Organizing for Action,
and the study was done by members of another
activist group, Skeptical Science. The study's
authors admitted only 64 of the nearly
12 000 papers claimed most of the warming
is caused by humans. Other researchers
found only 41 of the papers made such claim.
Two-thirds of the papers expressed no view
on the subject, which means less than one
percent of the papers that did express
a view claimed most warming is man-made.
So how did 1% become 97%? From the papers
expressing a view the study authors accounted
all views that man-made greenhouse gases are
causing some warming. But this is virtually
meaningless. Most global warming skeptics agree to
some warming. So the 97% is a dishonest statistic,
but it's gotten a lot of press. What's less known
is the growing number of scientists who disagree.
They're often treated like those who disagree
with evolution, right? Climate change dissenters,
or maybe we should say realists, are often shamed
and persecuted for challenging the consensus view.
The alleged 97% consensus is an example of
manipulating data to support a particular
viewpoint. Richard and Matt mentioned the
fraudulent hockey stick graph in the last episode.
And, sorry to say there have been several other
instances of data tampering from institutions
like NASA, the UK climate authorities, and
the Australian Bureau of Meteorology or BOM.
For example Australia’s hottest day on
record was 51.7 degrees Celsius at Bourke,
way back on January 3rd 1909. BOM claimed
it was an anomalous event because the
rest of the stations failed to
record a similar temperature.
But nearby Brewarrina recorded 50.6
degrees Celsius on the same day.
Now that's pretty close and that
was more than 100 years ago.
If the 'hockey stick' graph was
accurate you would think that the
record should have been broken many times
by recent high temperatures, right? But
the second hottest day on record was 51.1 degrees
Celsius at White Cliffs on January 12 1939,
and was also not included in
the official digitized records.
More manipulated data. Here's another one. This
graph shows surface temperatures in the US from
1880 to 1998. Notice the high point in the 1930s
compared to the second highest in the late 1990s.
Now look at NASA’s surface temperature
records for a similar period. The 1930
spike was adjusted down and the 1990s spike
was adjusted up, along with other temperatures,
making it look like recent temperatures
were higher than ever, but they weren't.
Right. And examples like these of climate
authorities tampering with the data,
deceived the public into thinking that there is
a problem where there isn't. Climate change has
become accepted by society to the point
where it's just assumed to be reality.
And it's even blamed for about any natural
disaster like hurricanes, or droughts,
flooding, forest fires, even things like changes
in animal populations, or vegetation. For example
the 2019 bush fires in Australia were called
"unprecedented" and were blamed on climate change.
But "unprecedented" is just wrong because in
the 1938-39 fire season over 80 people died in
bush fires compared to 34 in 2019. Five million
hectares burnt in 2019 but there were 117 million
hectares burnt in 1974 - 75. The "unprecedented"
2019 fires were "precedented" after all.
Christians are sometimes blamed for
environmental problems including climate
change because of the biblical dominion
mandate. Historian Lynn White Jr said,
"Christianity insists that it is God's will
that man exploit nature for his proper ends.
Ummm, No. God gave man dominion over the earth to
subdue it. But the type of dominion involved is
benevolent, a caring and managerial dominion. It's
like the way King Solomon’s dominion resulted in
"peace on all sides around him",
with "every man under his vine and
under his fig tree". God gave us abundant
resources to manage and use for our benefit.
Based on the thoughts of the
late Francis Schaeffer we can
illustrate it this way: when a Christian
sees a tree within a biblical perspective
he respects it as a tree created
by God that's right so he doesn't
condone chopping it down just for the sake
of chopping it down without a good reason.
And at the same time he's free from the
pagan notions about nature that you're
angering the forest gods, for example. So
he's happy to use that tree God provided to
build a house, for example.
At the same time the dominion mandate
would encourage him to consider the
needs of future generations. That might mean
he plants another tree to take its place or
ensures that the supply of trees
isn't eliminated from the earth.
Last week we highlighted a few
failed climate predictions.
Since this is a common theme we can add some more.
In 2007 Dr Tim Flannery predicted there wouldn't
be enough rain to fill Australia’s reservoirs.
Yet Australia has had major floods since
then. He's the same Dr Flannery who was
mentioned on last week's show about being
wrong about the Arctic ice disappearing within
a few years. Climate alarmists have predicted
terrible consequences from rising sea levels that
just haven't materialized. In 1989 the UN said
entire nations will be wiped out by the year
2000 if the sea level rises are not stopped.
A prime candidate they thought was Tuvalu, a
nation of atoll islands in the pacific ocean.
But Tuvalu actually increased in land area by
3% over the last 40 years. In a 2018 survey of
30 Pacific and Indian ocean atolls including
709 islands showed that no atoll had lost land
area in recent decades at all. We'll examine the
topic of rising sea levels further after this.
Stromatolites are regarded by many as the oldest
fossils on earth. They are interpreted as the
remains of colonies of blue-green algae, or
more accurately cyanobacteria. The oldest ones
are claimed to be 3.5 billion years old. Within
this evolutionary perspective one would expect
these colonies to have radically changed, but
remarkably, they are essentially the same today.
Stromatolites, therefore, are classic examples
of living fossils. Living fossils cause major
problems for evolution because they provide
stunning examples of how evolution hasn't
occurred. They also call into question the
evolutionary time frame. Some people try to
downplay the significance of living fossils by
arguing that when something is well adapted to
its environment it doesn't need to change. But
this would need the environment to be constant
for the supposed period of time. This argument
cannot apply to stromatolites because during 3.5
billion years of alleged evolutionary time many
radical environment changes supposedly occurred,
including the arrival of new predators
and parasites. To find out more from
Creation Ministries International
visit our website creation.com.
Want to know a great way to stop
climate alarmism? Tell them . Click
like and subscribe to our channel.
That's right and that will let the
al gore rhythms know that you appreciate
our content. I see what you did there. Yeah,
you like that? Now in any case liking, subscribing
and commenting makes the al gore rhythms happy
resulting in the video being suggested to more
people. Who knows maybe Al Gore will watch it.
Maybe he'll leave a comment. I wonder what
data he'd have the most problem with? Maybe
some we're about to say. Well let's stop talking
about it and get back to the show. Great idea.
Regarding rising sea levels, in the biblical world
view Noah's flood created ideal conditions for
an ice age beginning right after the flood
lasting for several hundred years. There's
plenty of evidence for an ice age including
the erosion of landscapes, scraping of bedrock,
the leftover rocks and boulders from retreating
ice sheets, leftover ice caps, and much more.
Cappuccino? Not that kind of ice cap.
Naturalist suggests there have been many ice ages
over millions of years though the
evidence really just points to one.
As you can imagine, since Noah’s flood
there have been massive changes in sea level
and there's evidence for this
that scientists can see today,
like old shorelines, marine fossils and
small fossil coral reefs on land. This graph
includes the secular timeline so that
needs some adjusting but it shows the
rise in sea level since the height of the ice
age when the glaciers were at their largest.
It shows that at that time sea level was
about 120 meters, or 390 feet, lower than now.
And in the creation model the sea level values
indicated here would also change for a variety
of reasons. One of those is: there were
no ice sheets immediately after the flood.
The Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets
developed during a single post-flood Ice Age,
rapidly at first, and then continuing to
build slowly until reaching a steady state.
Because of that and recalibrating uniformitarian
assumptions on the size of the ice sheets
recent studies suggest that sea level was about
68 meters, or 220 feet, higher at the end of the
flood than it is now. As ice sheets grew over a
few hundred years sea level dropped dramatically
to about 55 meters, or 180 feet, below today's
level, and then rose as the ice melted.
Satellite measurements indicate
sea levels are currently rising
at about 3.3 millimeters per year,
or about one foot per hundred years,
assuming the data is accurate. Calibration
of satellites is quite complex with many
factors affecting it. Keep in mind global
sea level can't be measured locally because
continents also go up and down. For example,
much of northern Europe is rising, rebounding
after being pushed down during the Ice Age. Other
factors include volcanic and tectonic activity.
But what if all the ice in the Arctic
sea and all the icebergs melted?
It wouldn't raise the sea level. Remember
learning about Archimedes in school?
The bathtub guy. Oh yeah eureka. You can see the
Archimedes principle at home when you put an ice
cube in a glass of water. As the ice cube melts
its density increases while its volume decreases
so it takes up only the space displaced by
the ice, so the water level doesn't change.
Unless you drink some of it, right?
So back to arctic ice. If the arctic becomes
ice-free, if all the ice sea ice melts,
there'll be no change in sea level. The melting
of ice on land would cause sea level to rise.
A study of grounded ice volumes in Greenland
and Antarctica showed a loss of ice from 2003
to 2019 resulting in a 14 millimeter
rise in sea level over 16 years. If
all of Antarctica’s grounded ice were to melt sea
level would rise about 57 meters, or 190 feet.
That would be a problem for anyone
living close to the ocean near sea level,
but don't panic, at current
melting rates it'll take 82
000 years to get that far. No need
to call the moving van just yet.
Once again the data shows there's no urgent
emergency, climate data has been manipulated,
and past predictions about what we
should be seeing now have failed.
We ought to be more concerned about the
effect that climate alarmism has on children.
Children are becoming increasingly
worried about the future because
they continue to be told that
the earth is going to fry.
Shouldn't we just let kids be kids? Scaring them
with faulty 'doom and gloom' stories is really
a form of child abuse, not unlike telling them
that monsters are real and living under the bed.
Some have become mistrustful of older
generations believing they've ruined the planet.
And some young couples have chosen not
to have children at all because of their
own fear about the future. Yet
it's the children of today who
will have the opportunity to come up with
solutions for real environmental problems.
It's a shame that big decisions
often get made based on fake news,
exaggerated predictions and even fraudulent data.
So what about coral reefs? It's been suggested
climate change will result in higher water
temperature which causes the bleaching of coral.
This means corals will expel the algae living in
their tissues causing the coral to turn white. The
coral doesn't necessarily die but they do become
stressed and their mortality rate does go up. So
what was predicted and what actually happened?
In 2012 Dr Nancy Knowlton from the Smithsonian
National Museum of Natural History predicted
that 90% of the living coral in the central and
south sections of the Great Barrier Reef would be
gone in 10 years. There has been some damage
from the crown of thorns starfish and cyclones
but little evidence of a long-term downward
trend in the amount of hard coral recovered.
The Smithsonian did admit that only 10% of
the claimed losses of coral were actually from
bleaching. Another failed prediction.
There are other factors causing coral
bleaching besides a rise in ocean temperature.
For example, upward growth of the reef traps
pools of water that then overheat. A study
of long-term bleaching of the great
barrier reef by way of drill cores
showed periods of severe bleaching going back to
the 1700s, well before any recent global warning.
And now for the topic you've all been waiting
for: ocean acidification. You excited?
Sure. Well let's do it anyway. When atmospheric
CO2 increases more of it dissolves in the ocean
creating carbonic acid which can affect
the availability of calcium carbonate
used by creatures like corals to build their
skeletons. Researchers from James Cook university
in Australia published eight papers claiming
acidification also harms coral reef fish species.
However other scientists were unable to
replicate the findings and even found
evidence of fraud. In fact there's evidence
that coral can acclimatize to much higher CO2
levels. They certainly did in the past both
before and immediately after Noah’s flood.
So yet another prediction failed,
and yet there are alarm bells being
unnecessarily rung about calamities that
will supposedly result from climate change.
It's fear-mongering plain and simple.
It's very sad. We acknowledge that we've thrown
a lot of data at you in these two episodes.
But rather than try to remember it all you
can refer to the comprehensive article on the
subject at creation.com/climate-change. Great
article. The bottom line is climate change is
not a huge emergency like you've been told.
For Christians, everything we witness happening
in our world, including small changes in climate,
makes sense in a biblical worldview. While
activists sound the alarm the Bible tells us
we live in a fallen world. But we can
rest assured that God is in control.
Now does that mean we should ignore threats
to our environment? No. But there are other
environmental threats that are more
serious than alleged climate change,
such as plastics in the ocean, overfishing,
and heavy metals in drinking water.
Fossil fuels do cause problems like air
pollution, and there are technological
solutions available if there's available wealth
to invest in them. Although it's not a perfect
system, wealth is created primarily by
industries dependent on fossil fuels.
For companies that want to convert to a different
energy source that will take time. For example,
wind and solar are not viable everywhere
and there are pollution challenges and
other problems to overcome in setting
up those systems. In the meantime let's
be careful that our economy doesn't fall
apart out of zeal for a cleaner environment
because that hurts everyone. There's no
use replacing one problem with another.
And in some countries that
can't afford fossil fuels
people burn dung and wood both releasing
CO2 and causing terrible air pollution.
Under the Paris accord wood is considered
renewable energy as opposed to coal
so there are coal-fired power stations in the
UK and Europe being converted to run on wood.
So much for save the trees. Back
in the day before oil wells,
whale oil was used for lamps. So, in a
way, fossil fuels helped save the whales.
Other proposed fuel alternatives aren't as
wonderful as they sound either. Electric
cars might be the future, but there are
serious problems associated with mining
lithium for batteries including using a
lot of water and potential leaks of toxic
chemicals used in processing. Oh, and that
electric car should ideally be charged by
some other form of electricity not generated
by pollution-producing power plants.
In southeast Asia rainforests are being
destroyed to make room for palm oil plantations
to make biofuels. In some places existing
farmland is being converted from food to
grain production for ethanol. So
more non-fossil fuel in the car
but less food to eat. I vote
for more food. I second that.
Speaking of food: CO2 is plant food. And more
of it would actually be a good thing. A 2017
paper in Nature indicated, the increase in
CO2 is responsible for 30% of the world's
biomass production over the last century.
That's food for both animals and people.
With more CO2 in the air plants spend less time
with their leaf pores open losing less water,
so they can survive in drier climates. Increased
CO2 is causing the greening of deserts.
Meanwhile here in Canada the government
refers to CO2 as a 'pollutant'
and, as in some other countries,
it's enacted a carbon tax.
Pollutant? Try living without it, we'd all die!
The pre-flood world had up to 15 times the amount
of CO2 as now, and vegetation flourished. That's
where fossil fuels came from. As the vegetation
of the pre-flood world was buried during the
flood it was then converted into coal and oil.
The burial of much carbon in the ground has
resulted in the CO2 drought that we are now in
All of these environmental
concerns need to be tackled
ultimately with care for people.
We'll talk more about that after this.
Did you know that the earth's magnetic
field has reversed direction, or flipped,
multiple times in the past? The evidence for
these reversals is rock solid because when
molten rock cools certain mineral grains align
with the earth's magnetic field thus recording
the direction of the earth's magnetic field
at the time in the solidified rock. Previously
most geologists thought that a single reversal
would take many thousands of years. However,
creation physicist Dr Russell Humphreys reasoned
they must have happened quickly to fit within
the biblical time scale. So Dr Humphreys made a
prediction that quickly cooling, thin lava flows
would be found that recorded fast changes in the
direction of the magnetic field. This prediction
was later proven correct. Scientists were shocked
to find major magnetic field changes had occurred
within weeks in a single lava flow. They
published this in the regular scientific
literature. Thus yet another scientific prediction
based on biblical history proved to be correct.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Stop climate alarmism! But how? Give the video a
like, subscribe and share the video on Twitter
and Facebook. The more people who
interact with the video in this way,
the more the algorithms suggest it to
others and if more people see it we
can stop climate alarmism! Everyone wins! Except
the climate alarmists. They won’t like it. Well,
maybe they won’t be alarmists anymore. Hey, you’re
right! Everyone wins! And now, back to the show.
Climate change is a huge topic involving
many different environmental factors.
Let's look at a few more and
then draw some conclusions.
While CO2 emissions seem to get all the
attention there are other factors affecting
global temperatures including chlorofluorocarbons,
remember those? Authors of a 2020 study wrote,
"Gases that deplete the ozone
layer could be responsible for
up to half of the effects of climate change
observed in the Arctic from 1955 to 2005."
Wow. Up to half is pretty significant. A
resulting reduction in the area of snow
or its annual duration means less reflection
of sunlight back into space and, therefore,
more Arctic warming. But because CFCs have been
discontinued this effect may decrease over time.
Obviously the sun is a major factor.
Without it we wouldn't even be here.
Solar cycles affect climate by
way of stratospheric warming,
cosmic rays, and cloud cover. For example, an 11
year cycle of earth's position relative to the sun
results in a variation in earth's
temperature of 0.2 degrees Celsius.
The Maunder Minimum refers to a prolonged
period of very few sunspots from 1645 to 1715
during the Little Ice Age. Recently,
for the first time since the 1600s,
we've had several years with no sunspots.
Maybe the normal 11-year cycle will resume,
but maybe not. So if the primary driver of
climate is the sun and if we can't predict
what it will do in a short time frame how can we
predict temperature decades and centuries out.
Also there's a hypothesis that when the
sun's solar wind is strong and the earth
is protected from cosmic rays the result is
less cloud formation and the earth warms.
When the solar wind is weak, like
now when sunspot activity is low,
more cosmic rays cause more
clouds to form cooling the planet.
And none of these models get clearly as
much press as CO2 maybe that's because
we've already stopped using CFCs,
and we can't control the sun.
And humans do like to think we're in control. In
these episodes we've thrown a lot of information
at you in a short amount of time, and
we've only touched on some of the data.
To dig in further, check out Don Batten's
article at creation.com/climate-change
Let's finish up by summarizing the key points
we've learned about the climate change debate
and how Christians should respond. First
the whole issue has become politicized to
the point where it's not even
about the environment anymore
and has led to failed predictions and
the corruption of some of the science.
Worldview affects how we think about the
environment and our hope for the future.
Atmospheric CO2 has been increasing over the
last hundred years or so but temperatures
over that time don't support the
hypothesis that human generated CO2
is the prime cause of temperature increases.
The science is not settled.
Official climate models predicting up
to 4.5 degrees Celsius of global warming
do not line up with actual data.
Those models should be rejected.
The impact of global warming on various natural
disasters is not supported by the evidence.
There is no climate emergency
so please stop fear-mongering.
We live in a fallen world
but this isn't all there is.
Believers are to take care of this world while
looking forward to the new heavens and new earth.
Ultimately God is in control not mankind.
As Christians our priority needs to be
on spreading the gospel of Jesus Christ.
As more people turn to Christ and grow in
their understanding of the Christian worldview,
conforming their thinking
in every area to the truth,
they'll be better able to correctly
prioritize climate change issues.
And a lot of these issues right that are
addressed in Creation magazine, like the
article that this one was based on. You can get
a free copy of Creation magazine, digitally,
if you go to creation.com/free-mag.
A lot of great content in there.
Lots of great things. And, it does all come
down to worldview in many cases because,
if you take a long ages, evolutionary worldview,
there's no God, everything's natural processes,
then we get some of these climate
change ideas that we've been hearing
about. With a biblical worldview we
get a different perspective on it all.
Remember Christianity is an evidence-based
faith, and science supports Scripture.
Thanks for watching. If you watched episode
1 and episode 2, two half-hour shows, then
you’ve just seen a short, little, brief, itty bitty summary
of Dr Don Batten’s massive 14,000 word article.
The full title is “Anthropogenic
Global Warming - a biblical and
scientific approach to climate change”
You’ll want to look that up
at creation.com to get more
fascinating facts that balance what most
of the media is, unfortunately, missing.
See you next week!