Now, unless you've
been living under a rock,
the issue that many
are near hysterical about
is that atmospheric temperature is
supposedly going up
because humans are producing too
much carbon
dioxide. And if temperature goes
beyond a certain
threshold, it'll be catastrophic
for life on Earth. That's
called anthropogenic global warming.
Whoa! Can you say that one again?
It's anthropogenic, means man-made.
Okay, man-made. In
1860, the amount of CO2
in our atmosphere
was approximately 285 parts
per million, or
0.029%. Now, as of 2020, it
was 410 parts per
million or 0.41%. So that's
just under 50% increase over 160
years. And the current rate of increase is about
2 parts per million per year.
Okay, meanwhile, the planet has
warmed by about 0.8 degrees Celsius since 1880,
but half of this occurred
before any significant change to the CO2.
This graph shows both
the man-made CO2 emissions
and global
temperature changes from 1850 to 2010.
The green line shows an increase in
man-made CO2, most of
it since 1940, you can see.
The black line shows
fluctuations in overall temperature.
Now, notice that the rate of
temperature increased from 1860 to 1880,
when there was
relatively little man-made CO2,
is about the same as
for the most recent period,
when emissions
were about 60 times higher.
Now, also note that there were dips in
temperature at times when
CO2 emissions were still going up.
So the increase in temperature
cannot be entirely due to man-made CO2.
Now, that's not to
say it isn't a factor, but
it's just maybe not
the most significant one.
Human contribution
to CO2 emissions by burning
fossil fuels
accounts for less than 5% of the
total global carbon budget.
I mean, other factors
include things like changes
in land use,
deforestation, volcanoes, CO2 release
from the oceans as
they warm, the breakdown of
organic remains such
as dead wood and forests,
and other factors like that.
Like, even assuming if all of the 2
parts per million increase in CO2 is man-made,
it would take nearly 200
years to double the level to 800.
So why panic?
Why panic?
One question for
activists is, why not focus on
the biggest CO2
contributors like China and India?
In 2018, for
example, China generated almost
a thousand gigawatts
of electricity from coal.
The United States was only
261 in Australia, for example, at 36.
China and India are planning
hundreds more coal-fired power stations.
Australia, for example, accounts
for only 1.2% of the world's emissions.
But like other Western nations,
they're targeted by activists far more than China.
It's not that Western
nations shouldn't reduce emissions.
But shouldn't the protests
be focused on the biggest offenders?
You'd think so
There's also something you fishy
about the infamous hockey stick graph.
The graph shows
that after a thousand-year
period of relatively stable temperatures,
there was a
dramatic spike within the last
century,
particularly in the last few decades.
This is usually
attributed to the use of fossil fuels.
However, this graph has
been shown to be fraudulent.
It doesn't record either the
medieval warming period or the little ice age
from the mid-1300s to about 1885.
When we add those back, the
graph should look more like this,
showing
fluctuations in global temperatures
before any increase
in man-made CO2 emissions.
It said that a
picture is worth a thousand words.
The image of that fraudulent graph was a
fear-mongering tactic
that influenced millions of people.
And the fear it produced
motivated people to voting climate activists.
Another major historical event related to
climate change
happened about 4,500 years ago.
Noah's flood
covered the earth in water and
buried massive
amounts of vegetation and animals,
turning them into
coal and other fossil fuels.
Nearly all of
today's coal was formed from
the vegetation
buried during Noah's flood.
The huge amount of buried
vegetation suggests that pre-flood CO2 levels
must have been very
high compared to today's levels.
CO2 is plant food.
Even secular geologists agree that
ancient Paleozoic CO2 levels were much higher,
like even 15 times
more than they are today.
Way higher.
Yeah, there's no evidence that
the earth was cooked by this situation,
you know, a runaway
greenhouse effect or something.
The much higher CO2
levels would boost plant
productivity and also
allow for much more animal
biomass.
CO2 is plant food, and more
of it would actually be a good thing.
A 2017 paper in
Nature indicated the increase
in CO2 is
responsible for 30% of the world's
biomass production over the last century.
That's food for both animals and people.
With more CO2 in the air, plants
spend less time with their leaf pores open,
losing less water so they
can survive in drier climates.
Increased CO2 is
causing the greening of deserts.
Meanwhile, here in Canada, the
government refers to CO2 as a pollutant,
and as in some other
countries, it's enacted a carbon tax.
Pollutant.
Try living without it.
We'd all die.
The pre-flood
world had up to 15 times the
amount of CO2 as now,
and vegetation flourished.
That's where fossil fuels came from.
As the vegetation of the
pre-flood world was buried during the flood,
it was then converted into coal and oil.
The burial of much
carbon in the ground has
resulted in the CO2
drought that we are now in.