[Music]
Let's crank the
clock back to 1859, long before
Bill Gates, when
Charles Darwin wrote his book
on the origin of
species. The thinking back
then was that the cell
was a fairly simple blob of
matter. It's easier to imagine organisms
evolving slowly and
gradually if they're fairly simple.
Right.
We now know that
there are problems with that
view. Darwin didn't
know anything about genetics,
which really took off
shortly after he published.
He did, however,
famously admit, "If it could be
demonstrated that
any complex organ existed,
which could not
possibly have been formed by numerous
successive slight modifications,
my theory would absolutely break down."
Now, while Darwin
was referring to organs, we
can apply this logic
at the molecular level, since,
as we mentioned,
evolutionists now assert that
even DNA formed as
a result of random natural
processes. For
example, biochemist Michael Behe
coined the term
"irreducible complexity." Now,
that refers to a
system of interacting parts in
which every part has
to be in place before it can
function. Now, this
means that a system couldn't
come into being
gradually bit by bit, and there
are many examples of this kind of
evolution-refuting design in molecular biology.
Here's an example. Life depends on an
incredible enzyme called
ATP synthase. That's the name of
the world's
tiniest rotary motor, rotating
at up to 7000 rpm.
These are so small that
100,000 would fit side by side in a
millimeter. Yeah, ATP
synthase makes ATP, or adenosine
triphosphate, the
fuel that powers cellular
machines. Each of
the human bodies, about 14
trillion cells,
perform this reaction about a
million times a
minute. Over half of your body's
weight of ATP is
made and consumed every day.
A current of
protons drives the motor, unlike
man-made electric
motors which use electrons.
The portion shown here
in green is where adenosine
diphosphate is
combined with a phosphate ion
in the presence of
a catalyst to produce ATP,
which is then released making way for the
next cycle. This
nanomachine exhibits all the
characteristics of
super intelligent design.
That's right. ATP
is vital for life, and many
of these motors
were needed before the first
living cell could
exist. That's an evolutionary
impossibility.