hi today on creation talk did
life come from outer space
[Music]
hi and welcome again i'm gary bates
ceo of creation ministries international
us
and i'm talking here with paul price one
of our staff writers
how you doing there paul hey so subject
that you and i
are deeply interested in i wrote the
book
alien intrusion ufos and the evolution
connection which was made into a
movie a couple of years ago and in that
i discussed this topic of
panspermia panspermia literally means
life from space or seeds from space it's
based on a
actually a greek term and there are two
types right
so there's what they call undirected
panspermia
so that is the idea that somehow some
primordial dna
has floated into the earth landed on
earth or as we're going to discuss
has got here in some asteroids or comets
that impacted on the earth and all life
generated from that
that's what we call undirected and then
of course there's the directed one which
was
highly evolved advanced space aliens
visited the earth and we covered this in
the movie with it with great animation
and deliberately seeded life here and
then have been
you know overseeing our evolution that's
the more interesting version for
yeah well there's a point though why do
people come up with those ideas
you know why do we say fun it's fun to
talk about fun to think about obviously
well isn't the eye isn't the problem
that uh we're trying to get away in some
respects from
a biblical creation and the idea that
you know
if if evolution doesn't work and it's
not a satisfactory answer i mean
scientists still can't figure out really
and i know this is a big statement and
hey don't write in and say well what
about the rna world
searchcreation.com because we'd have
answered it but aren't
uh if if evolution the origins of life
is still an intractable problem
by pushing it off into outer space and
saying well maybe it floated here from
elsewhere or aliens created us
is that really solving the problem um i
would say it's definitely not
solving the problem this issue has been
sort of
building for quite a while now in
scientific realms
scientific communities trying to figure
out
on a basic genetic level and on a
molecular level even
how is evolution possible and they're
running up against a brick wall time and
time again
um i think the majority of the
scientific community is still
trying to maintain the illusion
of solidarity behind their theory of
neo-darwinism and
and abiogenesis but behind the scenes um
there's lots of indications that uh
changes are on the way
that uh this this theory is not holding
up
with the latest evidence and uh changes
are gonna have to be coming
but the idea of panspermia which is seen
as a solution to that doesn't solute
solve anything because whether it's
directed or undirected
how did life evolve out there or if
aliens created us
who created the aliens that created us
and that's called the infinite
regression
problem because you're just pushing
pushing it off into outer space
where you can't solve it but here's
something recently and you've written an
article on this
the idea of undirected this is the idea
that
these primordial seeds from space
traveled here in some icy comet
you know millions or even billions of
years ago
and seeded the earth that was a view
popularized by a darwinian skeptic
in fact an astronomer by the name of
fred hoyle he he in fact said there were
so many problems with
traditional darwinism that they couldn't
be solved which is why he
resorted to this idea of undirected
panspermia
he was a bit of a pariah in his
own community wasn't he but
he's been resurrected somewhat and this
is the article
you wrote about so just explain to us
what the premises are
of this uh shall we call it new hoyland
yeah theory of the origin of life i i
think i'm the first one to coin the term
hoi lights but that's that's what i'm
calling these scientists
that are following dr fred hoyle i'm
calling them hoilites but
we investigated this article because
it's
it's really interesting and unique among
the
uh secular peer-reviewed scientific
literature
so this is a peer review it's peer
reviewed and uh and secular so that's
what makes this
particularly interesting because this is
not an article
where um you know you can have the
skeptic can come back and say well they
just said that because they're biblical
uh you know fundamentalists trying to
push their religion
no these guys aren't even christians uh
let alone
fundamentalists so they're not even
theists in fact
um so so tell us what they're advocating
yeah so the
this article is from 2018 and it's
called uh
cause of cambrian explosion terrestrial
or
cosmic they're arguing for what fred
hoyle
and his co-author from sri lanka chandra
weak ramazinga
these guys have this term cosmic biology
as you mentioned earlier they believe
that
life was actually seeded on this planet
through extraterrestrial means
by comets or other foreign bodies
actually entering the atmosphere and
bringing
genetic material or life or what have
you
to the planet and one of the things that
i think our viewers would be really
interested to hear is some certain
specific quotes that are really telling
from this paper because
uh they really honestly sound to me just
like something
that could have been written by a
biblical creationist
and the the sort of things that we do
right so there's the idea of that that
they're skeptical about
winningianism exactly and let's make
that point yeah
uh so first quote modern ideas of
abiogenesis
in hydrothermal vents or elsewhere on
the primitive earth
have developed into sophisticated
conjectures
with little or no evidential support
so that's the first quote these guys
don't believe that life
could have come about by random means
here on this planet
another thing they say the
transformation of an ensemble
of appropriately chosen biological
monomers
example amino acids nucleotides
into a primitive living cell capable of
further evolution
appears to require overcoming an
information
hurdle of super astronomical proportions
an event that could not have happened
within the time frame of the earth
except we believe as a miracle yeah
so not only do they think it would cause
it would be a miracle
for life to come about randomly but uh
they're also admitting
that this would represent an information
hurdle which is something
yeah we've got to really talk about yeah
well we would agree with that 100
percent yeah
exactly yeah all right so we just don't
agree with their conclusions
where they take it you know exactly so
we got this big preamble
so tell us you've coined them as uh hoi
lights
yeah and that's what these guys are now
tell us why well you've written the
article tell us why
these guys are highlights so they're
darwin's darwinian skeptics
they're basically saying the odds of
life evolving you know in these
hydrothermal vents in the earth or
by any other means is basically
impossible so
it's not the god of the bible so what
else have they got well
uh what they say is at this stage of our
scientific understanding we need to
place
on hold the issue of life's actual
biochemical origins
where when and how may be too difficult
to solve
on the current evidence so they're
saying we're just not going to go there
however
we think it's in it's infinitely more
probable that it must have somehow
someway happened out there in the cosmos
and then came here to earth at some
point in our past
isn't that a bit of a circular argument
yeah it's impossible for it to evolve on
earth
but it's possible that it evolved
somewhere else and they came to earth
actually haven't they just doubled the
the yeah well they're kicking the can
down the road they're saying you know
what
it's it's beyond our means to figure
this out there's no way it could have
happened by chance here
so let's just take that as a given and
let's see where we can go but they're
not willing to go
uh obviously in the one direction that
so how do they say it gets here that's
the typical hoiling view viewers that
has traveled here on some icy comet or
something like that
well it it's kind of clear as mud when
you read their paper
they're kind of all over the place so
they're hedging that they're hedging
their bets exactly they they put forward
a whole
slew of different ideas maybe it came
just you know through dust or through
comets
or there there's one particular idea
which
um goes back quite a ways where there
they've got some idea of a of a icy
comet that has a liquid center well that
definitely is a hoiling idea
yeah um i got a quote because you
brought that up
let me read this quote by fred whipple
who's an astronomer wrote an article
origin of the solar system he was
reviewing fred hoyle's work work
and i actually quoted this in my book he
said i'm charmed
but not impressed by the picture of life
forms developing
in warm little ponds protected in their
icy
igloos from the cruel cold and near
vacuum of open space
and falling to earth or falling to a
primitive earth
at speeds exceeding 11 kilometers per
second
and if you want to know what visually
that looks like just take a look at this
clip
some have suggested that life on earth
could have arrived by chance from
another planet and floated to earth in
some
icy comet or meteorite this is known as
panspermia or almost literally
seeds from space everywhere but
how could organic life survive the
incredibly harsh environment of space
when there's no oxygen there's below
freezing temperatures there's harmful
radiation
and then just happened to be captured by
earth's gravity as it flew past at tens
of thousand miles an hour and
somehow avoided being burned up as it
entered the earth's atmosphere like 48
kilometers per second
and then survived smashing into the
planet at supersonic speeds that are
fast enough to melt the very ground on
impact
so paul that that clip visually
demonstrated i mean
anything entering our earth at thousands
of miles per hour
is going to burn up i mean think about
our spacecraft they've got special heat
shields or on the shuttles they have
tiles to avoid that
and not only that this impacts the earth
at that speed which as the clip says is
is you know hot enough to melt the
ground upon impact
and somehow this primordial dna
or viruses that hijack have hijacked
some life somewhere
survive to become everything we see on
earth because we know natural selection
does not produce new information
so basically they've got to keep topping
it up but here's a there's another
problem
they've got to land in the right spot to
be suitable for life
as well and this has got to be happening
time and time
the idea that it would even happen one
time is incredible
but the idea that these guys are putting
forward is that it has happened
repeatedly
throughout the history of life on our
planet and that is their explanation
for how evolution has supposedly
proceeded over time
but didn't they have a didn't they say
they tested this yes
they appeal to a few different alleged
scientific tests that
supposedly give credence to their ideas
one of the ones that they
uh listed was a paper by theo at l
who had used a sounding rocket test
where you know they they send up these
rockets and
do some experiments let the rockets come
back down and collect the results and
what they did was they painted some
dna on the side in a very heavy
concentration
in a few different places and then they
say that
once they got the rocket back they say
they were able to retrieve some of it
well hang on if if they're trying to
recreate these alleged
natural conditions how did they get the
rocket back i mean
we're talking about a comet crashing
today this rocket
obviously didn't crash to earth it had a
parachute so that's one
that is not a fair comparison not a fair
comparison which you know that the
authors admit that they admit that they
they weren't attempting to make it
realistic but then yeah i mean if they
weren't doing that then what was the
point exactly
exactly well it's a non-starter it's a
non-starter
so i mean we don't like to ridicule
but i have to be honest we've kind of uh
a bit of gas that these types of
explanations that
that come up and i think in some ways i
don't know about you
it shows me that there's a type of
desperation yeah absolutely it's
it's uh grasping at straws they're they
they've
hit a brick wall they're trying to
explain things without god
uh but as you and i would obviously say
you can't do that
so what is what is going to be the
result they're they're going to have to
come up with these
these kind of crazy ideas so a couple of
lessons there
sometimes some very clever people can
come up with some
seeming technically plausible answers
but sometimes when you look
underneath the surface it's not always
as it appears i think paul you uh nailed
it on the head there when you said
it's about god a wise man once said
there's nothing new under the sun
and all of these very very
complex and elaborated ideas are
ultimately to
explain life without a creator
thanks for today paul appreciate it and
as we always say if you
like this well hit the like button and
let me challenge you folks if you like
this information we've had some great
comments that people are enjoying this
but it's up to you to share it and get
the information out so hey
you know people just share the link and
you've done
the work of an evangelist right there
and then
remember it's not our job to save people
but we are called to be a faithful
witness
so we look forward to seeing you next
time thanks for joining us