You know a lot of
people challenge us
and say that carbon dating
proves millions of years.
Well you might be surprised by
what carbon dating really tells us.
Stay tuned!
So welcome back.
I’m Scott Gillis and I’m here
with my good friend Joel Tay.
How are you doing Joel?
Hi Scott.
You know that we talk all the
time about the origins issue,
about evolution
versus creation and …
you know that deals with time.
Yes.
You know for example evolution
needs millions and billions of years,
and that stands in opposition
to the biblical account
which is a much shorter time.
So …
We’ve talked about in other episodes
as well as on our website creation.com
how the millions of years they
come from the sedimentary layers but
how many times have we
heard before the idea that
carbon dating proves
millions of years. Right?
So here’s the question:
Does carbon dating
prove millions of years?
No, it doesn’t!
Okay. All right, well
why do you say that?
Well, we have to ask
a question first, right?
So “What is carbon dating?” —
before we can even
address the issue.
Right.  And when you
think about carbon, you know
I’ve been told that carbon is kind of
like the backbone element of all life.
You know, the Star Trek people used to say
that there are ‘carbon-based life forms’.
Yes, that’s right, yes.
And so all living things, both we
and the animals and the plants, are …
have this basis, this backbone
of the carbon element.
So how is that used? How is
that a part of carbon dating?
Okay, so to understand carbon
dating we have to understand that
normal carbon that we have is carbon-12,
but cosmic rays hit the earth and
cosmic rays actually cause
nitrogen 14 to become carbon-14.
Now where is this nitrogen 14?
Oh, nitrogen is in the air — an
enormous percentage is nitrogen-14.
So cosmic rays hit that,
convert that to carbon-14.
So now we have two types of carbon:
normal carbon which is carbon-12,
and then we have the radioactive
carbon which is carbon-14.
And carbon-14 decays
over time back into nitrogen.
So, um, what’s the ratio?
Well we have: for every one
trillion carbon-12 atoms
there is one carbon-14 atom.
So we know the ratio.
Okay, one trillion …
for every one trillion carbon-12
atoms we have one carbon-14 atom.
Yes, about one trillion.
Okay. So … and that’s
in, like, the atmosphere?
It gets into everything we deal
with — in our food, in the atmosphere.
When we breathe in, we drink water,
we eat, we take both carbon-12 and
carbon-14 into our body.
And not just we, but
the animals and plants.
All living things.
All the creatures
that respirate carbon,
because like I mean we have carbon dioxide
so it’s part of the respiration thing
Yes.
All right so that means that this carbon-12
and carbon-14 is inside living things.
All living things, yes.
So as long as we’re living
we’re taking that in right?
Yes that’s right.
Okay.
But what happens when we die?
So that’s where the question comes in.
Right. So what do you mean ‘when
we die’? How does that change things?
You see when we die we stop taking
in any more food, any more carbon,
And stop breathing too,
right? Stop breathing too.
So no new carbon is
coming into our bodies.
But carbon-12 is stable. It’s
normal carbon. It remains at
the same amount or same level.
Well carbon-14,
it’s radioactive.
Over time it decays
away back into nitrogen.
So if you have carbon-12 here
and you have carbon-14 here
over time carbon-14 halves
itself, and we call that ‘half-life’.
Half-life? Well what’s
… what do you mean?
I’ve heard that term. I remember
that in school. What’s a half-life?
Well half-life is the
amount of time it takes for
a certain element to decay —a
radioactive element— to decay by half.
So in carbon-14 you’re looking
at 5,730 years as a half-life.
So what that means is: imagine
you have this amount. After
5,730 years it halves itself.
Okay.
And another 5,730 it halves
itself again so you get a quarter.
A quarter left?
One eighth, one
sixteenth, and so on.
Well eventually it would go
down to almost nothing, right?
Yeah. Eventually it would
just, um, you know, be all gone.
Wait a minute here.
So if indeed carbon-14
has this half-life of almost …
Well, I mean 5,730
years is a long time
but compared to millions
of years it’s not very much.
I’m thinking that if it
goes down to a half
and then after another
5,000 or so years a quarter,
sixteenth, you know an eight,
sixteenth, and it goes down …
I mean there’s a certain point that there
wouldn’t be any measurable amount left.
I mean when does that happen?
That’s right, so it keeps
halving itself and we say that
the upper limit is about
50,000 to 100,000 years.
Oh!
So in other words if you have a fossil
that is more than 100,000 years old
it should not contain any carbon-14.
All of that should have degraded away.
Yet don’t they often times tell us that
these fossils are millions of years old?
Yes, that’s what
evolutionists claim.
So this is kind of
a problem isn’t it?
It is, because the thing is, almost
every fossil that we test contains
traceable amounts of carbon-14.
All right. So where do we
find this radioactive carbon-14?
Where do we find
those kind of things?
As we have mentioned earlier on,
carbon is taken in by living things
so things that were once
alive now contain carbon-14
so things like fossils …
Yeah.
Um, coal, because
coal is carbon as well.
So what … coal used to be what?
It used to be plants,
trees that were once alive.
Okay.
So they’d have carbon-14
and carbon-12 in there.
Okay.
So when we test coal, it contains
carbon-14: we know they are young.
We test oil, it
contains carbon-14.
We can test diamonds and
diamond is made of carbon.
Oh, okay. So diamonds, okay.
And the big one is this:
What?
We can test dinosaur bones.
And guess what they contain?
Carbon-14!
Which means that they are … ?
Young! They are not even
100,000 years old, max.
So even by their own assumptions it
can’t be more than 100,000 years old.
That’s right.
Sounds like a huge problem
for evolutionists, this
whole idea of carbon-14.
And yet most of us are told that
that’s where we get millions of years,
or one of the places we get it.
That’s true, yeah.
Yeah. I’ve heard an
explanation of this whole idea of,
of not just carbon-14
but radioisotope decay
kind of given as an
analogy as a bathtub.
I think you’ve probably
heard that before.
I’ve heard that, but
can you explain?
I’ve told this story before
where you know, let’s say that
when I get home tonight I come and
walk up to my door and nobody’s home,
but I hear water running.
All right? And it sounds like my
house is flooding—a lot of water!
So I go in there and in the
bathtub the faucet’s running
full force. Nobody’s there!
So I just happen to have a one
gallon pail next to my bathtub.
I put it underneath
the faucet and I time it,
and it takes one minute to
fill up that one gallon pail.
Yes.
All right, so later on if I
measure 15 gallons into the tub,
so what would be the logical
answer that you would give —
that it took one minute to fill one
gallon and I have 15 gallons in the tub?
Most people will
say “15”. 15 minutes.
Right. Now I’ve given this analogy
before and I ask that question and
they always answer “15 minutes”.
But then I tell them they made
a lot of assumptions, right?
Yes.
I mean for example
they didn’t say …
They assumed that there was
no water in the tub when it started,
that nobody added
any, nobody took any out,
that the drain plug
wasn’t being fiddled with,
that the amount of water coming
out of the faucet wasn’t turned
on and off or changed the rate.
Yes, that’s right.
And that’s a good analogy of
the assumptions that scientists use
when they’re doing radioisotope
dating like carbon-14, right?
Yes, that’s true.
But some of these things, those
assumptions, I’ve heard you know
scientists have said for example
the decay rate — which would be the
amount of water going in the tub —
that it’s not always been consistent,
that it’s changed over time.
Have you heard that kind of thing?
Yes, I’ve heard a
few explanations.
So what are some of the other
assumptions that scientists use that
the evidence really doesn’t support?
Yeah. Um … Well you know
sometimes people come up to us to say
“100,000 years? That’s still very
big!” referring to the Bible, right.
Yeah.
But we must understand — like you
say, the bathtub analogy — there’s
lots of assumptions that we have.
Yeah.
So one of the assumptions:
you must understand that
when we say ‘radio carbon dates’
we’re not talking about actual dates.
Right. So that machine, I think it’s
called the accelerator mass spectrometer,
Yes, that’s right.
that’s the big expensive machine
that counts those atoms, right?
Yeah, they count
individual atoms.
and I think a lot of people think
that, like, a little slip of paper
comes out and tells a date of an item
and that’s not it at all. I mean what
does that machine do, just plainly?
Just count the atoms.
That’s all, and so then the scientists
they have to interpret that count, correct?
Yes, that’s right.
So one of the things that
you mentioned is that we …
we kind of know how many half
lives — we assume we know how
many half lives — have passed.
So we know the ratio of
carbon-12 and carbon-14.
But like the bathtub analogy — what if at
the very beginning, or before the Flood,
there was a different ratio
of carbon-12 and carbon-14?
Right. So scientists are assuming that
the ratio that’s in the environment today
has been true for actually
millions of years, right?
Yes, yes.
But in a biblical scenario are there
some questions that we can ask that
might change that assumption?
Yes, because the Bible
speaks about a worldwide Flood.
Right.
And we also know
from science that
our magnetic field around the earth has
been decaying exponentially over time.
And why this is
important is this:
Do you remember how
carbon-14 is formed?
Yeah, the cosmic rays coming in
from the atmosphere and bombarding
those nitrogen-14 atoms, right?
Yes, that’s right.
But when we have a
stronger magnetic field
— and we know that we had a much
stronger magnetic field in the past —
that kind of shields the
earth from the cosmic rays.
Oh, it shields from
the cosmic rays? Okay.
Which means that less
carbon-14 would be formed.
Back in those earlier years when
the magnetic force was greater
there would be less
carbon-14 in the atmosphere.
That’s right.
In fact we even know from
archaeology that when we test things
that go back further than 400 BC
the carbon dates don’t actually
match the written records very well.
Right.
The further back you go before
that it gets more and more skewed.
So if that’s true about the magnetic
field then we would actually get
older ages than they actually were.
Yes, because if there’s less
carbon-14 created in the past
and we assume today’s
rates to measure that,
it will give us inflated ages,
so that things will appear to be
older than they actually are.
That makes sense. So
you get an inflated date.
What other kind of things do we find in the
evidence in the world, in the rock layers?
Well I think one of the
most interesting things is this:
See, where do we get the
idea of millions of years from?
Well most people would say from
the sedimentary layers building up
millions and millions of years.
They’ll say all these layers stack
up and actually are hundreds of
millions of years, right?
That’s right and this is
where it gets interesting.
What?
When we test fossils from different layers,
different depths in the rock layers,
they all give the
same age range.
Really!
Which means they are not
a record of millions of years.
The rock layers are formed
as a result of one single event.
So that means all those layers
probably were laid down quickly
in a very short period.
Ah, perhaps a worldwide Flood?
A worldwide Flood! Those creatures
lived and died at the same time.
All right.
And if the rock layers are not
set down over millions of years
where do you get your
millions of years from?
So we have established that
carbon-14 tells us a fossil cannot
be more than 100,000 years old.
Right.
So where do people get the
idea that radiometric dating
gives us millions of years?
Well I’ve heard that sometimes they use
different radio isotopes besides carbon-14
that have much longer half-lives.
You know for instance I think
potassium argon is one of the tests
that’s done to get millions of years.
But then that reminds
me of a report where
a sample from a volcanic lava dome
was sent in to a potassium argon dating lab
and they got an age
of 350,000 years.
Yes, that’s right.
And then they extracted a
mineral from that same sample
and this time they got a completely
different date — 900,000 years.
And yet another mineral they took out and
this time it was 1.7 to 2.8 million years.
And this is all from
the same rock?
Same rock all right,
but it turns out that
that rock came from the
volcanic lava dome of Mt St Helens
and the people knew that this rock
had formed only 10 years before.
And yet they got ranges of
350,000 to 2.8 million years.
From a rock that was 10 years old!
So it doesn’t even agree?
Right. So there are some
questions that we should be asking
about the assumptions that scientists
are using when we do radioisotope dating.
So when we get results that conflict
with what the actual evidence is,
how do the
scientists answer this?
Yeah, what do they say?
I mean sometimes they say that,
well, there’s a contamination, right?
Yes.
You know, that something must
have gone wrong with the tests.
And one thing I think of when
I think of contamination is,
you know, just take a diamond.
You know that’s the hardest
substance known on earth
(outside of the human heart!)
But you know what? If there’s
any place that contamination
couldn’t happen it’s in diamonds.
But, as we’ve reported on
our website creation.com,
there is carbon-14 in diamonds.
That’s right.
And one thing interesting
about contamination is that
when we say something is contaminated we
would expect that to be the rare exception.
Okay, right, the rare exception.
But if in almost every case it’s
contamination? Perhaps it’s not
really contamination at all.
It’s especially when the result is
different than what they were hoping for.
There’s always
a reason for that.
So you could say that
carbon-14 is our friend.
It actually supports
what the Bible says.
Yes, a good friend
of the creationists.
Right. Now we’ve only scratched
the surface here in this episode
and there’s so many more
things that you can investigate.
For example go to our
website creation.com
and click on articles, topics,
and then click on dating.
No you’re not going to find anything there
about Valentine’s Day, that kind of dating,
but it’s going to give you a
better understanding of what
we’re talking about today.
If you want a general overview I’d like to
suggest you get The Creation Answers Book
and in Chapter 4 there’s a
really good summary of the
things we’ve been talking about.
However if you want to go
into really in-depth, here’s
a book: Rocks Aren’t Clocks.
This is going to go
into all kinds of detail.
But if you prefer
to watch a video
as you probably do since
you’re tuned in to youtube here
here’s a video that’s on DVD as
well as a video download that
you can get at creation.com  :
Radioactive Dating
and a Young Earth
by Dr James Mason who is a
experimental nuclear physicist.
You might say he knows
a little bit about this, right?
So I hope you’ll dig in and learn
more at our website creation.com
It’s been great. Thank
you Joel. Thank you.
And we’ll see you next
time on Creation.com Talk.