[Music]
You may have heard about the
infamous Miller-Urey experiment back in 1953,
in which electricity was added to
certain gases under specialized conditions.
This was intended to show how
life could spontaneously arise without God.
But the experiment
actually showed that it took
a great deal of
intelligence to set up conditions
that produced mostly a lot
of tar and just a few amino acids.
This is a long way from a living self.
Here are some of the
problems with that experiment.
First, there were
starting assumptions about what
gases would have been
present on the primordial Earth,
and these didn't
include oxygen, which tends to
destroy chemical bonds,
preventing anything from forming.
Now, since then, evidence indicates
that oxygen likely was present at the time.
So because it didn't
accurately simulate the Earth's atmosphere,
it's pretty much
irrelevant as an experiment,
and those amino
acids could not have formed.
Not only that, many
molecules required for life exist
in two forms that look
like mirror images of each other,
like your left and right hands.
This is called chirality,
from the Greek word for "hand."
The Miller-Urey experiment produced equal
amounts of left and
right-handed forms of amino acids.
Yeah, but all amino
acids and proteins are left-handed,
while all sugars in DNA and RNA
and in metabolic pathways are right-handed.
Random chemical
reactions won't produce 100%
left-handed amino
acids that are needed for life.
This is just one
example of thousands where
evolutionists have major
problems explaining how life originated.
But evolution continues to be
promoted as established scientific fact.
It's not.
No.