[Music]
Let's talk about the
predictions made by activists, including the IPCC,
and compare them with the actual data. In the
1970s we were told, and many of you will remember
this, that we're heading for another Ice Age.
What scientists are telling
us now is that the threat of
an ice age is not as remote as they once thought.
At weather stations in the far north temperatures
have been dropping for 30 years. Sea coasts long
free of summer ice are now blocked year
round. According to some climatologists
within a lifetime we might
be living the next Ice Age.
That didn't happen. Oops! But some of the
same experts who predicted global cooling
started talking about global warming.
But then again those predictions didn't
materialize so today it's just called
climate change. It's just climate change
For example 2008 Dr Tim Flannery, from the
Australian government's climate change unit said,
"Just imagine yourself in a world five years from
now [so that would be 2013 2013] when there's no
more ice over the Arctic." That same year Al
Gore made a similar prediction. That was the
common view of the mainstream climate scientists
at the time. Now, the minimum annual coverage of
Arctic sea ice has declined from a high of
about 7.5 million square kilometers in 1990.
But it was actually higher in 2020 than it was in
2012, at near nearly 4 million square kilometers.
And that's a lot of ice. So the
predictions were way off. And,
by the way, fluctuations in the amount of
Arctic ice over time are expected. This was
especially true after the post-flood
Ice Age a few thousand years ago.