Other arguments include that the
preborn child is just a clump of cells,
or that embryos pass through various
evolutionary stages
on the way to becoming human.
By that logic, one might be
aborting a fish or a reptile rather than a human.
But that notion
comes from a long-discredited
evolutionary argument based on
fraudulent drawings by Ernst Haeckel.
While this idea may still show up in
an occasional biology, text, or online video,
most evolutionists
know it's completely false.
Even if it were
true, the notion that an embryo
can be aborted while
it's in a fish or reptile state
implies that it becomes more
valuable when it reaches human form.
Well, this runs contrary to evolution.
But what about the
so-called clump of cells?
Even the first fertilized
egg has its own unique DNA code
that's distinctly human
and different from both parents.
So not the mother's body.
This new life will
follow these pre-programmed
instructions to grow
and develop into a human baby,
and eventually a full-grown adult.
Science has shown that birth changes
where the child is, not what the child is.
Psalm 139:13-14
reads, "For you formed my inward parts.
You knitted me
together in my mother's womb.
I praise you, for I am
fearfully and wonderfully made."
I love it when
science catches up with the Bible.
Yeah, me too.