greetings everybody welcome to another
edition of creation talk and today's
subject will be
how did noah fit all the animals onto
the ark
my name is dr matthew chihari and so
with me is uh keaton halle hello
hey there matthew and so today's subject
is about how
all the animals could fit on those orc
is a very interesting question because
it raises a lot of doubt into people's
mind as to whether
noah's ark was real whether it was
really feasible
yeah it's obviously something that we've
uh if you grew up in church like
like i did uh you may have learned a lot
about this in sunday school
singing songs about um how the rains
came down and the floods came up
and uh noah going onto the arky arkey
but at the same time it's a challenging
subject for adults
because this is one of the most attacked
areas of scripture right
and of course uh secular uh people in
the secular media
they see a lot of things against the
noah's ark for example that
the ark was very smart it was very
unstable and that
of course what uh some biologists also
say is that while we know that there are
10 million species all across the world
how could they fit onto noah so i mean
it's impossible yeah so let's talk about
this how it really is possible for all
the animals to
fit onto the ark and a lot of times we
talk about misconceptions that people
have
i mean if somebody says to the believer
how did noah fit all the animals on the
ark we can say
ask them in return well how large was
noah's ark and
how many animals did he need to take
right exactly exactly
and so i mean uh i i believe that the
bible has the answer to our questions
so let's look at what the bible says in
genesis
chapter 6 verse 15 noah's orc was
actually very large it was 300 by 30 by
50 cubits and one cubit being 18 inches
cubits basically the length of
somebody's forearm right um
from elbow to fingertip yeah exactly in
ancient times they had different
standardized measurements so we don't
know for sure how long the cube it was
that noah used but it's
it's on the order of a foot and a half
or 18 inches like you said
and so of course if we uh calculate the
volume it comes up to 1.5 million
cubic feet and that really is humongous
yeah noah's ark the real arc would have
been longer than a
than a football field right about maybe
450 feet long is
300 cubits times a foot and a half right
and then according to other measurements
they say that it's about the size of an
ocean liner if somebody's familiar with
the queen elizabeth
ii that's about about the size or at
least on the order of the size of what
the orc was like
yeah so it's very different from the
picture that people might have if
they're just thinking of
the the visuals that they've seen before
on nursery walls and things where noah's
ark looks like
an overcrowded bathtub with giraffe
snacks all the time it's very unstable
but you know
actually korean scientists creation
creationists they did a study
and they they floated these different uh
like types of like
different ship models they found that
noah's ark was which is like in the
shape of a brick uh it was
a single most stable uh shape of a boat
for riding on the turbulent waters
of of the flood so it was very stable
and the dimensions are specifically
given in genesis chapter six
we know it was a six to one ratio which
is you know still the way many modern
ocean liners are built built to those
dimensions yeah
yeah okay so this was one myth that we
just plastered
out of the water let's take a look at
another myth that people
come up with did noah really take on
board
every single species of animal did he
did really do that
yeah well the the bible doesn't use that
term species at least not in the modern
technical
scientific sense um it rather uses the
word kind
uh matthew of course you're an expert on
on the biblical kinds that's your
your special field of research yeah
because that means that you know the
bible doesn't use our modern
concept of taxonomy whether we should
let the bible speak for itself
so a kind it's a broader category of
animals
it corresponds maybe to the level of
genus or a family
and even even evolutionists have found
that if you go above the level of
family you can't really cluster or group
animals together
so at the level of genus or family
animals and different plants
they they cluster very nicely together
into these into these uh
what you're saying you know if people
don't aren't familiar with these
scientific
taxonomic categories species is kind of
a narrow
category a genus would be broader than
that and the family would be even
broader and their families bigger and
we're saying the kind
probably corresponds more to the family
or genus level rather than the species
so that means you can have many
different species within each biblical
kind because god
built into the kind a lot of potential
for for variation yeah for example you
could take
uh let's say the dark kind or the cat
kind or the horse kind these are all
different kinds
you can recognize a kind very
intuitively and for example
like in the past few hundred years
they've read like several hundred dog
dog breeds starting from like the wolf
and so
uh if we if we you know go with a single
kind covering
several hundred species then that means
you know this 10 million species of
animals on the ark
it gets gets reduced to a very small
number
in fact he just brought the kinds right
so instead of bringing
two great danes to dachshunds to
dalmatians etc he just brought two
canines basically would include not only
you know from that original pair on the
ark developed our modern varieties
uh domestic dogs as well as wolves and
coyotes and dingoes and so forth
and also according to creation
scientists john wooden wrap he
wrote a book called noah's orca
feasibility study and he estimated that
noah had to take on wood only a
thousand kinds a male on the female of
each kind so
that really really reduces the number of
animals making some assumptions but
that's
probably a reasonable approximation if
it's between
um the family and the genus level where
the where the biblical kind falls
so it's not millions of species just two
of each kind
greatly reduces the number of animals
that know how to take yeah
and of course uh according to genesis
chapter six verses 19 to 20.
uh noah didn't have to take on word fish
or insects he took on board the
the oaf that is the the birds and the
behemoth which are
land animals the vertebrates and so i
mean
the creatures in the ocean could survive
a global flood just fine so
noah just took the land vertebrates yeah
exactly i mean fish
many species of fish i mean of course
with the flood uh fresh water and salt
water would have mixed but many uh fish
species like a stickleback they're
capable of surviving in both
salt and also fresh water so that's not
the only problem for them
otherwise i mean uh when the flood
happened it would have crushed a lot of
a lot of trees and there would have been
a lot of log mats just an interesting
point that uh when i studied taxonomy at
university
they said that the way different
reptiles got from mainland south america
to
the galapagos island was that they
floated on these log mats on these tree
mats
all the way across the ocean to the
galapagos so even
secular biologists don't have a problem
with this
yeah yeah and lastly some people also
say that uh
that um we have these big dinosaur
species and you know can you imagine
like a big brontosaurus with this big
tail and it's a big neck in the or how
do these animals fit on the work
yeah well we certainly do believe that
the dinosaurs would have had their
representative kinds
on board uh but if people think well the
dinosaurs are just too big
once again we can go back to well the
arc was absolutely enormous on the one
hand
but then we can consider the the size of
the dinosaurs
on the other hand and actually um
there's a variety of things that we
could point to there
first even once dinosaurs were full
grown not all
got to be as big as the great sauropods
like brachiosaurus and so forth some
were
the size of chickens you know the
compsignation is a very small dinosaur
and so you average it out it might be
something more like the size of a pony
uh the dinosaurs as a whole as a group
um yeah so seriously seeing that
basically these these
big sized uh dinosaurs they're really
the exception
as a series exactly okay
we can also consider did noah have to
bring these full-sized adult dinosaurs
or might he have taken younger specimens
we know for example scientists who have
studied growth patterns
in in the bones of dinosaurs they've
been able to determine that at least
many of them
underwent a growth spurt in their
adolescent years and so it would make
sense
sort of for nowhere to take younger
dinosaurs like hatchlings hatchlings
yeah or maybe just before that growth
spurt so that they can
reproduce after the flood yeah you
certainly don't want to bring older
dinosaurs that are past their
their the age where they can reach that
that makes a lot of sense i mean so in
summary we can see that
noah's ark was very large and of course
uh um
there would have been space left over
even for for food
or for drinking water yeah and the bible
tells us he took plants on board as well
yeah and also so that means that the ark
was huge and that also
uh uh um as against popular
misconception
uh he didn't have to take on board like
lots and lots of animals
some could uh survive outside the ark so
it means that
there is a lot of evidence to show that
uh putting all these animals
you know uh is very feasible yeah
yeah so the bible really stands up to
the the
scrutiny of the skeptics the challenges
that they throw at the bible
actually it's consistent with what we
know from science today when you
understand the account correctly
right so that means that basically uh we
shouldn't listen to just one side of
the story of like atheists being
bringing up all these
all these uh content uh alleged
contradictions
if we uh make an examination ourselves
and we can we see that
that that science really really supports
what the bible says
yeah so that means that you can trust
your bible amen
yeah there's another question that
skeptics also raise about no ozark is
that they're really millions and
millions of species of insects
now did noah take on wood each and every
single insect species or
how is this yeah well again of course
there's the distinction between
kinds and species so noah would have um
for all the animals that he did take he
only had to take the kinds
but with insects in particular what the
bible says is that noah took
the animals in whose nostrils was the
breath of life
and so um insects don't have nostrils or
or breathe in the same way that we do
they breathe through little um holes in
their skin called spiracles
you know basically they they probably
don't qualify uh to the bibles this is
as high as higher cognitive life forms
yeah they're not land vertebrates
they're not the animals that the bible
is thinking of and so
well if they weren't on board the ark
though then how could they survive a
worldwide flood
there are lots of ways they could have
floated on massive vegetation and things
without
necessarily having to be obligate
passengers on board yeah i tried it
uh keaton thank you very much for your
discussion my pleasure
right and now this was just one topic
related to noah's ark we can talk about
so many
so many different things for example uh
what about the ice age
where did the flood waters go and so if
you want uh
answers to similar questions please
visit our website
creation.com and you can do a search and
you can look through
a lot of articles that we heard about
about the noah's ark and similar things
and so if you uh if you like this
production please hit the like button
and then you can also subscribe to start
receiving a similar
similar content and also if you'd like
then you can join
the comments below and thank you very
much for your attention
you