Welcome to Creation Talk.
Today we’ll be
answering the question
“How did saltwater and
freshwater fish survive the Flood?”
Welcome to Creation Talk.
My name is Joel Tay,
and this is Dr Robert Carter.
Hey Joel.
Hi.
Today we are dealing
with this question.
Sometimes we are asked,
“How did freshwater and
saltwater fish survive the Flood?”
Why do people even
ask this question?
Well, most people know that
freshwater fish don’t survive in salt water.
And when you read Scripture
—in fact I’ve got it right here,
ready to go—
Genesis chapter 7 verse 19,
“And the waters prevailed
so mightily on the earth that
all the high mountains under
the whole heaven were covered.”
And this is the Flood?
This is during the Flood.
And what it means is that
the oceans overwhelmed all
the freshwater places on land,
setting up a massive problem:
Doesn’t that mean all the
freshwater fish would go extinct
if it really was a global Flood?
So how does a fish survive
in salt water or fresh water?
Is it just a biology question?
It’s partially a biology question.
It’s partially a time question.
But the biology is
actually really interesting.
Most fish are what
are called ‘stenohaline’.
What’s that?
That means they can only
survive in fresh water or salt water.
That is true today.
Okay.
But a lot of fish are
called ‘euryhaline’.
They can go either way.
The famous one is salmon.
Salmon? Yes.
They’re called ‘anadromous’.
They spend most
their time in salt water
but they go into
fresh water to spawn.
But sturgeon, smelt,
some stingrays,
famously the bull shark,
bullshark can swim hundreds
of miles up the Mississippi,
hundreds of miles up the Amazon,
So you can actually get a
shark attack in fresh water.
Yeah!
And so …
There’s a lot of species that do that.
But then, on the other way there’s
some fish that are called ‘catadromous’.
Yes.
They spend most of the time in fresh water
and then they come into salt water to spawn.
like the North American
and the European eel—
famous for for doing that.
And there’s another fish
called the barramundi, from Asia.
And there are actually some
populations of barramundi now
that never go back
into fresh water.
So they have adapted, they have changed,
into a new environment?
Is that what you’re saying?
Yeah.
But, fish do struggle with salt.
I mean a saltwater fish is constantly
drinking and constantly excreting salt.
If they don’t do that the salt in
the water will overwhelm them.
There’s a lot less salt in
fish meat than in the water.
Okay.
The opposite is
true in fresh water.
A freshwater fish has
to constantly urinate.
He’s absorbing water through
his gills and he’s got to get rid of it
because there’s a lot less salt in
fresh water than there is in fish meat.
So this is two completely
different biological processes?
Yeah. They’re struggling in
different ways with salt concentration.
But some fish can
swim from salt water,
they take a day or two to adjust,
now they’re in fresh water
and vice versa.
So Rob didn’t you tell me a story
about you trying to grow
freshwater fish in a saltwater tank
or something like that?
Actually what I said was,
during my years of marine biology
when I had to start
a saltwater tank
um,
a lot of times when
you start a tank
there’s a lot of chemical
changes and fish tend to die
and so you don’t want to put an expensive
saltwater fish in your brand new tank.
What you do is you go to the aquarium
store and get a freshwater molly,
for a dollar
Uh-hm.
and use that fish
to start off your tank
because a molly works
great in salt water.
Now you don’t want to just throw
him in the salt water, he’d probably die.
So if you slowly add salt water
to the container the fish is in
over a couple of hours,
you just release him and he’ll be just
fine in salt water for the rest of his life.
So how does that
fish help the tank?
By eating and by excreting he’s
producing nutrients for the bacteria.
So beneficial bacteria,
that sort of thing?
Yeah, so you can start building
up a bacterial population in the tank.
If you just throw a whole bunch of
fish into a fish tank without bacteria
ready they’ll pollute themselves.
So what you did is you
slowly changed the water
and let it adapt from
fresh water to salt water?
Yeah.
And then you finally add
in with a saltwater fish.
Yeah then just put
them in the fish tank.
Pure salt water.
They’ll do just fine.
So for the fish that can
only survive in fresh water
or only survive in salt water,
how do we explain that if the Flood
is only a few thousand years ago?
How … Why are they like that now?
There’s actually a lot … there’s several
different important things to consider.
When we’re just …
Talking about fresh water—
that’s really the problem.
It’s not the saltwater fish, it’s the
freshwater fish that are the problem.
Why is that?
Because the oceans are salty
and if the oceans come up onto land
then it’s not a problem with the
saltwater fish, during the Flood.
It’s the freshwater fish that
live on land during the Flood
that we have a problem with.
So how do we get
freshwater fish today?
I mean fish that only
survive in fresh water.
There’s several different ways.
First of all,
just because a fish species
today can’t tolerate salt water
doesn’t mean its ancestors
couldn’t tolerate salt water.
So you’re saying that they
used to be able to tolerate both
and they kind of lose one ability?
Quite possibly.
If you have a fish species living way up
in the Amazon and it never sees salt water,
well if there’s a gene that
helps to tolerate salt water
and that gene gets deleted
or broken or something
it doesn’t affect the fish.
So you’re telling me that
fish changed very quickly
after the time of the Flood,
a few thousand years ago
and they specialized because
they lost some ability to adapt
to either salt or fresh water.
Is that what you’re saying?
Ah, that’s exactly what I’m saying.
A lot of adaptation that we see
is a loss of ability to do something,
a species getting
fine-tuned to an environment.
But once it becomes
fine-tuned and highly specialized
well it’s not a generalist anymore,
and
it would have actually have a problem
living in some of the environments
that its ancestors could live in.
Okay this is kind of
interesting because I think
a lot of people have this idea that
evolution believes in change and
creation doesn’t believe in change
but you’re telling me that the Word of God,
the Bible, tells us that
creatures would have
to adapt very quickly.
So it’s actually the creation …
—if I’m getting,
if I’m getting this right—
creationists are actually the
ones who believe in rapid changes.
Yes.
And evolutionists are the ones
who believe in slow changes.
Yes. And the reason they
believe in slow changes is because
Charles Darwin told us it takes a long time
and species change over millions of years.
So change over time is
consistent with the Word of God,
rapid changes in fact.
Yeah. The issue is that the
word evolution means change.
Uh-hm.
And so a lot of people, when they
ask them for a definition of evolution
they say “Oh, evolution is
just change over time”.
Yeah, it’s true. I mean all my textbooks,
they define evolution as change over time.
Yeah!
But that’s the lamest possible definition
because I believe in change over
time and I’m not even an evolutionist.
Oh, and like you say,
we believe in rapid change over time.
Yeah!
So just because there’s change
doesn’t mean evolution is true because
evolution is really a belief in
the common ancestry of all things.
Ah!
So really that
definition should be:
‘Enough change over enough time
can theoretically lead to the
common ancestry of all things.’
So why don’t they define
evolution as common ancestry?
I don’t know and it’s frustrating
because what if the
change is downhill?
What if the changes go backwards?
What if we see fish getting bigger and
fish getting smaller over over decades
because of different
environmental pressures?
That’s not any sort of a
common ancestry argument.
That’s just God and his brilliance.
When He created the species,
He created them to be able to adapt.
Okay …
So adaptations and change,
rapid change is an argument for design?
For design! For the smartness of God who put
into his creation the ability to do that.
And even when you
see the fish change
by losing the ability to adapt
to either salt or fresh water
that would be a loss.
Yeah.
So that’s what I mean by downhill.
Yeah. Most of the changes
we see are actually downhill.
They’re … It’s purging away
information that’s not needed,
or something breaking
and that’s the types
of adaptation we see.
We’ve written a lot about that.
There’s tons of
stuff on creation.com
Natural Selection Q&A page,
Speciation Q&A page.
It’s just part of
the creation model.
Oh, that’s wonderful.
So … But does salt water
and fresh water mix together?
Only sort of.
And you’re hinting at something
that I told you earlier today.
When Europeans
discovered the Amazon …
Yes.
they weren’t in sight of land.
They weren’t in sight of land?
They were not in sight of land.
So where were they?
They were way out in the ocean,
in a sailboat
and as they’re sailing across
the ocean they crossed some
water they had a different color
and they said wait a
minute—this is fresh water!
So they turned and sailed right
into the mouth of the Amazon.
They were way over the horizon.
They might have
been 50 miles offshore.
I don’t know how far
offshore they were,
but it was a long way and they just
followed the fresh water into the Amazon.
So there was fresh water more than …
like way out there,
and it did not mix
with the salt water?
That’s right, because fresh
water isn’t as dense as salt water.
Salt makes the salt water heavier and the
fresh water tends to float on salt water.
And sometimes it can
float for a very long time
Okay, so why would this be something
that we would consider when we talk
about the worldwide Flood?
Because the rain that came down during
the Flood would have been fresh water.
And theoretically, possibly we
could get a freshwater lens on top
of the oceans during the Flood
which would provide an
environment for fish to survive
if they were fish that could
not survive in salt water.
And that water would not mix very quickly.
It would take a while for it to …
It depends on the
salinity difference,
it depends on the
temperature difference
it depends on how
much stirring there is.
Oh, that’s interesting.
But it can last for a long time.
In fact if there was a lot of
vegetation floating on the water
Uh-hm.
that vegetation can have
fresh water on top of it.
You know, a giant log mat maybe 100 miles
across with lots of branches and leaves,
fresh water on top.
But it can also,
as the fresh water soaks in
you can get a freshwater
lens underneath it.
Oh wow!
So there’s tons of
places for fishes to hide
but it might also be
—backing up a step—
Uh-hm.
that they could survive in both
fresh and salt water initially.
And then they lose one ability.
Yeah.
So there’s tons of options here.
In fact there’s so many options
it’s not really a problem like it
sounds when it’s first postulated.
Just to summarize what
we have covered so far:
first of all we have explained that
evolution is not change over time
That’s right.
because creationists
believe in change
and actually change that’s much
faster than what evolutionists believe.
That’s right.
And we also mentioned that salt and
fresh water can exist in the same place,
because they may not
always mix together.
That’s right.
So we have mentioned that
salt and fresh water can
exist in the same place
one floating on top of the other
and they won’t mix as
quickly as they could.
We have also mentioned that
fish at the beginning could perhaps
live in both salt and fresh water.
They were designed to adapt.
So after the Flood some fish might
have actually lost the ability to
go between both environments.
Yeah.
So I guess that answers
the question we have,
“How do fresh and saltwater
fish survive the Flood?”
Thank you Rob.
We hope you enjoyed
this video and discussion.
Join us on creation.com
Go to our website.
If you like this discussion, type into
our search engine ‘freshwater fish’.
We have a good
article waiting for you.
We have a few other videos that’s
related to this discussion as well.
And leave your comments there.
We would love to hear your thoughts
on what you think about this discussion;
did we answer your question?
And if you’d like to listen
to us while you’re driving,
subscribe to our audio podcast.
Thank you.