at creation ministries international we
take a look at the physical evidence
that we see in the world and
show how it supports the historical
account of the bible
hello i'm scott gillis i'm here today
with my friend and associate uh dr
jonathan starfady how you doing
everyone good well listen today we're
going to be talking about
the bible you know and of course it's
our final authority as
as believers right it should be but
whether it is to a lot of people is not
a matter but definitely should be
right and yet there's many that claim
that the bible is not historical
and they'll even specifically say that
genesis was written to be poetic to be
poetry
what did we say to that well i'd say
they don't really understand the
difference between poetry and potatoes
if they think that because they clearly
don't understand what hebrew poetry
look like it's not about rhyme or rhythm
but about something called parallelism
all right well let's just for the sake
of argument assume
that genesis might be poetry we know
that's not the case but just for the
sake of argument
if that were the case what would it look
like well we have
uh something in in the hebrew bible
which definitely is poetic and that's
the book of psalms and also you have the
book of proverbs but let's look at the
book of psalms the most obvious one
yeah so in fact i'll even turn here to
psalms
uh chapter 19 it's talking about
creation
if you don't mind i'll just read a
couple verses here sure all right
so in psalms 19 verse 1 and 2 it says
the heavens declare the glory
of god and the sky above proclaims his
handiwork
day to day pours out speech and night to
night reveals knowledge so
what are we seeing here that's poetic
explain that to me
see hebrew poetry is not about rhyme or
rhythm but as i said about
parallelism and you you just illustrated
that because
parallelism means saying one thing and
then saying the same thing
using different words so for example
where it says the heavens declare the
glory of god
and the sky above proclaims his
handiwork is that kind of what you mean
right
the sky and the heavens mean the same
thing
or the rakia or the expanse depending on
what translation you use
but they are clearly the same thing
because of the rakia the
expanse is called the heavens in the
book of genesis so clearly you're saying
using the same
different words to mean the same thing
and they're about doing the same thing
they're both declaring god's glory
and day to day and night to night mean
the same thing it means the entire
24-hour cycle so all the time so see
what i mean
about same thing being said but
different words and you look at that
all throughout the poetic books you have
this parallelism all the way through
so this is what genesis would look like
if it were poetry but you can read it
yourself
yeah it doesn't sound like that at all
nothing like it i know there's one
passage that some people might
might argue with i think it's here in
genesis chapter 4 verses 23 and 4.
and there it says lameck said to his
wife ada
and zillah hear my voice you wives of
lamech
listen to what i say i have killed a man
for wounding me a young man for striking
me
if kane's revenge is seven-fold then
lemex is
77-fold now that sounds a little like
poetry
and i think it really is poetry and
notice this is lamech bragging to his
two wives about
how what a big hero he is in killing a
young man
um notices audiences just as two wise a
pretty safe person to bring
people to break to but the point is that
someone quotes it but you look at the
rest of the narrative it's nothing like
that that's why
this stands out is something quite odd
it's clearly something being quoted it's
not the narrative itself
in fact it sort of proves the point that
it stands out so much as being poetry
it stands in such contrast that it shows
that the rest of genesis is nothing at
all like poetry
right um going back into psalms i
remember a verse that you've referred to
before
in psalm 104 which actually is dealing
with both creation and the flood
so i'm here in psalm 104 verses 5
through 9
where it's talking about creation then
the flood it says he set the earth on
its foundation
so that it shall never be moved you
covered it with the deep
as with a garment the water stood above
the mountains
at your rebuke they fled at the sound of
your thunder they took flight
the mountains rose and the valley sank
down to the place that you appointed for
them
you set a boundary that they may not
pass
so that they may not again cover the
earth
now i hear this parallelism in there and
since it's talking about
creation and the flood which is where
they get that from genesis 1 11 that
yeah
if god was going to write it poetically
it would sound a lot like that well i'd
say that
psalm 104 leaves the first part of it is
a poetic version of genesis 1 but also
incorporates some things from genesis 2.
so clearly regarded them as
by the same the same accounts not
contradictory creation accounts for some
104 harmonizes though but clearly that's
what it would look like if it was poetic
but genesis 1 doesn't look like that
so clearly you don't write poetry about
poetry
it's a bit redundant you have poetry
written about history so psalm 104 is
the
poetic version genesis 1 is the
historical version
now for the sake of argument although it
is the truth
let's say genesis was history well then
what would that look like
well again we have plenty of accounts in
the bible
that noaa disputes were at least
intended to be history and they have a
particular pattern of verbs like you
have
the first verb is always something
called the
carl perfect it's a complicated thing
but then you have
throughout you have a type of verb
called the valve consecutive it's called
the preterite
the hebrew germans value total that's
what you find all throughout
the historical books okay you're gonna
have to explain that to me okay
five consecutive can you kind of explain
that to us um okay now
see vav is a hebrew letter it means on
its own it means and but when it's
tacked onto a verb
it means then okay uh so if you have
a verb like victor it means then he
killed that's the the model versus then
something happened you see it's the
verb used to narrate a sequence of
historical events so that's why it's
found in historical narrative parts of
the bible
so now let's apply this to genesis right
and um
first of all you have in the beginning
god created this
type of verb that's found at the
beginning of the narrative
then you have vaio mera which means and
god said
let there be life there and there was
light and
god called it was good these are all
valve consecutive over 20 of them
in the first chapter alone yeah
so and dr stephen boyd is a hebrew
scholar he actually did a huge analysis
of verb patterns in the historical
and the poetic books and he found that
jared genesis
correlated completely with the
historical books
and not with the poetic books with a
probability of 0.9999497
now one is certainty zero is
impossibility to give you an idea so
it's almost
as a certainty that this is meant to be
a historical narrative
so clearly from a literary standpoint
genesis is history hands down the odds
are
are not just in favor but they're
certain that that's the case
and yet so many people that that do
believe
somehow they believe the bible is
authoritative but they still take that
position
why do you think so well i think the
only reason they can possibly take it is
because they're intimidated by
uniformitarian science which is
basically saying
that there wasn't a flood in the past so
we have to go to lot
slow and gradual changes and therefore
the earth must be millions of years old
to explain the rocks and fossils
we see so when you look at the christian
scholars
who want to say genesis is not does not
mean what it says often they will admit
it certainly looks like six literal days
but certainly looks like
six thousand years a global flood but it
can't be that way because of
science so it must be something else it
must not be history it must be poetry so
they force that paradigm
on the text yeah if you go to a previous
episode where gary bateson talked about
hugh ross uh he wants to say the days of
creation were billions of years long
okay that's one
era when we dealt with that and this is
another way of trying to fudge
the obvious facts of genesis by saying
it's not really meant to be history
and i know we've often talked about how
the new testament authors and even jesus
himself when they're referencing
the old testament which is quite often
right
but they see it as historical they don't
see it as any kind of metaphor or poetry
right
well a lot of examples and i think
there's a future video that
you're doing with our new testament
specialist leader cossa on this very
thing and she knows what she's talking
about in that area
but just a few things to mention uh when
jesus talked about marriage he goes to
genesis 1 27 and 224 and clearly regards
as a historical narrative the basis of a
man
woman marriage he goes to the flood as a
warning as a future judgment
the flood was real though was real the
ark was real in fact
every time the new testament authors
refer to
genesis they clearly take the people as
historical
the time frame is historical even the
order of events as historical they
clearly not treating it as mythological
it's clearly treated as historical
so if jesus and those new testament
testament authors took it as historical
we should be doing the same thing i mean
surely isn't the christian follower of
christ and that should mean following
him
in his belief about genesis i can't see
how you can say it any other way i mean
maybe i'm not saying you're not a
christian if you don't believe it take
genesis to the truth i think you've got
a problem
because you're going again against what
jesus himself said yeah
it reminds me of a passage in the new
testament
in uh the third chapter of john which of
course people
uh quote john 3 16 all all the time but
here just a few verses earlier when
jesus is addressing nicodemus he said
if i've told you earthly things and you
do not believe
how can you believe if i tell you
heavenly things
and of course genesis is dealing with
not only earthly things but really the
creation of the world
exactly what he did historically and
when we don't believe him there
it makes us question the rest of the
bible and the gospel
right does it also affect how you go
about witnessing because of the skeptic
you're talking to
sees you don't really believe the bible
in genesis
he might as well when does god start
telling the truth why should i believe
him about the
stories of jesus rise from the dead
because that goes against science too
doesn't it
right and so that opens the door to not
only
uh to question all kinds of other
doctrines that are firmly in the bible
and that's kind of happening in the
church today isn't it
it's been happening for over a hundred
years that when they abandoned genesis
the next generations are banned as a lot
of new testament truths even
going so far as to reject the
resurrection right
and isn't that what jesus told that that
rich man and lazarus
and jesus quoted abraham saying if they
don't listen to moses and the prophets
they would be convinced by someone
rising from indeed we're seen that
yes in the liberal cemetery i mean
seminaries
well you know there's a lot of uh
sections on our website where you can
learn more about this idea about is
genesis history some of the search words
you could do is
just that is genesis history we also
have an article
entitled yes genesis really is
historical narrative
and genesis means what it says i'd also
like to let you know that
dr sarfati here actually made a a dvd a
video called six days really
it's going to go into details and of
course your book
genesis account here it's going to go
into more detail than you even knew
existed on this very subject and of
course the genesis academy dvd series
that accompanies it oh you look for a
speaker aren't you
i'm one and you are yeah we have quite a
bit of people on there so please
subscribe to our podcast
as dr stefani mentioned there's going to
be a
subsequent episode where we're going to
talk about how the new testament authors
and even jesus himself believed that
genesis was history
so thanks for watching creation.com talk
and we'll see you next time