today's topic is a highly controversial
one
we're going to be discussing did
dinosaurs have
feathers
[Music]
i'm dr robert carter i'm in the studio
today with my dear friend dr jonathan
sarfati well thank you for having me on
on here thank you you're welcome this
could be a lot of fun you and i have had
a lot of very long discussions on this
topic right we've co-authored
an article a major creation paper on
this topic too
we did and yet there's still a lot of
arguing
uh between the creationists and
evolutionists even some within the
creation of creationist community on the
subject of feathered dinosaurs
it is true although i must admit some of
the people in the creation community
have never actually addressed
what we wrote about in our paper this is
true we addressed
everything the evolutionists had list to
our best attempt
well yes of course yes okay so so right
on the surface
everyone needs to know yes there's some
controversy here
fair enough all right so let's let's
deal with this controversy openly
yep and let's see maybe we can unpack
this and help the audience understand
some of the implications and what parts
of this are important and what parts are
it
that's a good idea yeah i like to ask my
audiences this i'm going to ask you this
does it matter if dinosaurs had feathers
probably not in the long term actually
because the bible doesn't say one way or
the other
so creationists are perfectly entitled
to have feathered dino so it doesn't
make them any less creationists that
they propose this
exactly that's my answer too i want to
know i'm a nerd i'm a scientist i want i
want to know the answer
but in the end if dinosaurs have
feathers or not doesn't change
anything it so it doesn't mean that
flying birds ever evolved from
dinosaurs or that's the second question
did birds evolve from dinosaurs
completely separate questions
okay so a lot of fun stuff where do we
start here
um looking at the ancient fossil record
good place to go i think yeah there are
clearly animals
with beautiful feathers oh sure yeah and
you know the
dinosaur era rocks we have very
bird-like things with beautiful feathers
do we have anything like that in a
dinosaur
well that's the debatable point isn't it
because there's a certain
uh fossil characteristic the bone the
skeletal characteristics of a dinosaur
one thing
is a fancy name called perforate
acetabulum that's
okay acetabulum is the latin for little
vinegar cup because that's where three
bones of the hip
meet and in most creatures it's a cup
shape
okay where the femur is a process from
the femur that
articulates into that cup shape now
dinosaurs were unique in that this is
actually
a hole there open or perforate okay okay
we'll back
way up okay okay i understand exactly
what you're saying
right i don't think most people
listening i understand this so
you're saying that dinosaur hips are
different than hips of other animals
with that hole there instead of a cup
shape thing okay yes
okay so so dinosaurs have what's called
a perforate
acetabularium acetabulum
acetabulum okay okay okay yeah okay so i
knew that i was just
and that's so a dinosaur is set apart
from other animals
based on the hip socket that's one major
one of the men there's also things in
the skull holes in the skull but okay
that's one of the big differences so
when we look at these fossil bird-like
things
dinosaurs are not that's the question
that is one of the questions yes okay
i guess the other thing is what are the
things claimed to be feathers
so sometimes i see no doubt they're
obviously fearless in fact they're
obviously
flight feathers other times like
archaeopteryx a classic one even back in
the 1800s
yeah it had flight feathers like a
pigeon has today and
by a flight feather what we mean is it's
a feather
and it's also it's wider on one side
than the other
right and you can tell where you know if
it's left or right depending upon
the asymmetry birds don't have feathers
that are symmetrical
all the feathers anyway right on the
wing is definitely asymmetric feathers
okay and very
highly strong amazing structure but bob
and then the the
central shaft the bob's coming off and
barbells and hooks connecting it's
actually quite a
elaborate design and feathers actually
that brings up another very interesting
point too
the difference between a scale and a
feather
now what is a scale well scale is just a
fold in the skin
and we can tell that because when like
when the snake you know
peels the skin off there's the scales
right there
i got scales in the back of my hand here
if you look really carefully under a
microscope okay
so scales are folds in the skin
what is a feather well feather starts
with
follicles so if there's anything you
think the feathers evolve from mammalian
hairs because they both start from
follicles in the skin
and poke out from those it's very
different from a scale so one of the
defining characteristics of a mammal
is that we have these these tubes in our
skin and from those tubes
comes this very complicated thing called
a hair which is made of protein
yep now feathers are sort of like a
hyper complex hair
right because they have to be in a tube
and they when they come out then they
unfold into these unbelievably cool
structures
and quite amazing and also you've got
some which are very decorative like the
peacock feather which means you've got
these things which have to be so
coordinated that
they form these patterns of circles and
heart-shaped things but it means every
fiber has to have the the dark parts in
the right place
to coordinate with the other one so it's
a lot of coordination to go with a
feather it's actually much more
complicated than one of our hairs
okay so it's really kind of funny to
think that feathers evolve from scales
because it's not true it had to evolve
from something more like a hair
yeah and reptiles don't have hairs okay
and i think there are some flightless
birds but you tend the flight the spurs
tend to have more hair like
yeah feathers because i don't need the
structure for flight anymore in fact
they could actually be harmful
so why not make it a simple thing so you
think of the feathers they're actually
much more hair-like so it's a case of
their feathers seem to be degenerate
forms of the more complex ones
as opposed to evolving from something
simple there's no evidence they evolved
from something simpler but there is
evidence that some could degenerate back
to something like a hair
that's one of the major problems that we
see with evolution in general
right it is easy to devolve something to
degenerate something to break something
um so if you had a beautiful feather you
get a mutation in it
and all of a sudden it doesn't work
anymore maybe that animal can't fly but
it might still be able to run
and also might be a good insulation
device or do you think of the insulation
the down the the down as you have those
feathers are actually very loose they're
not
joined together like the proper feathers
are yeah
but to go in the other direction that's
the hard part to go from nothing
to a feather i'm you're talking about an
incredibly highly engineered system
that has to be pre-planned its function
has to be known from the beginning
et cetera et cetera et cetera so we have
issues with the evolutionary story of
the evolution of feathers and the
evolution of
birds because birds also i mean one of
my favorite topics is the way birds
breathe
okay now we have a diaphragm we have a
muscle here that
pulls down it inflates our lungs okay
well reptiles don't do that
they move their liver that's called the
hepatic pump their liver moves up and
down and that pushes air in and out of
their lungs
that's weird it's weird but that's how
they do it
uh birds don't do either of those a bird
lung is a one-way system
there's a hole in the bottom of their
lung so their air goes through the lung
all the way through there's no dead
space
that's sufficient sounds like a super
efficient we the reason that
we can't fly one of the big reasons is
we will never be able to pull enough
oxygen out of the air
because most of our lung is dead space
the oxygen has to fuse down
the co2 has to diffuse out the bird has
no dead
space the air goes all the way through
comes out the bottom side
comes around so they might be breathing
in and out their neres
in their beak but their lungs are
radically different
and so the evolution of the bird long is
a massive problem because it's the first
step you're gonna poke a hole in the
bottom of the lung
so it's basically a hernia of a sword
and it's and that's
a creature with one of those is dead is
that yeah
i mean because natural selection can't
know that in millions of years from from
now it's going to become a nice
functioning bird lung it only functions
what it
has now so the origin of the bird lung
is
sounds pretty huge right yeah so bird
lungs
bird feathers yeah all these giant
evolutionary steps are majorly
problematic
right let me ask you a curveball
question though ooh okay
that's not on our list it's not on our
outline here totally curveball
if we were to classify birds what are
they most similar to
oh i mean that's an interesting question
because
they're not really similar to anything
there's no other animal that we know
that has
feathers so they're unique there and
they're warm blooded
they're warm blooders they're like
mammals in warm blood
in this they have a structure that comes
from a follicle like a mammal but they
lay eggs like a reptile does
and they lay hard eggs though like a
reptile i suppose
reptiles are soft eggs oh do they no
okay leather and
also don't burs they excrete uric acid
yes rather than urea like mammals do
yes okay but let me ask you let me turn
around the other direction here
okay what are humans most similar to
are we animals or plants or definitely
animals
within animals are we mammals yeah okay
we're mammals because we have
um live youngs um
we have breast feeding or the females of
our type do anyway yeah and we're
warm-blooded and we produce hair
okay amongst the mammals
are we more similar to monkeys or
squirrels
definitely monkeys right okay and
amongst the monkeys are we more similar
to
apes or lemurs differently the types
okay so we have no problem classifying
humans
right right next to the apes fine yeah i
think that's true from similarities from
similarities
okay i have no problem personally
classifying birds right next to reptiles
even as a subset of reptiles if the
taxonomists want to say that birds
cluster
underneath alligators underneath turtles
and within a certain group
of of of of dinosaurs even
okay i have no problem necessarily with
that that's just the way they cluster
using
using morphometry and and statistics and
they talk about archesaurs now as a big
overarching group including the
dinosaurs
yeah and birds being part of their celia
orcillosaur type
dinosaurs by just clustering
similarities yes
what i have a problem with is when they
talk about the non-avian dinosaurs
that's going way too far like we
wouldn't call us um hairless apes
or some people yeah some people would
and we disagree with them very strongly
right so it's not a question of um
who's more similar to whom it's a
question of is evolution possible
right and no evolution is not possible
mathematically physiologically
physically it's not going to happen but
still birds do
have some things if you look at a bird
foot i mean it's very similar to a
reptile foot
in some ways at least dinosaur foot in
some ways i don't care where they
classify them
in some ways they're different because
you've got the arch archiopt with a very
clear perching foot which is designed
for
branch perching yes because you've got
the various way the claws are designed
which i think a t-rex or um velociraptor
wouldn't have that sort of perching foot
that's right so but so the variations on
a foot theme
but it's a scaly footwood clause yeah
that's true
all right so we can put that aside also
then the next question
is what do we do with all these
feathered things in the fossil record
going back to earlier we didn't answer
the question
did dinosaurs have feathers well i'm
actually dispute there's anything
with proven dinosaur features like the
perforate acetabulum that has
undoubted feathers i agree as opposed to
say
um a crest like sinusoidal tricks seem
to have when you look at the
fossil these the fibers they've found
seem to be connected to something so
it's a single structure we're like a
crest
which and they were found near lakes so
i had to wonder if there's a crest of
some
sort of thing to help with swimming in
the water
um it doesn't look like they're fibre
supporting individual things like
feathers that's clearly they're combined
into a crest there so that's one thing
with um
so we do find some dinosaurs
with fuzzy like things yes at least
along their back and along their tail
right okay and they could or could not
be feathers but they're not
screaming this is a feather
like some of the obvious feathers that
we found in the fossil record yeah the
arcade is very obvious feathers and the
other thing is when you
look at archaeopteryx and even something
like confucius ornish which is a
feathered bird flying bird with a beak
when you use the evolutionary dating
methods they predate
the usual feathered dinosaur candidates
by
tens of millions of years often so it's
a case of uh
how does a grandfather be younger than
the grandson
it's a very interesting conundrum that
we don't have many
bird fossils because birds don't
preserve very well
hollow bones spray them yeah yeah but we
are finding more of them over time right
and the dates that they ascribe to them
have pushed birds back pretty close to
the point where they
the group that supposedly evolved into
birds evolved itself
and so i like to say so if birds evolve
from dinosaurs
when you might have run out of time well
especially when you haven't got the
usual candidates
in the fossil record to evolve them from
yeah
so timing issue is actually quite an
interesting problem that people like
evolutionary paleontologists like alan
feducci pointed out this problem that
the
the dates are not right even using their
dating systems
so there's no clear evolutionary
progression
from dinosaurs to birds well the other
thing is when you look at the way birds
uh run in fact they're there what you
think
is their knee joint is actually
correspond to our ankle jump because
their
thigh bone is actually inside their body
it's actually fused to their body
as part of their their avian lung system
that you talked about right so
i mean that's another thing we look at
the t-rex here the thigh comes out of
the body when you look at any bird the
thighs inside
so how do you go from one thing to the
other because it wouldn't be very good
for running if you
if your thigh got stuck inside your body
no i wouldn't
because surely you're trying to evolve a
fast running thing you'd have to fly
outside the body for leverage you want
to have very
very heavy hindquarters for the muscles
there but for a bird you want to
reduce your hindquarters so you've got
less weight to take off
if you think about all the muscular of a
bird is in its arms
they've what to do for the actually
massive flight muscles
but that's why we eat chicken breast
meat even and
that's because of their and it's yummy
it is
but we don't see any dinosaurs that are
front heavy
we look at t-rex with its very tiny
looking arms okay
they could curl 400 pounds but compared
to the size of their body
but then look at any bird with a
powerful wing the weight distribution is
totally wrong
to go from one thing to the other yeah
so even the select
the selection would actually favor the
fast running and not
the top heavy thing yeah because the top
everything would have a great
disadvantage
before it actually learned how to fly
just look at um look at something like a
an ostrich or an emu that has big old
back legs
very strong back legs and his tiny
little wings because they need to run
right and they run they can and they're
never going to re-evolve the ability to
fly if they ever lost the ability to fly
in the first place but they never
re-evolved the ability to fly because
they
can't that transition means they get
eaten and how they get their their
fine feathers back which aft after
degeneration so a lot of things
yeah it's not going to go in reverse
there's something else that
really bothers me in the feathered
dinosaur category
okay and that is most of the fossils are
coming from one particular place
a quarry in china oh my goodness and
one particular scientist has his name on
essentially every one of the papers
uh shushing i think it might be i don't
know how to pronounce that you did a
much better job than me but
that is a um a caution for me
and we've had a lot of scientific um
examples over the last couple of decades
of
you know one person who's cornered a
particular field
only to be brought down because of
incorrect reporting and things like that
i mean there are certainly dubious
fossils from that area because one of
the most
infamous was called archaeoraptor yeah
national geographic put on the front
page
oh and nature loved it but then it
turned out there was a complete pelt
down bird type thing
combining two different um fossils and
the way they figured that out is some
paleontologists went back to this quarry
and they said let's look for what's
called the counter slab
they only had one half the fossil let's
look for the other half the split part
and when they found it which they did
they realized it didn't match up so
someone had taken
a dinosaur and a bird a couple other
things and glued them together
and sold national geographic for a
couple of million dollars
and it wasn't true and you find i think
stores olson who is a curator of birds
is the smithsonian so real
a real bird expert really excoriated
national geographic
and nature for being so tied up with
this dinosaur origin of birds that they
were willing to to believe
a forgery without proper justification
that's right
now the same team the same chinese group
uh published a supposed dinosaur tale
with feathers on it in amber right a
couple years ago
and that again you know this one guy's
got his name on his paper again
and but something came up also that's a
problem and that
they didn't find it they bought it
so there's actually a lack of provenance
lack of provenance and that a lot of
these
uh feathered dinosaur fossils is you
know villagers in china are going out
because they realize they find a
world-class fossil they can make some
cash
and they're doing all the digging and
they'll bring it to the scientists say
hey look what i found
and they'd lost the content what layer
was it found in so was it found in the
right layer well we don't really know
because they've actually
yeah didn't see themselves and so this
um this dinosaur supposed tail feather
um there's a couple bones there and it's
in a piece of amber the thing is
you can melt amber you can stick stuff
in it now
it tends to turn to brown but i'm kind
of wondering if you put it under you
know
exactly right at that melting point
using some some high-tech piece of gear
maybe keep probably getting away from it
or something i'm not sure if it's
oxidization yeah you can throw
oxygen away from it and then put
something in and let it cool
well clearly they're feathers in this
piece of amber yeah
but it's not clear if that's a dinosaur
towel
or the end of a bird towel because you
wonder i mean how did the um amber
managed to catch the tail but what about
the rest of the dinosaur did it
lose its tail like a lizard did or what
happened i mean where's the rest of it
don't know don't know but there's there
are big questions and even amongst the
creationists they argue oh no there
really is this or really is that but
my i just take ten thousands of you and
i look at this and i said i got
questions about his providence
yep okay questions about um whether or
not it's a dinosaur
or a bird but there's definitely
feathers in the amber
right yeah okay now i think it's a bird
feather
because i mean even something like t-rex
we have skin fossils of t-rex we've got
skin fossils of a lot of dinosaurs
if you're going to have a feather
there's going to be hole there because
you got to perforate the skin to get a
feather come out that's true yeah and
t-rex multiple places on its body no
evidence of feathers in fact it's quite
distinctive some of the
they've got sort of bumps on their skin
but no
places for feathers to grow from that's
right
so i personally don't care
if dinosaurs have feathers or not that's
a fair thing to say actually yep
but scientifically i want to know and
scientifically
i am yet to be convinced and that's
exactly the phrase i like to use
is the evidence is not convincing
there is some evidence and we can't just
say there's zero
right but when i look at it i'm like eh
you got nothing better than that
clearly the bird fossils have feathers
and they're beautiful yep
but dinosaurs i i'm i'm yet to be
convinced
right i mean but it wouldn't overturn
our general biblical worldview
if something like that was found no
wouldn't change anything at all because
the bible doesn't say dinosaurs did not
have feathers
in fact the bible seems to have very
much more functional groupings
of animals like they have a term off
meaning bird bats yeah it's probably
pterodactyl
anything that's fly so there's groups
it's a fish i think you as a marine
biologist know about things like the
the necton that swim and the benthos
that dwell on the bottom
and the plankton you're actually the one
who pointed it out oh really yes i mean
i knew that but as soon as you said i'm
like oh that's true we use functional
classifications the things that stick to
the bottom are the benthos the thing
that swim or the nectar
we do and it doesn't matter what it is
talk about plankton well that could be a
a crab larvae it could be a
single-celled animal
it could be a little
you jellyfish radically different things
and we just call them plankton oh that's
pretty dismissive and the bible uses the
same sort of functional classification
as modern top marine biologists do it
sounds like yeah
so how will we classify dinosaurs
it's not super important but it's fun
yeah
and we want to you know back away from
from yelling and
screaming at each other sure yes but we
also want to acknowledge that
the data do not demand that dinosaurs
had feathers
i would have to agree with that yep well
that's our show for today
i hope you enjoyed that um it's a lot of
fun there's a lot more resources on this
topic on creation.com you can find
the article that jonathan and i wrote on
christian.com it'll be in the show notes
also
we have an entire dinosaur section
dinosaur q a
because we've been writing about
dinosaurs not just me i mean cmi in
general for a long time
because this is a subject that
christians struggle with they want to
know about
and we've provided answers for you so go
ahead and dig in
and you can learn on your own from here
on out but we hope we encourage you a
little bit
on a very difficult and very
controversial subject
you