Here's another one.
If you were really pro-life,
you'd pay for the upkeep of the child
until he or she reaches 18.
If you're not prepared to do that,
then you have no
right to oppose abortion.
- There are several reasons
why this argument doesn't work.
If you see a child
being abused by their parents,
do you call the authorities only
if you're prepared to
raise him or her to adulthood?
Just because we can't
adopt every unwanted child
doesn't mean we
shouldn't try to save their lives.
- But suppose pro-lifers
really don't care about babies
after they're born.
Does that mean it's
okay to let them be slaughtered?
- No, no.
- It's also rather
melodramatic and manipulative
to say that anyone
who doesn't actively support
a child's welfare after
birth must want that child dead.
If someone comes to
your door asking for donations
for cancer research and you decline,
does that mean you want
everyone with cancer to die?
Of course not.
- No.
And the idea that
pro-lifers are pro-birth only
is not even true.
- That's right.
- Pro-lifers are at the forefront
of care for mothers and babies.
In the US, pro-life
pregnancy counseling centers
outnumber Planned
Parenthood abortion meals
over three to one.
Yet those centers receive
little to no government funding
while Planned Parenthood
receives $500 million a year.
- A pro-abortion
group called Action Canada
for Sexual Health
and Rights has complained
that in Canada, there
are more crisis pregnancy centers
than abortion
providers, including hospitals.
- Sounds great.
This group has claimed
that crisis pregnancy centers
are giving out false information,
but they haven't offered any real proof.
One objection they have
is that some of these centers
offer ultrasounds,
which they say can trick people
into believing
they're a medical facility.
- The gas station has an ATM,
but no one mistakes it for a bang.
But an ultrasound
could help a woman realize
her baby is not just a clump of cells.
- That's right.
- That's a factor of decision.
Maybe that's the real objection.
- Yeah, one research paper indicated
that pregnant women who
visit crisis pregnancy centers
are 20% less likely to
choose abortion than those who don't.
- Good.
- The study authors
suggested that this must be
at least partly
because the centers lie to people.
For example, NARAL Pro-Choice America
conducted an undercover
investigation in which they said,
"More than 67% of
the locations intentionally
referred to the fetus as
baby and told our investigator
she was already a mother
because she was already pregnant."
That's certainly a pro-life perspective,
but it's also factually accurate.
- Most pregnancy centers are upfront
about what services
they do and do not provide.
The name alone, pregnancy centers,
should be a clue that
their focus is on pregnancy,
non-abortion.
- That's right.
- Oddly enough, many
offer counseling for those
who do choose an abortion,
even though they don't perform them.
- Meanwhile, it's been
suggested that other organizations
tend to give the impression that abortion
is the only option.
It's not.
- No, adoption is a
great alternative for any mother
who feels unprepared to raise a child,
but wants the child to live a happy life.
There are more couples wanting to adopt
than there are babies available.