Years ago, Judith Jarvis
Thompson put forward a hypothetical scenario.
Suppose you wake up
in a hospital to discover
that because you
have the same rare blood type,
your circulatory
system has been connected to that
of a famous violinist
with a serious kidney infection.
The hospital claims you are now
morally compelled to stay connected until the
violinist can function
independently, at least 9 months.
Thompson asks whether you
would feel morally obliged to go along.
Her point is that the right to a life
of one person does not override the right of
another person to choose
what happens to his or her body.
She argues that even if we grant
the humanity of the unborn baby, she has no
ethical or moral right to the use
of her mother's body to sustain her life.
It's actually not a very good argument.
Francis Beckwith pointed out some ethical
problems in his book
Politically Correct Death.
Number one,
Thompson's analogy assumes all
moral obligations
to offspring or voluntary.
But both parents
have involuntary obligations
because they had sex
knowing it could result in pregnancy.
Number two, Thompson equates
volunteerism with family morality, which involves
personal obligations to our
offspring, which we don't have to others.
Number three, the preborn child has a
right to the mother's body because he or she
is dependent on its
mother at this stage of development.
And there's no reason to deny that right
if the child is a
human, as Thompson allows.
Number four,
abortion is not simply withholding
treatment, but is
actually the killing of the baby.
In the analogy, there's no guarantee the
violinist will die, but
abortion is intended to kill.
Thompson's point is
that a woman should have autonomy
over her body and
everything in it, even another human being.
By that logic, a woman
could continue drinking alcohol,
knowing that the baby
could develop fetal alcohol syndrome.
Who knows why someone
would do that, but then why would
someone deliberately have
a baby chopped up and vacuumed?
Terrible things can happen
when fallen human beings are in charge.