Secular pro-life is
run by three atheist women who
wish to advance
secular arguments against abortion.
They outline their argument as follows.
Number one, the human zygote,
embryo, and fetus are all human organisms.
They are early
developmental stages of a human's life cycle.
Two, all human
organisms are morally relevant.
Three, it's
generally immoral to kill humans.
And four, bodily rights aren't
enough to justify elective abortion.
The right to
choose is often considered to
be in line with
feminism as it empowers women.
Or does it?
Susan B. Anthony's
newsletter, The Revolution,
described abortion as
child murder, infanticide,
and feticide.
Anthony's friend
Elizabeth Cady Stanton argued,
"When you consider
that women have been treated
as property, it is
degrading to women that
we should treat our
children as property to be
disposed of as we see fit."
In our time, the
Organization Feminist for Life asserts,
"Abortion is a reflection that
we have not met the needs of women."