It's mind-boggling
to think that ending a human
life could be
considered a matter of personal choice,
like choosing a career or dieting.
Let's put some of
the pro-abortion arguments in
perspective by
applying the two-year-old test.
Whenever there's a reference
to a fetus, substitute two-year-old.
For example, it's the right
of every two-year-old to be wanted.
We're not pro-killing
two-year-olds, we're pro-choice.
Unless you're prepared
to adopt this two-year-old, you
have no right to tell the
mother she should not kill her.
If we don't make it possible for
the mother to kill her two-year-old safely,
then she'll do it unsafely and
possibly put her own health in danger.
That sounds shocking,
but you can see the logic.
Why should killing a
pre-born baby be any less
monstrous than killing a
toddler, a teenager, or an adult?
They're all human beings at
different stages of development.