The neo-Darwinian
theory of evolution says
that all life on
earth arose from a common
ancestor by way of random mutations to
genes preserved by
natural selection. Organisms
with beneficial
mutations produced more offspring
than those with
deleterious or damaging mutations.
Some beneficial mutations provided
adaptations to new or
changed environments, producing
new kinds of
organisms. In order to get extra
new information to
build more complex organisms,
existing genes must have been
duplicated and then mutated into something useful.
Right, but
population geneticist J.B.S. Haldane
realized that when a
beneficial mutation occurs
in a population,
the number of copies of that
mutation must increase
over time for the population
to progress evolutionarily. It has to
substitute for the
non-mutated genes in the population.
But the rate at which this can happen is
limited. Haldane
realized that there hasn't been enough
time to accumulate
enough beneficial mutations
to transform an
ape-like creature into a human.
This became known as
Haldane's dilemma, and he
explained it like
this. Imagine a population of
100,000 ape-like
creatures 10 million years ago,
more than the
supposed time since the last common
ancestor of humans
and apes. Suppose a male and
a female both
received a mutation so beneficial
that they survived
while the 99,998 all died
out. Then they had
enough offspring to replenish the
population of
100,000 in one generation. If
this repeated every 20
years for 10 million years,
there would be
500,000 beneficial mutations added
to the population. This
amounts to only 0.02% of the
human genome. Even the old myth of 1-2%
difference between
human and chimp DNA wouldn't work.
But we know the
difference is actually at least
5%, or as much as 15%.
We did an entire episode on
this subject titled "Chimp to Human
DNA, Less Similar Than Previously Reported."
Obviously Haldane
put forward an incredibly
unlikely scenario
here. He calculated a more
realistic scenario
would be one beneficial
mutation about every
300 generations on average
for a total of 1,667 beneficial
mutations over 10 million years. That's nothing.
Definitely not enough. Even if the 1%
difference were true,
we'd need 30 million beneficial
mutations, which
would take about 9 billion
generations, or 180
billion years. That's about
13 times the supposed age of the
universe according to the Big Bang Theory.