Today we're summarizing a great piece
of evidence for the Creator God of the Bible.
Yes, it's the amazing
complexity of the human genome.
Today on Creation Magazine LIVE!
[Music]
Welcome to Creation
Magazine LIVE! I'm Richard Fangrad.
And I'm Thomas Bailey.
All right, today
we'll be looking at discoveries
in genetics that
powerfully support that DNA was
created and that it could never be
the result of millions of years of evolution.
We're also going to explore
problems with evolutionary assumptions about DNA.
The failed
predictions and scientific dead ends
that often result
when you approach observations
with the wrong assumptions.
Yeah, and along the
way we'll reveal some of
the mind-bogglingly
complex biological machinery
associated with DNA.
This will be fun. DNA, by
the way, is an
instruction code for how to build
and operate a living thing.
All living things
have DNA. Bill Gates, the
co-founder of
Microsoft, made this statement back
in 1995. He wrote, "Human DNA is like a
computer program but
far, far more advanced than any
software ever
created." He wasn't kidding. An
organism's genetic
material is called a genome.
Since Gates made that statement, we have
learned that the human
genome is way more complex than
he or anyone else knew at that time.
Yeah, meanwhile,
evolutionists continue to
maintain that all
living creatures, including
their DNA, obviously, evolved by random
processes, natural
processes only, over millions of years.
No intelligent designer. That's their
assumption. Our assumption
as Bible believers includes what
King David wrote,
for example, 3,000 years ago,
"For you formed my
inward parts, you knitted me
together in my mother's womb. I praise
you, for I am
fearfully and wonderfully made."
Let's crank the
clock back to 1859, long before
Bill Gates, when
Charles Darwin wrote his book
on the origin of
species. The thinking back
then was that the cell
was a fairly simple blob of
matter. It's easier to imagine organisms
evolving slowly and
gradually if they're fairly simple.
We now know that
there are problems with that
view. Darwin didn't
know anything about genetics,
which really took off shortly after he
published. He did, however, famously admit,
"If it could be
demonstrated that any complex
organ existed,
which could not possibly have
been formed by numerous successive
slight modifications, my theory would absolutely
break down." Now,
while Darwin was referring to
organs, we can apply
this logic at the molecular
level since, as we
mentioned, evolutionists now
assert that even DNA
formed as a result of random
natural processes.
For example, biochemist
Michael Behe coined the
term irreducible complexity.
That refers to a
system of interacting parts
in which every part
has to be in place before it
can function. This
means that a system couldn't
come into being
gradually bit by bit, and there
are many examples of this kind of
evolution-refuting design in molecular biology.
Here's an example. Life depends on an
incredible enzyme called
ATP synthase. That's the name of
the world's tiniest
rotary motor, rotating at
up to 7,000 rpm.
These are so small that 100,000
would fit side by side in a
millimeter. Yeah, ATP synthase
makes ATP, or adenosine
triphosphate, the
fuel that powers cellular
machines. Each of
the human body's about 14
trillion cells, perform this
reaction about a million times a minute.
Over half of your body's weight
of ATP is made and consumed every day.
A current of
protons drives the motor, unlike
man-made electric
motors which use electrons.
The portion shown here in green is
where adenosine diphosphate is combined with a
phosphate ion in the
presence of a catalyst to
produce ATP, which
is then released making way
for the next cycle.
This nanomachine exhibits all
the characteristics
of super intelligent design.
ATP is vital for life, and many of these
motors were needed
before the first living cell
could exist. That's an
evolutionary impossibility. That's right, yeah.
Getting back to
DNA, in 1962, James Watson,
Francis Crick, and
Maurice Wilkins won the Nobel
Prize in Physiology and Medicine for the
discovery of the
structure of DNA. That was in 1953. DNA,
by the way, stands for
deoxiribonucleic acid. Say that 10 times fast.
Once for that matter. DNA is the most
compact information
storage system in the universe.
The amount of
information that could be stored
in just a pinhead's
volume of DNA is equivalent to
a pile of paperback
books 500 times as high as
the distance from
Earth to the Moon, each with a
different, yet
specific content. A single gram of
DNA could store about
215 petabytes, or if you're
in the UK,
petabytes. That's 1.21 gigawatts, or
no, it's 215 million
gigabytes. Either way, that's a
lot. That's a lot.
All of that information is
stored in a double
helix molecule made up of four
chemical letters,
adenine, cytosine, guanine,
and thymine, or A, C,
G, and T. It's already a huge
problem for
evolutionists to explain how these
chemical letters
could arise spontaneously from
a so-called primordial soup of non-living
chemicals, but it gets
better. It's better for us, worse for
the evolutionists.
In the protein coding areas
of the genome, these
four letters are arranged in
three-letter
combinations called codons, sort of
like words in a human
language. Now, consider that
if you change one
letter in a word, you either
get gibberish, you get
nothing, or you could get a
different meaning,
like changing, for example,
C-A-T to C-A-R in English.
That's a different meaning.
But the letters
themselves don't mean anything
unless they're
translated. For example, in English,
the letters
G-I-F-T mean a present. That's
something nice. But
that same sequence of letters
in German, which is
my first language, means
poison. Ouch. That's
something you want to find
under the Christmas tree. No. Now, each
three-letter codon codes
for one protein letter called an
amino acid, and there are a total of 64
possible codons, but
there are only 21 different amino
acids coding for
proteins. Well, this means that
more than one codon
can be used for any particular
amino acid. Yeah, but
why so much duplication? As
cells divide and DNA
gets copied, copying errors
or mutations occur.
Sometimes letters get put
in the wrong place,
but this apparent duplication
means that in many
cases, one letter can get
changed and still
result in the production of
the correct amino
acid. And that is brilliant
engineering by the
creator God of the Bible.
Not only that, even if an error
results in the wrong amino acid being selected,
it will often have
characteristics similar to
the correct one. Yeah,
amazing. This is just one of
the design features in DNA, and
we'll talk about more of them after the break.
Many people think
that the biblical flood of
Noah was abandoned
because of the evidence.
However, history tells a different story.
Modern geological
thought owes much to a man named
Charles Lyell. Lyell,
a lawyer, published a book
in 1830 called
Principles of Geology. Described as
a masterpiece of
persuasion, it changed the way
people thought about
Earth's past. According to
Lyell, we should only
appeal to today's geological
processes to explain
Earth history. However, this
approach meant that the global flood
recorded in the Bible
was automatically ruled out of
consideration. Lyell
wanted, he wrote, to free
the science of
geology from Moses. Regrettably,
many people have
uncritically adopted Lyell's
philosophy without
considering how Noah's flood
can help us
understand Earth history. Lyell
changed the way many
people think, but his approach was
motivated by his
anti-biblical philosophy.
Indeed, it is very
difficult to explain Earth's history
without Noah's
flood. To find out more from
Creation Ministries
International, visit our website,
creation.com.
Welcome back. This is fun,
isn't it? Yeah.
Let's talk about more design
features surrounding
DNA. Now, these are things
that are very
difficult for evolution to explain.
You may have heard
about the infamous Miller-Urey
experiment back in
1953, in which electricity was
added to certain gases under
specialized conditions. This
was intended to show how
life could
spontaneously arise without God.
Right. But the
experiment actually showed that it took
a great deal of
intelligence to set up conditions
that produced mostly
a lot of tar and just a few
amino acids. Yeah.
This is a long way from the
living self. Yeah.
Here are some of the problems
with that experiment. First, there were
starting assumptions
about what gases would have been
present on the
primordial Earth, and these
didn't include oxygen,
which tends to destroy chemical
bonds, preventing
anything from forming. Now,
since then, evidence
indicates that oxygen likely was
present at the time. So because it didn't
accurately
simulate the Earth's atmosphere,
it's pretty much
irrelevant as an experiment,
and those amino
acids could not have formed.
Not only that, many
molecules required for life
exist in two forms
that look like mirror images
of each other, like
your left and right hands.
This is called
chirality, from the Greek word for
hand. The
Miller-Urey experiment produced equal
amounts of left and
right-handed forms of amino
acids. Yeah. But all
amino acids and proteins are
left-handed, while
all sugars in DNA and RNA and
in metabolic
pathways are right-handed. Random
chemical reactions
won't produce 100% left-handed
amino acids that
are needed for life. This is
just one example of
thousands where evolutionists
have major problems explaining how life
originated. Yeah. But
evolution continues to be promoted as
established
scientific fact. It's not. No.
Let's move on to
another evolutionary problem.
Discoveries in genetics
refutes the idea of ape to human evolution.
The neo-Darwinian
theory of evolution says that
all life on Earth
arose from a common ancestor by
way of random
mutations to genes preserved by
natural selection.
Organisms with beneficial
mutations produced
more offspring than those
with deleterious or
damaging mutations. Some
beneficial mutations
provided adaptations to new
or changed
environments, producing new kinds of
organisms. In order
to get extra new information
to build more
complex organisms, existing genes
must have been
duplicated and then mutated into
something useful.
Right. But population geneticist
J.B.S. Haldane
realized that when a beneficial
mutation occurs in a
population, the number of
copies of that
mutation must increase over time
for the population
to progress evolutionarily.
It has to substitute
for the non-mutated genes
in the population.
But the rate at which this can
happen is limited. Haldane realized that
there hasn't been
enough time to accumulate enough
beneficial mutations to transform an
ape-like creature into
a human. This became known as
Haldane's dilemma,
and he explained it like this.
Imagine a population
of 100,000 ape-like creatures
10 million years ago,
more than the supposed time
since the last common
ancestor of humans and apes.
Suppose a male and a female both received
a mutation so
beneficial that they survived
while the 99,998
all died out. Then they had
enough offspring to
replenish the population of
100,000 in one
generation. If this repeated every
20 years for 10 million
years, there would be 500,000
beneficial
mutations added to the population.
This amounts to only
0.02% of the human genome.
Now even the old myth of 1-2%
difference between human
and chimp DNA wouldn't work.
But we know the
difference is actually at least
5%, or as much as
15%. We did an entire episode
on this subject titled "Chimp to Human
DNA, Less Similar Than Previously Reported."
Yeah, now
obviously Haldane put forward an
incredibly unlikely
scenario here. He calculated
a more realistic scenario would be one
beneficial mutation about
every 300 generations on average
for a total of 1,667 beneficial
mutations over 10 million years. That's nothing.
Definitely not enough. No. Even if the 1%
difference were true,
we'd need 30 million beneficial
mutations, which
would take about 9 billion
generations, or 180
billion years. That's about
13 times the supposed age of the universe
according to the Big Bang
Theory. Evolutionists would need
to stretch out the
age of the universe in order
to allow for human
evolution, never mind everything
else. Yeah, don't
give them any ideas. Right.
Of course, God
didn't need anywhere near that
much amount of
time. No. Back to Haldane's
dilemma. Since only 2% of human DNA codes
for proteins, it
was assumed that the other
98% was
non-functional and was eventually labeled
"junk DNA." This
appeared to solve the problem
since there could be
all kinds of neutral mutations
in the junk DNA
with no significant damage
to the organism. Junk DNA was not just an
arbitrary label. It was
mathematically necessary for evolution to occur.
Yeah, and this led to an unfortunate lack
of research into
the majority of the genome.
Junk DNA was assumed to be a result of
evolution by mutation
and was then used as proof of
evolution. There's
a bit of circular reasoning there.
Like vestigial
organs. Yes. About a hundred years
ago, there were
around a hundred body parts
labeled vestigial. No one
knew what these parts were for,
so they were
assumed by evolutionists to be
leftovers or
vestiges from a previous stage in
human evolution. They
were then used as evidence
for evolution. This
hindered research into these
organs for many
years. But guess what? Almost all
of those vestigial
organs have since been found to
have a purpose, as
if they were designed. Nice.
Fearfully and
wonderfully made. I love it when
science catches up
with the Bible. Yeah. It's
the same with junk
DNA. Evolutionist assumptions
hindered research.
It took a while, but in
2003, finally, the
ENCODE project, which stands for
Encyclopedia of DNA
Elements, began studying just
1% of the human
genome, including areas that did
and did not code
for protein. They found that
80% of so-called junk
DNA has a function. Who knew?
Lead analysis
coordinator Ewan Birney said,
"It's likely that
this 80% will go to 100%,
said Birney. We
don't really have large chunks
of redundant DNA. This
metaphor of junk isn't that
useful," he said.
So, Haldane's Dilemma still
hasn't been solved,
not even close. When we come
back, we'll talk
about how the human genome codes
in four dimensions.
Did you know that animals have
genetic switches?
These are regulatory regions of
DNA that control the
genes. Scientists have noticed
that dramatic things
can happen when a genetic
switch is mutated. For
instance, a mutated genetic
switch can
dramatically alter the appearance of
stickleback fish or
generate a great variety of
coat colors in
animals. Veterinary researcher
Dr. Jean Lightner has
suggested that God may have
created genetic
switches to facilitate variation,
the switches having
been created with a propensity
to mutate without
negatively affecting other
traits.
Modifications to genetic switches are
not examples of
evolution in action, even though
they are often spoken
of in that manner. Indeed,
these changes don't
involve new information, new
genes arising, and
evolutionists cannot explain
the existence of
the genetic switches in the
first place. The more we
learn about the complexity of
genomes, the more they point to a super
intelligent master
programmer. To find out more from Creation
Ministries
International visit our website
creation.com.
I don't get how a geneticist or
anyone who knows even
a little bit about DNA can
look at it and
conclude random. Yeah, right. Yeah,
no design, nothing
to see here. To get the
information that
we're sharing today out to more
people, hit that
like button and subscribe. It
helps. Yeah, and
sharing the video on Twitter
and Facebook and
elsewhere also helps more
people see the silliness
of evolution and the power of
our Creator God.
Stick around, there's even more
amazing complexity at
the smallest levels of life
that we want to
share, starting right now.
Welcome back. We're
going to continue discussing
serious scientific problems with the
evolutionary origin of
life. Since DNA was discovered,
researchers have
been finding out more and more
astounding things
about it. And the more we learn,
the less plausible
evolution becomes. For example,
human DNA codes in not
just one, not two, not three,
but four dimensions. Yeah, comparing the
genetic code to a
computer code, which we did,
isn't really fair
because it's way more complex
than any computer
code. And we'll show you how.
A few years ago, researchers compared the
relatively simple E.
coli genome with the Linux
operating system.
The E. coli genome uses a
few high-level
instructions that control a few
mid-level processes that in turn
control a massive number of protein coding genes.
Linux is much more
top-heavy and thus much less
efficient. E. coli
can do a lot more with fewer
controls. Now,
that's some great programming
right there. Yeah, if
we replace the four chemical
letters with four
colored pixels, it would look
like this. That's
just the first 700 letters of
the human Y
chromosome. Lots of information stored
in this long line of
letters, but that's just one
dimension. Yeah,
the second dimension deals
with how one section
of DNA interacts with another
section. It would be
impossible to draw arrows
showing all the
connections between different
sections. This
diagram shows a small portion of
the microRNA
regulatory network as it acts on just
13 genes associated
with arthuris sclerosis or the
hardening of the
arteries. Remember, this is just
a tiny piece of a
much bigger picture. One of the
greatest mysteries
about the human genome is that
only about 22,000
genes can produce more than
300,000 distinct
proteins. This means we don't
have many more
genes than simpler organisms,
indicating efficiency
in design. This is possible
because genes get
spliced and diced. It used to
be thought that a
single gene coded for a single
protein, but it's not
that simple. Protein genes
are broken up into
exons which code for proteins
and intervening
non-coding sequences called
introns. When the
DNA gets copied, the gene is
transcribed into RNA
or ribonucleic acid, then
the introns get
spliced out, the exons get stitched
together, and the
remainder is translated into a
protein. Introns
have specific sequences at the
head and tail ends to
tell the splicing mechanism
where to cut. Exons
also have spliced signals at
their ends. So the
protein coding section's code
for both protein
sequence and splicing patterns
at the same time. The ENCODE project also
documented an amazing
amount of alternate splicing,
and it appears
there is some sort of splicing
code. But wait, a
code means information which
would involve
intelligence, wouldn't it? Yeah,
yeah. Information
comes only from intelligence.
Okay, now on the
third dimension, amino acids
come together in
linear strings to form proteins.
That sounds simple
enough. Remember, the simpler
it is, the easier it
is to imagine it could come
from evolution. It
could be evolved. But genes
that are used
together do not necessarily appear
near one another in the genome. There are
sections of DNA that are
buried deep within the coiled up
DNA strand, meaning they cannot be easily
activated. So 3D
folding of chromosomes is
incredibly important
for overall gene function.
That's right. Every
chemical letter needs to be
in just the right
place and line so it will make
all the right
connections after the DNA is folded.
Thus, when God
wrote out the information in
the genome along
that one-dimensional strand,
He intentionally put
things in a certain order
so they would be in
the correct place when the DNA
was folded into a
3D shape. It's pretty hard
to claim that DNA
came from millions of years of
random mutations
to happen to occur in just
the right spots in a
tightly folded genome. Yeah,
yeah. Imagine
folding a sentence so that the
letters line up with
other letters in different
parts of the
sentence to make additional words,
giving you more than
one sentence simultaneously.
This is a huge problem for the concept
of evolution by random mutation. Of course,
this is not an issue
if the genome was designed.
We mentioned machinery
a moment ago. Tiny machines
translate the
information in DNA, but how do
we get those
machines? Philosopher of Science,
Sir Karl Popper,
noted, "What makes the origin of
life and of the
genetic code a disturbing riddle
is this. The genetic
code is without any biological
function unless it is
translated. The machinery by
which the cell
translates the code consists of
at least 50
macromolecular components which are
themselves coded in
the DNA. Thus the code cannot
be translated except
by using certain products of
its translation.
This constitutes a baffling
circle, a really vicious
circle, it seems, for any attempt
to form a model or
theory of the genesis of the
genetic code." In other
words, you need the machines
to translate the
DNA in order to build the
machines that
translate the DNA, so you can get
the machines to
translate. It's a chicken and
egg problem, right?
And there are lots of those in
molecular biology.
But wait, there's more. The
fourth dimension deals
with the way the first three
dimensions change
over time. That's right. The
first three
dimensions, the sequence of letters,
the interaction network, and the shape of
the chromosomes all
change. Now on the surface,
that sounds like
evolution, but it's actually
pre-programming.
Certain genes get switched on
and off at the right
times in the right sequence.
In other words, the
genome regulates itself over
time. Evolve that.
Now we've only just briefly
summarized the
four-dimensional genome. For more
on that, watch Dr.
Robert Carter's talk, "The
High-Tech Cell," that's
available on DVD or streaming
at creation.com.
More after this. One of the
remarkable things
about the geologic record is
that blankets of
sediments cover vast areas of
the continents. In
his book, "The Nature of the
Stratographical
Record," evolutionary geologist
Professor Derek Agar
marveled at the way sedimentary
layers extended for
thousands of kilometers, even
across continents. He
was particularly impressed
with the chalk beds
that form the famous white
cliffs of Dover in
southern England, as these trace
all the way to
Turkey and Egypt. The strata
exposed in the walls
of the Grand Canyon provide
another example.
Some of these sedimentary
formations extend
thousands of kilometers across
North America.
Such vast sedimentary layers
suggest that
geological processes must have
occurred in the past
that we don't observe today.
Sedimentary deposits
forming today are localized
and confined to
river deltas, lake beds, and
along narrow strips of
coastline. Sedimentary blankets
covering vast areas
are exactly what we would
expect if the global
flood recorded in the Bible
actually occurred. To find out more from
Creation Ministries
International, visit our website
creation.com. All
right, we've been talking
about how the
complexity of the human DNA supports
creation. Now, a 10-year study
called the Genotype Expression Project, or GTEx,
was recently
completed. The goal was to see how
variations in the
genome affect RNA production,
phenotype, and
disease. They were able to separate
effects by sex, race,
tissue type, and cell type.
The hope was that
sequencing the human genome
would lead to a
cure for disease. This failed
massively. It was
also thought that we would
understand how the
genome worked if we could
only obtain the DNA
sequence of our chromosomes.
But as we've seen,
there's a lot more to it than
that. Yeah. GTEx researchers obtained
samples from 52 tissue
types from 838 organ donors,
making sure they had
complete genomes for each
donor. They also
compared their results to those
from living samples
and cell culture. Here are
some of their
findings. Okay, variations in RNA
expression and
splicing are more common in coding
areas, but only
one-third are affected by nearby
variants. Long
distance control of genes is
quite common, and a
lot of variation exists in this
system. Also, the
average gene has more than one
expressed form. This
makes sense in a creationist
model, as God programmed a huge amount of
diversity into the genome
from the beginning. Some tissues
express genes
differently than others, and there
are both race-specific
and sex-specific differences.
Out of 13,294 genes associated with
sex, sex differences across all tissues,
only 369 of these had truly significant
differences between
the sexes. For example, SLC44A5
is a sugar and amino
acid transport gene that is
expressed in all
tissue types. It's also one of
the main drivers of
different skin shades among
the so-called races.
Okay, yeah, over a third of
all genes show
sex-biased expression in at
least one tissue, but
individual variation produces
overlapping effects.
The difference between male
and female is the
result of the sum total of the
effects of many
different genes, many of which
do not apply to
obvious tissue differences between
males and females.
So it's a lot more complex
than just X and Y
chromosomes. God really did make
male and female.
That's right. Different cell
types exist in any
given tissue. They discovered
3,347 coding and non-coding genes with
different expression
profiles among the cell types
with single tissues,
and 987 genes with different
splicing patterns.
Okay, telomeres are repetitive
DNA at the tips of
most chromosomes and are
associated with
longevity. Longer telomeres
correlate to longer
lifespans, which could help
explain much of the
longer lifespans before Noah.
Think of it as a
counting device with a number of
beads on the end of
the chromosome, for example.
Every time the cell
divides, it's as if a bead is
snipped off,
shortening the telomere. Once all the
beads are gone,
cell division no longer takes
place. It turns out
that relative telomere length
varies across tissues between the sexes.
Rare variants occur
throughout the human genome.
Anytime you add new
people to a genetic database,
you will be adding
new rare variants. This is due
to the high rate of
new mutations per generation.
The rapid increase in
human population size of the
past few thousand
years means that many of
these rare mutations
have not been lost. This makes
sense in a creation
model, as the population
has grown
exponentially from only eight people
approximately 4,400
years ago. Yeah, now this
is just a summary of
some of the findings of the
GTEx study. Again,
we see how evolutionary
assumptions led to
false conclusions, or in
this case false
predictions, several years and
billions of dollars
later, researchers are still
just getting a
glimpse into the amazingly complex
functional machine
that God created out of dust.
Which he made from nothing.
From nothing, yes. One of the benefits of
learning some of
these amazing discoveries
that we've summarized
today is it fills you with
an awe for God.
Psalm 104.24 says, "O Lord, how
manifold are Your
works in wisdom You have made
them all, for the
earth is full of Your creatures."
Incredible. Wow, we covered
quite a bit today. Yes, we certainly did.
Anyways, we'll see you next week and
remember, Christianity
is an evidence-based faith.
And science supports Scripture.
Wait, wait, wait. Don't go just yet.
If you learn something, then others will too.
Share this video
as widely as you can, and
if you haven't yet, hit that like button.
Or leave a comment
about what you found most
interesting, or
respond to some of the other
comments. Those
activities help push the video
to other people's
feeds. Thanks for watching.