[Music]
There's also something fishy about
the infamous 'hockey stick' graph.
Yes there is.
The graph shows that after a thousand year
period of relative relatively stable temperatures
there was a dramatic spike within the last
century, particularly in the last few decades.
Now this is usually attributed to
the use of fossil fuels. However,
this graph has been shown to be fraudulent.
Yes. It doesn't record either the Medieval
Warming period or the Little Ice Age from the
mid-1300s to about 1885. When we add those
back the graph should look more like this,
showing fluctuations in global temperatures
before any increase in man-made CO2 emissions.
Well you know it said that a picture is
worth a thousand words. Well the image of
that fraudulent graph was a fear-mongering
tactic that influenced millions of people
And the fear It produced motivated
people to vote in climate activists.
There's also a lesson from history here and
that's that the world was better off when global
temperatures were warmer. And commenting on a TV
documentary about global warming, anti-creationist
Ian Plummer said, "Groups like BAMOS and the
IPCC deny, minimize or ignore significant
recent climate changes that gave us the Roman
warming, the Dark Ages, the Medieval Warming and
the little Ice Age. Both history and archeology
show that in previous warmings, temperatures
were far higher than at present. Populations and
economy thrived. Previous coolings led to famine,
depopulation and social disruption. History
shows that his dangerous to ignore history."
So a little warmer is actually
a little better better. Okay,
so, it's clear that there are other goals
mixed in with the climate change debate,
right? It's not just about saving the planet and
and following the science. There's outright fraud.