But let's see what the Bible says.
Yes, let's.
In Exodus 21:22-24 we read,
"When men strive
together and hit a pregnant woman
so that her children
come out, but there is no harm,
the one who hit
her shall surely be fined,
as the woman's
husband shall impose on him,
and he shall pay as the judges determine.
But if there is harm,
then you shall pay life for life,
eye for eye, tooth
for tooth, hand for hand,
foot for foot, burn for burn,
wound for wound, striped for stripe.
So there was an additional penalty
if an unborn child was harmed.
Note the term
children, not clumps of cells.
- Yeah, the late first
century Christian work Didachē
says, "The second
commandment of the teaching,
you shall not murder,
you shall not commit adultery,
you shall not seduce boys,
you shall not commit fornication,
you shall not steal,
you shall not practice magic,
you shall not use potions,
you shall not procure an abortion,
nor destroy a newborn child."
- God considers the
preborn child to be human
and worthy of his attention.
In Genesis 25:23, God tells Rebecca,
"Two nations are in your womb,
and two peoples from
within you shall be divided.
The one shall be stronger than the other,
the older shall serve the younger."
- Later, God says to Jeremiah,
"Before I formed
you in the womb, I knew you,
and before you were
born, I consecrated you.
I appointed you a
prophet to the nations."