on today's show a super controversial
subject
the age of the earth according to the
bible
[Music]
i'm dr robert carter i'm in the studio
today with my dear friend lita kosner
hey lita
hi rob and we're going to be discussing
something that you and i
have struggled with wrestled with
studied
for untold number of hours that is
the biblical age of the earth so let me
ask you a question
first off why is this even important
it's not really important at all
that was a joke
well this is important because the bible
claims to be a book about history and
so when you look at other ancient
documents
you see them talking about the gods
doing things
outside of time and space the bible
is very different from that in that it
puts god's actions on a map and on a
timeline
and so while the bible doesn't primarily
exist to give us
a chronology of the earth
part of what it does as a historical
document is it gives us chronological
statements
and it's important that we take those
statements seriously like anything
else the bible says okay so if the bible
makes a statement about you know this
number of years this number of years
and that's wrong that's a really
important for our understandings of
biblical
inspiration and inerrancy and things
like that okay
so if someone wanted to to figure out
how all the earth is recorded in the
bible
where are they going to go where what
parts of the bible discuss this
well there are several places in the
bible that give us chronological
statements but the first place
is in what we call the chronogeneologies
okay big word
chronogeneal
yeah so basically we know what a
genealogy is that's where you
is this guy had the father this guy
father this guy
a chrono genealogy says adam was 130
years old
then he had seth then he lived 700 years
seth
lived 103 years he fathered enosh and so
on and so forth okay so chrono means
time
and then genealogy is a list of names
yes so it's a list of names that gives
us a
time frame yes okay cool i like that
oh by the way excellent article on
creation.com called chronogenealogies
it'll be in the show notes
okay so my next question then is we have
these
chrono genealogies big word we just
learned it a lot of fun
um how many of them are there in the
bible
well there are two of them genesis 5
takes us all the way from adam to noah
okay and then genesis
11 takes us from noah's son shem
through terror and then
and then abram okay we have these these
long lists of names and all these dates
how do we link them together because you
went to noah and then you went to shem
we have to read the bible for clues of
how old shem was
when the flood came or how noah was when
shem was born and things like that and
then we can link them together
exactly there are some places where we
have to
use a little bit of interpretation we
have to make a few assumptions
but the bible does give us enough
information
to allow us to create a timeline with
very little uncertainty really from 587
or 86 bc
that's when judah went into exile in
babylon oh i know why all of a sudden
you jumped to 586 bc
we were just in adam and noah because
that is the place where we really have
a hard point of history where we can
link a biblical event
to a secular date okay so the bible
talks about the babylonian destruction
of jerusalem
yes very clearly and history tells us
about it also and
modern historians have pegged that to
586 or 587 bc
right so this is where we hang our
chronogeneology
into history yes and the bible gives us
chronological statements
about the reigns of the kings of
israel and judah how long they reigned
and that's notoriously complicated
yes and fun to study but that's another
place where you have to make some
assumptions where there's
some interpretational decisions to be
made but i think the differences might
amount to maybe 50 years
yes i think i think some scholars have
gone through and figured it out really
carefully down to probably a year or two
yeah but if you just start off and you
try to do it yourself you're going to
come up to some differences
and have to figure out how to fix them
yes one thing with this whole topic that
we're going to be discussing is that
people have been studying this and
trying to figure these things out for a
long time and they've come up with some
brilliant conclusions
this is not something that you can just
dive in yourself
with just your bible ignoring everything
everybody else has said and come to
solid conclusions we need to listen to
what other godly christians have said
throughout history
you and i have seen that a lot on
youtube on facebook
social media things people thinking they
found the holy grail
of biblical timing yeah and really
they just stumbled into something
without really understanding the depth
of discussion has already been done for
the past several thousand years
yes it's really rare to come up with an
absolutely new
question to ask about scripture or a new
solution to something you think is a
problem
and so when we have a historical view as
far as looking at
okay what conversations have people
already had about this
okay so one of the conversations
is how accurate can we get it
and we're asking you know how old is the
earth well
how old is the earth and how close can
we know it to be
well that depends on a lot of factors um
overall if you present the absolute
worst case scenario
um with all of the uncertainty you can
possibly put in there
it's under 200 years the worst case
scenario okay that's interesting that
but what
uncertainties are we talking about what
do you mean uncertainty well exactly
adam is 130 years when seth is born it's
130 right
well maybe once you get to 131 years
what does an extra 12 months
matter why does it matter if adam was
almost 131 what does it matter
if um if seth was
almost 103 and since most of those
numbers end in a five or a zero
yeah there might be some cultural
counting issues we're dealing with yes
but there's more than that though
the the biggest question is assuming
those numbers are
exactly right hundred thirty hundred for
thirty five hundred forty whatever the
number is
um when was seth born not on adam's
birthday
right sometime during his 130th year
which means 130 plus on average six
months
yeah and so we have this
range of uncertainty that builds up
every time
there is a new date added to the
timeline because we don't know how many
months
we don't know if there's rounding
involved
scripture is as precise as it means to
be
and so that means different things at
different times we know that scripture
is capable of being
very precise like when it's talking
about the flood we know down to the
number of days how long the flood was
um but often scripture doesn't need to
be that precise
it's not the purpose of scripture
wouldn't some people hear what you're
saying and say oh therefore the bible's
got errors in it
well it's not an error like if i say
i'm this number of years old
it can be accurate without being
accurate to the precise amount of
seconds old i
yeah yeah exactly it's not like i'm not
51. you know
five six seven three two two because who
cares
there's 51. yeah and so scripture is as
ac
is as precise as it means to be for its
purposes
and we have to examine the context to
see how precise that is
okay so big question what is the purpose
of the bible
is it to give us a chronology of earth's
history
no it's the purpose of the bible is to
tell us how
god created how he has worked in
relation to his creation and ultimately
it's to tell us about christ
okay so the purpose of the bible is to
teach us about jesus christ
yes now the back story in genesis and
exodus and
and all those books is really good to
know yes
but the purpose of the books is not to
teach us
exactly how old the earth is down to the
day right
it does have chronological details that
we can use
to build a picture of history yes
but it's not if we're saying we can't
know it down to the day or even to the
year we're not saying the bible has
errors
it's just not the purpose of the text to
teach us down to the year
right just as it wasn't the purpose of
the creation account to tell us how god
created electrons
ah good point you're right all right
okay so
we have this bible it's full of numbers
the numbers are
you can add them up yes if you add them
all up or
no before we even get there we have this
bible
we can add up all the numbers how do we
get from
adam in the beginning to today or let's
say to the time of christ
or 586 bc how do we get there
the chronogenealogies only get us to
abraham right
so certain statements in exodus allow us
to tell how long it was from when jacob
went down to egypt
to when moses led them out of egypt
okay and then when solomon built the
temple it said
that that was 408
years yeah 480 years to the day yeah to
the day and so that obviously
intends to be a very precise measurement
okay
well 480 years from what from the exodus
okay so we have adam to noah noah to
abraham abraham to
moses moses to solomon
yes and then we have all the king lists
yes in in chronicles and kings of how
long each of these guys reigned 586 bc
yes wow
so we actually know how old the earth is
yes that's crazy okay according to the
bible
how old is it well that depends
on that range of uncertainty
okay so it's a little over 6 000 years
old
okay i'd say 60 200-ish
yes okay plus or minus a few decades yes
okay maybe a few centuries even okay i'm
happy with that
um but there's a famous date 4004 bc
4004 bc what is that number where's that
come from
well there was a brilliant scholar
called archbishop
james usher yes he was a brilliant man
who wrote this
really huge book called the annals of
the world and i've read that excellent
book
we actually carry it in our store if
people want to read it it's true
and he he basically
attempted to link all of biblical
history and
all of secular history together and give
everything in the bible a date they
tried to pin it down to a date and he
pinned
creation down to 4000 for bc this was an
amazing work of scholarship
he did make interpretive decisions as we
all do when we
interpret the bible but it probably
wasn't
exactly 4004 bc it's well within the
range
of all the things we've already talked
about yes there's you can't be that
precise
exactly okay but he also made an
assumption
one of the classic arguments is how long
were the israelites
in egypt some people say 430 years
some people say 215 because the promise
started with abraham
except which gives them two and usher
took the 215-year route which is a lot
of scholars have done
yes so that shaves off 215 years right
there oh wait a second now we're talking
about
a couple of hundred years difference
from one decision
there's something else we hear about a
lot and it's a bigger difference the
single biggest difference in all
biblical chronological studies
yes is the masoretic versus the
septuagint oh what's the septuagint
the septuagint is the greek translation
of the hebrew old testament
okay so we have the bible also in greek
yes shouldn't it be the same they just
translated it
well you never just translate a text
because when you translate a text or
interpretive decisions that's right you
go to different languages you have to
wrestle with some things okay and this
is a much bigger topic
but in some places it looks like
somebody
made intentional systematic changes to
the text
excuse me what well the septuagints
um numbers in genesis 5 and 11 give us a
substantially
longer timeline how much longer
about 1600 years oh that's a lot
yes okay now how do now are these just
like typographical errors or sloppy
scribe
doing something no not at all the reason
why i call them
intentional systematic changes is
for instance when the hebrew text says
adam was 130 years old and he fathered
seth and he lived
800 more years and he lived a total of
930 years
okay the septuagint says adam lived 230
years he fathered seth then he lived
700 years he lived a total of 930 years
and he died
two of those numbers are different and
they're different by exactly 100 years
exactly and you see the same thing with
seth he lived 105 years in the hebrew
he lived 205 years in the septuagint
before he fathered enosh
you see these intentional systematic
changes but because
there's a total life span in genesis
5.30
they were careful to adjust it so that
it still added up to the same age
wow okay so this is this is a huge
debate
and i know the audience might not know
but you and i
have written several important articles
on the
masoretic subtuition debate which will
be linked in the show notes but it
sounds like we're going to have to have
another long discussion
on septuagint yes this is going to be
fun
but i think we're going to have to table
it for now
yes okay so we'll get back to this we
promise you we'll be back with another
one on this subject
but to sum up here the age of the earth
is scripturally important
yes it's calculatable
for gradable i don't know it you we can
figure it out
um there are interpretive decisions that
have to be made
yes there are some big decisions that
affect
the date by centuries and we know
approximately at least in in the hebrew
masoretic bible that it's
6 000 plus a few years old yes all right
that's that's really good to know
a lot of people probably don't even know
how these numbers come about
if you need more information
creation.com
is a great repository of articles on the
subject
if you want to comment on this do
yourself a favor first
and review some of the background
material because you might be surprised
if you make a comment that
is a comment we hear a lot you might get
a
sharp reply from another person who has
actually read these articles
so this is really fun stuff we love
studying the bible we hope you love
studying the bible also
we want you to dig deeply not on the
just on the surface
thanks a lot we'll see you next time
you