one of the most popular ways to insert
millions of years into the bible
is by appealing to the gap theory today
on creation talk
what do we do with the gap theory
[Music]
hi welcome to creation talk i'm joe tay
and this is
gary bates and today we are dealing with
this question
what do we do with the gap theory yeah
but before we start
gary do you want to explain to us what
is the gap theory as you said in the
intro it's an idea to insert millions of
years in scripture
uh it was taught in our seminaries in
the 50s 60s 70s
and so people kind of my generation and
a bit older have been
exposed to that and as a result
um it's just been accepted it's a it's a
lot of what was taught in the bible
colleges and the seminaries
as i said based on the scofield's study
bible is where it originally came from
and many pastors today have accepted and
passed that
on in my experience and probably yours
most lay people don't really fully
understand the gap theory they've been
taught it and have just accepted it but
ultimately
it's an idea to try to insert millions
of years
into scripture somewhere you know if you
and i had a dollar for every idea we had
we'd be millionaires but this is one of
the most popular for the reasons i
mentioned so
we start with genesis 1 1 in the
beginning god created the heaven and the
earth
and then they allow a huge gap of time
verse 2 then talks about kind of the
filling of god's creation in six days
but between verse 1
and verse 2 we have this gap of deep
time and that supposedly just
solves everything because they don't
think it does you know violence to
scripture or the gospel
so is there anything else that's unique
to the gap theory that we
you know we hear about lucifer flood
what's that and
well why here's the thing and i always
say to people and if people are
listening
and maybe if it did to it i would just
ask you to
just to be open because we're going to
really deal with what the bible says
about this
first off is you don't get an idea of a
gap there from a natural reading of
scripture
we can talk about the the grammar in in
there
uh in a moment but the whole idea to
insert millions of years
was a deference to a secular
interpretation of the natural world and
when i say secular
we're talking about non-christian so
evolutionists
have said that the earth is millions and
billions of years old
now where do they get that idea from the
rock layers so that's where they get it
from
exactly it's the rock layers so uh now
those rock layers have what in them lots
and lots of
fossils and death yes so ultimately
just on the surface there the fall
didn't come into
the world until genesis chapter 3 death
and sin entered the world romans 5 12
the new testament says that but here
we've got all these rock layers in the
gap between genesis 1 1 and 1 2
with lots of fossils in them lots of
death
but putting that aside for a minute you
mentioned lucifer's flood yes
so they claim that those rock layers and
the fossils in them
were caused by something called
lucifer's flood
so what's what's that well remember the
genesis flood
which probably explains the majority of
them is not until chapter six
yes but here we have a lucifer's flood
this is a pre-adamic world
okay that uh lucifer
was allowed to rome and he destroyed
the earth that was and then what we're
reading from verse 2 is a reconstruction
of god's creation so some people call it
ruin reconstruction theory so is satan's
unfallen state
ruling on earth before adam was even
created
well it's not his unfallen state it's
his fallen state
because lucifer's flood is a judgment
okay so lucifer falls into sin
and god sends a lucifer flood to destroy
all life on earth
exactly but there's a problem with
lucifer satan
um actually falling before day six yes
that's right because i think
the bible is clear at the end of
creation week god saw all he had created
and it was
very good so how could satan have fallen
before sin entered the world well that's
the issue is is satan part of god's
creation job 38 tells us about
god creating the angels satan as a
fallen angel
and the word or the term very good at
the end of day six because we have
you know those days good good good we
get to day six it's very good
tov is the hebrew term and it means
perfection
completion so god's creation is finished
that kind of doesn't
really adequately describe well it was
good
then it was bad and then i made it good
again yes
as well so there's a problem uh with
that idea
people try to get out of that job by
quoting and i just want to look at the
biblical passage here ezekiel 28
yes some say that this refers to the
king of taya
some say it was first the fall of adam
and so on and so forth so gap theorists
appeal to this this is that passage
where it says
you were in eden in the garden of god
every precious stone was your covering
on that day you were created they
prepared you were anointed a guardian
cherub that's a key point isn't it so
what was the cherub
yeah so i placed you in the holy
mountain of god
uh and then it kind of talks about his
destruction because his heart was proud
what's your take on that
well even though there are many
interpretations of this passage
since the gap theories all agree that
this speaks about the fall of satan
let's use this view
and look at the gap theory and see
whether it's even consistent with what
they claim
it says right here we read about
anointed garden cherub
right and so what's the chair room an
angel yeah and not just an angel is the
angel that guards
the throne of god it covers overshadows
the ark of the covenant that's right
yeah yeah
and you remember when adam and eve were
chased from the garden god placed a trap
to guard it with a flaming sword correct
yeah so this being is in his unfallen
state
he says here that on the day he was he
was created
he was adorned with precious stones
where adam was created naked so this is
obviously something else
and he's walking in the garden of eden
he says that you were in eden the garden
of god
when was the garden of eden created yeah
yeah and i think we're getting a picture
from the holy mountain the stones that
this is
a perfect world yes so the fall has not
really occurred there you know you and i
were discussing before
we mentioned that the millions of years
comes from the rock layers yes
and so that lucifer's flood was a way of
explaining those you know rock layers
with fossils in them a difference
but um the secularists believe that
those rock layers were all laid down
slowly gradually
over millions of them yes so was lucifer
doing that over millions
of years you see my point that lucifer's
flood would have to
say well all those rock layers were laid
down instantaneously
i mean we kind of believe that as a
result of noah's flood what has happened
in the 12 months of the nova's flood
so isn't that actually a self-refuting
argument it is you see the the reason
why they come up with this idea of
lucifer's flood which is not even the
bible at all
right is because they want to explain
the rock layers and so when you believe
in the lucifer flood you have to deny
that no worse flood was a global
flood why because if lucifer's flood lay
down the rock layers
noah's flood would have destroyed all
the rock layers and laid down
its own rock layers yeah in other words
the rock layers
is no longer a record of millions of
years so when they believed in lucifer's
flood destroying all life they had to
say
no was flood was the local flood but but
lucifer's flood couldn't occur over
millions of years
but they're trying to say you know the
rock layers are millions of years which
is why we put a lucifer's flood in
that's a circular
circular reasoning that doesn't work
precisely it's an issue because now they
appear to lose the first flood for the
rock layers
but if lucifer flood was what laid down
all the rock layers
the rock layers is a record of a
one-time event yeah it's not slow
gradual millions of years
so let's discuss the syntax because this
is another one gap theorists appeal to
that
and it depends upon your which version
of the bible you're going to read
because at the
beginning of verse 2 scofield said that
this
could be rendered the earth became
void etc now some passages say and
was void and now was void at the uh
the beginning there we have something
it's a hebrew letter known as a valve
and here we have what's called a valve
disjunctive
the best way you can describe it it's a
pause in the narrative sequence so we
got yes in the beginning god created the
heavens and the earth
boom that's it and now we're going to
tell you what happened
but there's no huge gap of time there
and then following that we got something
really important which is
the same hebrew letter but we call it a
vav consecutive
yes and with the valve consecutive
that's why we read in our english bibles
and now and and and
and and it goes on all through genesis 1
through the whole six days
and that's telling us that these are you
know sequence of consecutive events
one after the other what's some other
points about this
this alleged gap this disjunctive that
don't work
yeah the gap theory tries to put
millions of years in between
verse one and verse two but this is what
genesis one
chapter verse one and two says it says
in the beginning god created the heavens
and the earth
and then he puts that valve disjunctive
which is now the earth was without form
and void
so the valve disjunctive is not an event
that occurs
after verse one verse two is not
something that occurs after verse one
verse two is a description of verse one
see verse one is a summary statement in
the beginning god created
that's the big key it's a summary
statement picture now we're going to
give you the detail
yes yes and that's okay now yes so if
you try to put a gap in between
verse 1 and verse 2 you really do not
understand hebrew at all
that's not the way the the syntax
doesn't allow you
to put a gap in between there so i want
to revisit those
the the uh the rock layers the
sedimentary layers
uh which is where the millions of years
comes from at the time of scofields
they found neanderthals yes that's right
they were alleged missing links
in my day growing up in school these
pictured as brutish
creatures but that's not the case
anymore yes so in the gap year
they used to believe that we find human
bones in the fossil record
and they say that was caused by
lucifer's flood so instead of calling
that humans they say that those are
sub-humans like neanderthals
right and so um but today we know
neanderthals they are fully human
they live in caves which in caves are
caused by the worldwide flood which
means they are descendants of
noah well they buried their dead they
had controlled use of fire made
cosmetics had musical instruments
and of course their dna has been
sequenced insulin
you have neanderthal genes in you and so
do i yes so if they bred with humans by
definition
yeah they're human so here's the
take-home point of that if
neanderthals which were alleged to be
missing links at the time of scofield
were in those rock layers
but they're fully human aren't we
putting humans
in the gap before day six of creation
when god said he made adam and eve
that's true but the gap here we try to
get around that they will say that these
are soulless
pre-adamic people yeah we've just seen
what we've just said the dna evidence
doesn't say that
the dna doesn't support so that's my
point that's the problem and these
people they're rituals that means they
have religious practices
so you have a group of soulless people
trying to worship some kind of deity
right
and then you're punished by lucifer's
flood for no fault of their own
destroyed
yeah but lucifer himself the guilty
party
escape to be able to attempt adam and
eve
in the new created war it doesn't make
sense at all so the guilty person the
guilty party satan himself
escaped scot-free and everyone else who
was innocent got destroyed as a result
of that
so we covered a lot of stuff there i
mean in our new series
the genesis academy in one of the
sessions i fully
discuss in more detail the gap theory
you can go to creation.com
type in gap theory soft gap theory
there's all sorts of different takes on
it
but let me just summarize the points
here that the whole idea
of the gap theory was to insert millions
of years in scripture
scofield his cohorts had deferred to a
secular interpretation of the natural
world
that said it was millions and billions
of years old the reason
is the millions of years comes from the
rock layers but then there's a problem
because there are fossils in those rock
layers
the genesis flood doesn't come happen
until chapter six
so we have a lucifer's flood to create
all the rock layers and the fossils
theological problem lucifer could not
have fallen before day six
then we've got neanderthal fossils
which they believed were missing links
now we know they're fully human
can't be because god didn't create adam
and eve until day six you can't have
humans in the fossil record before day
six of creation so there's a summary
statement
now i know some of you listening that's
very challenging i know from our own
experience joel when
you've held on to an idea it's what you
were taught maybe as a young christian
and you've reconciled this
tension between bible and the science 20
30 years ago perhaps
and it's all sorted out and here we are
trying to overturn that view hopefully
you will see
not from an arrogant point of view but
we've tried to point out the theological
problems with that
death before the fall being one of them
so again before you comment before you
say anything can i encourage you please
go to creation.com
type in gap theory lots and lots of
articles another great book is
refuting compromise by dr jonathan
sarfati
which covers all of these ideas of
trying to fit millions of years
in the scripture somewhere as well
anything you want to add on that joel at
all no i think that's good
all right and again thanks for joining
us don't forget to like
and share this and also if you're not
familiar there is a notification button
there
so as these new talks appear you can be
notified in your inbox on your phone
straight away
plug it into the car stereo bluetooth it
listen to it on your way to work
etc so we're trying to get information
out and we need you as a vehicle to do
that as well at cmi we're providing the
bullets
ultimately for you folks to fire so
thanks for joining us and we'll see you
next time
you