welcome today on creation talk we're
going to discuss whether our Bibles have
been changed what do you think
[Music]
well if you're joining us for this part
too just so you know in case we don't
cover some questions or thoughts you
might have we did do a part one I'm with
Lita cosna who did part one with me
welcome again leader hey Gary
so we're going to talk more about you
know the idea of transmission the Bible
being faithfully copied over time so we
said in the part one that people said
well what about all the copying mistakes
we discussed that the scribes were human
photo copiers who believed they were
dealing with God's Word and would have
treated it as such they would have been
very very careful not to make errors but
having said that we can determine hang
on folks
there are errors and the Bible's right
in some of the copies that we have now
you and I today we might call these
typographical errors correct so explain
how that may have occurred and how we
know that they've occurred well just
like the Bible was originally written by
men it was copied by men and if you
grabbed a book off of your shelf and
tried to make a handwritten copy you'd
have all sorts of errors in it and we
can see those same types of errors when
we look at manuscripts and skeptics
actually say did you know that there are
more errors in the Bible in the
manuscripts than there are actual words
in the Bible well that's only true if
you count every little spelling mistake
or even spelling variation it's a nice
sound bite isn't it yeah and it scares
people because we don't want to think oh
my Bible has errors in it but what but
once we understand that most of these
are just spelling errors or spelling
variations that couldn't possibly be
original that makes it a lot less scary
well I know so they don't change the
meaning of the text surely you know that
there's a very very few occasions my
understanding is where it might actually
change the meaning of a word or the text
itself and the wonderful thing about
Scripture is God doesn't teach us a
doctorate in only one place and no no
error affects a doctrine
and so you might have an error like we
don't know whether Paul said the Lord
Jesus Christ or just Jesus in one place
but doesn't change the major' we know
who he's referring to yeah exactly so we
have lots of family lines and various
copies that we can trace through various
geographical locations so surely that's
a cross-check as well we might see in
one family line and error introduced
over here we don't see it I mean that's
a little bit similar to you know me
looking it's studying or someone
studying your DNA right later and they
say well look here's a mutation and then
we check your mum and your dad and we
say well you got that from your mother's
line yeah and then we check your
mother's parents and can understand
where that error came in so in a lot of
cases can't they actually trace these
typos back to where they originally
introduced yes we can have some idea
where they came up and actually one of
the reasons we can have such great
confidence in the Bible we have today is
that it's based on so many copies we
have many many more copies of the
biblical documents than any other book
in history yeah let me let me jump on
that because if you went in the first
episode Leah and I have actually
co-written a booklet here called how did
we get our Bible and is that the Word of
God a lot of this information is in
there we have a lovely little chart in
there so people have heard for example
about Homer's famous Ilia you how many
copies we have today 643 right
Sophocles a hundred and ninety-three
manuscripts what about the New Testament
5700 I mean to me that's a bit of a
slam-dunk yes and we're still finding
new manuscripts today that there's a
ministry headed by a man and you can
watch his videos on YouTube dan Wallace
and because of what's happening in the
Middle East Dan Wallace's ministry is
trying to make digitized copies of all
the ancient manuscripts that we know
exist and when they go to someplace and
they haven't pulled off books for the
shelf what are they finding well they're
finding new manuscripts that we've never
before seen never before studied and
this is making these manuscripts in very
remote
locations available for scholars to
study all over the world and it's also
preserving them forever because
obviously when a manuscript is written
on parchment or papyrus this is a medium
that's going to wear out very quickly
and you know I think about the really
early people who studied manuscripts
like Erasmus was one of the first ones
and he sometimes only had a few
manuscripts to compare at most he had a
few manuscripts he couldn't have dreamed
of having the wealth of information we
have today so here's something where
personal preference comes in you see so
I was raised on NIV and you know I
personally you know like to still read
that today my parents and older
generations obviously they were raised
on something like the King James the ESV
is one of the more widely used ones
today here in the States the NASB is a
very very popular translation explain to
us the different modes particularly to
English that we have today and we're
going to get it a little technical but
it's worth understanding and then we'll
discuss whether we think there's a
better one how's that okay so a lot of
people ask us which translation is the
best one and to make a good informed
decision for yourself you should
understand it just a couple of terms
that describe the philosophy behind a
translation so a formal equivalence
translation tries to have word for word
so if it has the Greek word for heart
it's going to have the English word for
heart but some well-known formal
equivalence translations are the King
James Version the New King James Version
the English standard version and the new
American Standard Bible if you look at
them side by side by side they're going
to seem very similar because they have a
very similar translation philosophy and
then on the other side of the spectrum
you have dynamic equivalents now some
people say that these are not literal
translations they're trying to be
literal in a different way they're
trying to do thought forethought
translation and there are times in
translation where do
thought forethought is better now with
that because words would change their
meanings for example so what an original
word might say might have a different
meaning today so they're trying to
faithfully render the meaning of the
words would that be a correct analogy
yes and one instance of thought
forethought translation is in Romans
Paul says may it never be and a dynamic
equivalence translation might say god
forbid that it's a very good translation
of what that thought actually means of
course there's another one that most of
us probably cut our teeth on as young
baby Christians and that's what we call
a paraphrase a paraphrase is where
they're trying to rephrase scripture and
attempt to make it more understandable
and that's often meant for either
children or for people who aren't really
literate in the language where it's
being translated yeah or new to
scripture and they're wanting a better
understanding of it exactly so be fair
to say I mean you know to be honest when
I was a very young Christian I read a
paraphrase and it helped me understand
it but certainly they would not be it
would not be the best type of
translation to do a scholarly study on
you'd be looking for a formal
equivalence or or a dynamic equivalence
as a second best bet on that correct yes
we believe that it's the actual words of
Scripture that are inspired and so
that's why scholars even today will try
to go back to the Greek and Hebrew
because they want to get as close back
to the original as possible now of
course there's a few dodgy ones out
there and we make no apologies for
saying this some of the alleged cults
that call themselves Christians yes like
the Jehovah's Witnesses etcetera have
their own versions and we can clearly
see even in our English translations
where they've been modified correct yes
all right so now again please understand
we are an evangelical organization but
the Catholic Church has actually added a
few books yes what's the background to
that well in in the wake of the
Reformation the the Roman Catholics had
the Council of Trent and the big issue
was does the church decide what
scripture is or description the church
well the Roman Catholics came down
decisively on the position that the
Church decides scripture and to make
that point in the Council of Trent
they added what's called the deutero
Canon which are some books that are
preserved in the Septuagint which is the
Greek Old Testament but these are books
that were originally in Greek not Hebrew
and the Jews considered them history but
not Scripture and so for the first time
in history the Catholic said these
aren't just history these aren't just
helpful additional resources these are
Scripture and so we would say that they
aren't Scripture we have a 66 book Canon
but the Roman Catholics do consider the
Deuter canon to be they but they do
include the 66 books that that we have
as well in other words they've just got
some other ones added to them so look
we've had a very concise discussion
about this we literally could write a
tome on it and I know you'd love to okay
but what's the purpose of all this the
Bible isn't it isn't it like if I wanted
to say well if there is a God and he
wanted to communicate to us how would he
do it I mean is he gonna zap you and I
are we going to be basing it on our
feelings or a dream what's he giving us
he's given us his word and as we said in
part one it's a history book it does
give us information about how to live
our life but more importantly it
explains that the world we're living in
is a fallen one it's a corrupt one it's
not normal bad things happen one of the
most asked questions that people have so
it helps us doesn't it would you agree
make sense of our world and then the big
picture is of course this world is not
the only one right there's one to come
yes and you know Jesus said if I've told
you earthly things and you don't believe
how will you believe when I tell you
heavenly things and so when the Bible
tells us things that are historically
verifiable or scientifically verifiable
if if we can't trust that how can we
trust it when it tells us how to be
saved and even more fundamentally than
that
what even is the Bible and it's more
important than ever to be able to answer
these questions today well that same
Jesus we're talking about it says in
Colossians chapter 1 verse 15 the Sun is
the image that storm about Jesus of the
invisible God the firstborn over all
creation for in him all things were
created things in heaven and on earth
visible and invisible whether Thrones or
powers rulers or authorities all things
have been created through him and for
him that's the Creator Jesus is the
creator so you know when he talks about
scripture when he believes the Old
Testament as we said earlier we should
probably take his word for yes because
it is his word well thanks for joining
us again today and again if you want
more information go to creation.com and
you can certainly get this nice concise
a little booklet through our webstore
and one of the things we didn't show
check this out later
why don't we explain what I'm showing
people there well there are 2800 cross
references there where the Bible
references other parts of the Bible and
so it's like the Bible is constantly
cross-referencing itself you can't
remove one of those books without taking
along with it a whole bunch of those
cross references so the Bible is really
a cell for thickening document yeah well
we often call it 66 books but ultimately
it's one but it's one book and there you
have a 2800 cross references from
Genesis to Revelation the Canon of
Scripture
thanks a lot leader and thanks for
watching online or listening to your
podcast and again I encourage you to
share this and make sure you click like
and get this information out there we'll
look forward to seeing you next time
you