today on creation talk where did the
Bible come from and is it the Word of
God
[Music]
by today I'm here with our New Testament
specialist Lita cosna hi Lita hey Giri
and this is one that's not just only a
debate you know from non-christians and
skeptics but even within Christian
circles about the various manuscripts
and so on we're going to deal with that
a little bit more in depth in another
session because this is something we're
not going to cover in today's podcast so
we're just going to deal with the first
subject which is where did the Bible
come from a lot of people think well
it's just a religious book you know
there are lots of religious books in the
world you can think about all that great
religions of the world and they tell
people how to live you know what they
should do with their lives whether
there's an afterlife or not how to get
there and certainly the Bible does that
to some extent but I think the Bible's
quite unique because it also purports to
be a history book and obviously
something our ministry specializes in is
the creation account how the world and
the universe came to be that is
certainly a history book but the
skeptics main argument in this area
later is that the Bible is just a book
written by men and of course it's been
copied and copied and copied and copied
and we know it was copied by people
called scribes tell us who were the
scribes what do we know about him human
photocopy is right well we know that the
scribes who were copying these
manuscripts they believed this to be the
Word of God and so obviously if you're
copying something you believe to be the
Word of God you're going to be very
careful with it you're going to have
measures in place to keep the copies
accurate one particular group of
copyists called the macerates they
developed elaborate traditions around
copying to make sure that each line had
exactly the amount of letters that were
supposed to be there and so we know that
their copies were very very accurate so
with all of our articles that appear in
creation magazine or the Journal of
creation or on creation.com
I mean you've written stuff and I
proofread it and I write stuff and you
proofread it and we do that with each
other
of course we don't believe what we're
writing is the Word of God so in these
cases obviously they're gonna have a lot
of checks and balances aren't they yeah
you know not just some guy writing and
saying well here it is
I finished there's going to be a
checking procedure shortly yes okay so
we can believe or understand they
believe they were handling the Word of
God they would have treated it with that
respect now in a next session we're
going to talk about you know what errors
maybe were introduced but let's talk
about inspiration because one of the
critics arguments is that well you guys
believe the Bible because the Bible says
it's the Word of God they believe it's a
circular argument of course 2nd Timothy
3:16 says all Scripture is breathed out
or inspired right by God but isn't it
more than that you know you and I have
discussed this we've co-written a
booklet by the way if you're interested
called how did we get our Bible and is
it the Word of God and some of these
arguments in there and we talked about
inspiration it's so inspiration let me
just qualify that before I ask you
inspiration is that God's Spirit is
moving men to write is that how we
understand it
yeah and it's it's a very unique sort of
idea because we believe that the Holy
Spirit used these men and so it's
actually what they wrote he's using
their minds their experiences their
vocabularies their personalities but
he's superintending the process he's
overshadowing these men so that what
they produce is entirely without error
and it is actually the Word of God so it
is their thoughts in a way the way that
they would write yes but still conveying
in say in a sense what God wanted them
to to write and explain yes and looking
at the original languages anyone who can
look at the original Greek or the
original Hebrew there's a very marked
difference in style between Luke and the
Apostle John and the Apostle Paul they
have very different ways of using
vocabulary and grammar and you can tell
just from reading them that they're
different people now you certainly can't
in fact some of the Gospels that are
under dispute they look for
markers to try to find out who they're
written by right so the other thing to
point out is we're not saying you know
my ESV translation today is inspired
correct correct when we talk about
inspiration we're talking about the
original documents so what Moses
originally wrote is inspired by God and
errors may have crept in over time and
that there's a different there's a
different way for us to tell that what
we have is what Moses originally wrote
but when we're talking inspiration we're
technically only talking about the
originals which are also sometimes
called the autographs right so in the
next session we're going to talk about
some of the manuscript families and how
we can actually tell that the meaning of
God's Word has not changed over time so
hang in there for that one folks we're
not ignoring it we will get there now
the types of inspiration so you know you
mentioned earlier God is moving men to
write it's not a form of dictation I
mean in some cases we see God speaking
to men and they basically recorded that
yes but when the men are recounting
history or events in their lifetimes
it's not a strict form of dictation
right yes so sometimes we do see the
Bible saying Yahweh says the Lord says
and so that is dictation and we see for
instance where God tells Jeremiah write
this down and deliver it to the king
yeah so we do see some instances of
dictation but more often it's a little
bit more indirect than that for instance
we can see when David says Oh Lord my
lord how majestic is your name in all
the earth it's not like God is saying
okay David write this down Oh Lord my
lord he David is speaking out of the
overflow of his own heart expressing
worship to God and the Holy Spirit is
ensuring the David's expression is
theologically accurate and in the New
Testament you see that Luke he was a
very good historian and he was doing
research he was look he was tracking
down sources and eyewitnesses and so the
Holy Spirit was working in that process
of research and
good historiography ensuring that the
product was inerrant sir okay leader so
you mentioned one thing there a lot of
people have written out of the fullness
or the overflow of their heart about God
and their relationship with him that
would have been no different you know in
ancient times as it is today when people
right so who decided right I mean I know
I'm asking you the question but who
decided how did we how did the the the
Bible come to be in terms of the
collection of the sixty-six books was it
you know God says choose these books was
it some sort of lottery how did we get
the sixty-six books today that formed
the Canon of Scripture because that's a
big one because you know in the Catholic
Church for example they have extra books
that we don't have in the evangelical
church so how did the Canon of Scripture
come to be it's a bit of a different
argument for the Old Testament versus
the New Testament when when we're
talking about the Old Testament Canon
these are the books that ancient Jews
recognized to be Scripture and by the
time of Jesus you have basically two
people two different groups that have
two different canons of Scripture the
Pharisees had basically our Old
Testament Canon and then the Sadducees
said only the Torah only the five books
written by Moses are Scripture the ones
that didn't believe in the resurrection
exactly it was already settled by the
time of the New Testament in other words
yes and Jesus accepted basically the
Pharisees Canon of Scripture yeah so and
as Christians obviously we follow Christ
we believe that he had the correct Old
Testament Canon because of course he
inspired it well he believed in it so
should we yes so New Testament so there
are lots of you know wider books we see
around the New Testament times who
determined which books formed the New
Testament well in the very early years
of course the church is being persecuted
these texts are forbidden having
Christian texts in your homes could
actually get you killed it was actually
illegal to be a Christian and so it was
illegal to have New Testament texts so
it was obviously very important for the
early Christians to know
which texts were Scripture and which
were not because you could die for
having these days you don't want to you
don't want to be murdered on the basis
of having a wrong manuscript right
exactly and so by the time of the
Council of Nicaea which is in the 300s
ad we see that they had a well developed
developed Canon which is the same as our
Canon today and they had a couple of
they had a couple of ways to determine
whether a book should be in the Canon
the first is was it written by an
apostle of Jesus or one of their close
associates so somebody like the Apostle
John or close associate like like Luke
or John Mark yeah the second was the
books had to be accepted by the whole
church you couldn't have a book that
Alexandria really liked but Rome
rejected sure the third thing is it
couldn't contradict any other Scripture
and so if you had something that said oh
Jesus seemed like God but he was really
just a man that would be rejected
because it contradicts the rest of
Scripture well it contradicts true
Scripture and so that book would be
rejected so how do we know the Bible's
inspired Matthew 5:17 18 obviously
famous verse everyone knows not an iota
not a dot will pass from all the law
until it is or until all is accomplished
and then of course in John 10:35
scripture cannot be broken so scripture
is treating itself like Scripture
clearly right right and even more than
that Jesus said both of those things and
so we get our doctrine of inspiration of
Scripture from Jesus we don't have to
prove it because we have an infallible
source that tells us it is right great
criteria to start with is to accept the
Jesus who he says he is yes that he is
God in the flesh and then of course what
he says about Scripture ultimately goes
I mean that's a very important thing he
believed in a literal creation account
he believed in literal adam and eve a
literal flood you and i have written
that we shouldn't reinterpret those
areas because jesus clearly believed
what he was reading as well yes and he
believed that scripture was preserved
well enough that he based a whole
argument in Matthew 22 when he's arguing
with his opponents he he bases his whole
argument on the tense of one word I am
the God of Abraham Isaac and Jacob and
so that's how he proves to the Sadducees
that there is a resurrection because God
is God of the living not of the dead we
can get into the area of prophecy and a
contentious area because people have
different views on different scriptures
but there are some pretty
straightforward ones and you know people
will argue some prophecy has not been
fulfilled which has but there's a couple
of cast-iron ones we can look at in the
Old Testament as a creation as - one of
my favorite is job 26:7
where he says talking about God he
stretches out the north over the void
and he hangs the earth on nothing I mean
should we take something like that
literally yeah people would say well you
know job wasn't a scientist he couldn't
have known that the earth was a sphere
hanging in space but I actually believe
even if he didn't understand that that
he was faithfully recording what God
indicated to him there's a similar
passage in isaiah 40:22 God sits
enthroned above the circle of the earth
and it's people like like grasshoppers
the word circle in English is actually
the Hebrew word we might transliterated
kook which we could describe as a
vaulted object even as a sphere or
something that has dimensions and is
solid it's not flat and a circle like
this table now when we look at some of
the prophecies about Jesus in particular
that's where it gets pretty exciting
doesn't it we have the prophecy
regarding the destruction of Jerusalem
in AD 70 his own crucifixion before
crucifixion was even invented now I know
you love history but what about Daniel -
I mean there's a whole litany of areas
there that we saw fulfilled you want to
explain that well that's the passage of
course where daniel tells
Nebuchadnezzar's dream to him and
interprets the dream and it's the famous
edge of the statue with the feet of iron
and clay he accurately predicts the the
four great kingdoms and there's no way
that Daniel could have known
naturally the socio-political climate
that would make each of these kingdoms
arise
well they rise and fall pretty quickly
in history yes as conquering armies come
in and invade and some of the armies or
the kingdoms that he referred to didn't
even exist yet exactly yes yeah you know
in in our little Bible another plug
there once again a little Bible booklet
yeah don't call it our little Bible it's
not inspired thank you later
even though you wrote it okay well we
did right in there
and calculating the estimates of just
one man listen to this fulfilling just
eight prophecies okay let's think about
Old Testament prophecies the charts
would be one in 10 to the 28th power if
you want an analogy it would be the same
as a blindfolded person picking the
right Silver Dollar think 50 cent piece
of here in Australia out of enough
silver dollars to cover the state of
Texas two feet deep that's just eight
prophecies to get them all right I mean
they are unfathomable odds and yet we
see that consistency don't we through
Scripture scriptures written over a
couple of thousand years right and
written in different countries by
different men and we're going to
discover discuss next time there are no
contradictions I mean just that alone
what would be the chances is over every
person in a different time in a
different country writing in in their
own sphere of influence and yet we see
the nature of God his purposes for the
gospel being played out continually in
all of these different locations yes it
just shows us that the Bible is really
one book with one ultimate author
exactly we're going to have a part two
on this and we're going to talk more
about alleged errors in the Bible and
alleged contradictions and how we can be
sure in fact that the Bible hasn't
changed over long periods of
so once again thank you for joining us
Thank You leader and don't forget to
share this information with your friends
you've probably had these questions
yourself click the like button and also
make sure you subscribe to receive
notifications when new podcasts become
available thank you for listening and
for watching
[Music]