well welcome everyone to the latest
cmi podcast this time we're going to
talk about
who was kane's wife
now i'm dr jonathan sarfati and with me
is dr rob
carter welcome thanks general good to be
here
well thanks again for your assist
especially as you're an expert in
genetics and this is going to be very
relevant to what we're talking about but
this has been a common skeptical
objection for quite a while
rage is something christians have never
thought of
but what is the actual problem here
curtains kind of just married
into one of the other people groups
around the place what's the problem with
that view
this question actually has a lot of
background material that
maybe we should cover because some
people might not be aware of what we're
talking about
okay well the issue is the bible as
there's
adam and eve had cain
and abel kane of course was as a
murderer of abel but
also it talks about cain having children
so
whom did he marry and since the bible
says adam and eve are the only people
around
it seems to be a contradiction that just
a short time later now all of a sudden
cain's got a wife and he's worried about
people are going to kill him because he
killed his brother
and so why couldn't there have been
other people around do you think that's
a good question in fact this goes way
back this is part of the scope's monkey
trial
uh was famously part of that that
terribly inaccurate movie and play
called inherit the wind
oh goodness modern people you know
younger people today they don't ask this
question nearly as much
but you know back over the decades it's
a question we got asked
often well certainly my our predecessors
and the creation apologetic
were saying this is the most commonly
asked question it's not quite so much in
our experience nowadays
but the issue seems to be well the bible
talks about adam as the first man
explicitly
yeah so then how could cain have a wife
and eve was the mother of all living so
clearly there weren't any
para adamic people pre-adamites around
they're the only people so
where did he get his wife from him
what's the answer well
the answer um theologically is quite
simple
he married his sister or his niece or
his grandniece or his great-grandniece
but one of the
females around that time but i thought
adam and eve only had um
cain and abel that's the big
issue the bible says adam and eve had
cane
then they had abel and then when adam
was 130
they had a third son named seth yep well
that sounds like that's the birth order
and it sounds like cain's gonna have to
wait an awfully long
time for a sister to be born but
then he's got a family and he's building
a city so
the answer actually is is asking the
question how old was kane
when he killed abel or an article about
this is on creation.com
and so how old was he well the answer is
we don't know but how much time did he
have
right and also it says adam
and eve had seth but they also had other
sons and daughters which people usually
forget about but it's very clear in
genesis 5
4 other sons and daughters and
presumably a lot of them were around
at the time when seth was born do you
think eve names
seth essentially replacement you know
for
for he replaced the son who had died so
he is the first son born
after abel dies but
cain and abel could have been up to 130
years old wow that's a long time
they could have been great great
grandparents by then
whoa i mean it's not it's not like you
know
kane abel seth and then in some future
distant
there's some daughter but even if that
was true this still wouldn't be a
problem
because okay so the the bible is
semi-chronological here but we're
skipping over centuries of information
and so it just says you know kane had a
wife and they built a city that could
have been
two three four hundred years later
that's quite a lot of time
people don't seem to realize but it's
also interesting when you look at the
history of how
christian apologists throughout the ages
have discussed this
they were also well aware that kane
logically had to marry his sister
theodorette
in the 5th century bishop of cyrus and
then much later in the reformation
martin luther said well yeah he married
his sister
but then there are usually two main
objections to that
there's a moral one and a scientific one
so what's the moral objection to kane
marrying a sister then
well incest is illegal incest is gross
incest
is contrary to the bible so
why how could this have happened then
what's the issue how do we solve this
problem
well what we do is we look in scripture
to see when did
incest become illegal and the answer is
the time of moses thousands of years
after creation
so basically god doesn't make ex
post-facto law it couldn't have been
sinful until god said it was sinful
yeah so why was it okay back in
cain's time but not okay in moses time
in fact it was actually okay in
abraham's time because abraham married a
half-sister that's right he did
and god blessed that marriage right and
then jacob married his his two cousins
first cousins and the messiah came from
that line that's right in fact
after that between terra
abraham isaac and jacob that family had
intermarried
three or four generations in a row my
goodness that's
quite startling yeah i didn't really
realize that do they a shocking amount
of inbreeding there
well we are seeing some issues pop up
though we are okay because
you know sarah couldn't have children
took a miraculous intervention of god
yeah uh rebecca only had
two hmm and took a long time to have
those two as well took a long time of
those two
esau is covered in hair it's called the
wolfman gene
if you had the modern version of that
wow okay
um so he's got an issue there um then we
have leah who has
weak eyes whatever that means we don't
know but she's not desirable as a
partner and then her sister
um rachel rachel dies in her second
attempt at childbirth
after a long time getting pregnant the
first time after having struggling to
get pregnant the first time so we're
seeing
issues pop up here genetic issues okay
in the bible so on a genetic basis
what's actually causing those genetic
issues with inbree what's the problem
today
say with brother marrying a close
relative like a sister
what's the issue here well today the
human population is carrying
millions of what are called deleterious
or bad mutations which uh what's a
mutation
it's a change in the dna code so we have
this recipe book
says here's how to build a person it's
called the human genome we each carry
two copies of it and every once in a
while
as a mother or father manufactures a new
code
for the child a mistake happens right
you have a spelling error essentially
and they're no big deal usually
most of them why would that be because
the mutation's only on one of those
halves and not on the other so you can
because backup copies
yeah because god engineered us with a
backup copy which is really really good
sound engineering design principle no
it's redundancy yeah redundancy
that's why we're still alive if we only
have one copy of the genome
human race should already be extinct oh
goodness that's serious stuff but
because every time something breaks we
have a backup copy
you keep on trucking problem is when you
marry someone
closer related to you there's a higher
probability that
both of you are carrying a mutation and
that both of you could pass that
mutation to a child and then they have
two copies of the mutation
and they're usually not as fit or robust
or at least we could say a lot of times
you can't notice anything
but when it does appear the double dose
of that mutation will harm the child
i think we see it in other animals don't
we like purebred
dogs compared to the mongrel bits as we
say in australia bits of everything
and there's a purebred seem to have
these problems same sort of
reasoning you think yeah purebred
animals
across the spectrum doesn't matter where
species we're talking about they have
a lot of problems with mutations and we
have to be very careful
looking at the bloodlines trying to you
know like they got hip dysplasia out of
the german shepherd took a long time and
they i think they still pop up every
once in a while
one of the classic examples of
inbreeding is king carlos ii of spain
okay the end of the spanish habsburgs
after many many generations of this
family interbreeding
he turned turned up with two different
mutations
at the same time ooh he couldn't close
his mouth
he couldn't actually chew food his teeth
didn't meet
oh gosh and he was uh mentally not quite
there
and his death triggered what's called
the war of the spanish succession
oh that was serious stuff yeah yeah so
we we see inbreeding has
actually you know societal level impacts
here
wow but god didn't put a restriction on
it until the time of moses
1500 bc after thousands of years of
mutations had accumulated
right so you think kane and abel and
seth would not have had
this problem then nah there would have
been no problem marrying your sister
because there's no mutations in the
population yet
just like after the flood noah's
grandchildren they would have had to
have married each other there's nobody
else around and it wasn't a problem
except we do see the lifespan plummet
and you think so the inbreeding actually
had an effect on that lifespan even that
early stage then yeah because there
would have been some mutations around
and we would have lost some percentage
of the diversity from before the flood
on the ark because it's only you know
six people shame ham and javed their
three wives that's it that's the rest of
humanity
they can't carry every single gene
then they just started breeding like
crazy so but why wouldn't
cain have had many mutations why would
adam and eve have had mutations you
think
because when god created adam and eve he
pronounced creation
very good there's no
there's no sin yet in the world there's
no death in the world there's no
suffering in the world
everything is very good which means it's
perfect
and the mutations are copying mistakes
yes and god doesn't make mistakes
that's right now that doesn't mean that
adam and eve didn't have any genetic
diversity
but it does mean they weren't carrying
the genes for hereditary blindness
or sickle cell anemia or any one of the
other
great number of mutations that we see in
the human population today
and that's something you would have
discussed in your previous podcasts with
keaton halley on
adam and eve and genetics right so if
you want to look up you guys
on our podcast channel see the previous
podcast
adam and eve so the issue seems to be
adam and eve had no mutations at all
when they were created so therefore cain
and abel probably had none
and the sister probably had be hardly
any as well
and so you're talking about a time of
abraham and his family so it's about
2000 years later you've got problems
already
surfacing now in fact in the flood 1600
years later you've pointed out this
huge drop of lifespan because of the
force
in breeding between the six
people who are still breeding after the
flood uh so the time modes are talking
about another
500 years or so at least yeah
and then you think this this issue of
inbreeding was going to become a problem
yeah well it was already a problem some
places like when we look at
neanderthals they're scattered across
from spain to siberia
well it's just long-range huge range and
there's never many of them
only a few thousand neanderthals at the
most as the population geneticists have
estimated
okay but when we look at them they're
the most inbred population we've ever
seen
and you can tell from the fossils that
this the inbreeding
produce some problems then yes we also
can tell from their dna
okay they're carrying a lot of bad
mutations some of which appear in modern
humans and cause disease
okay they're also um their
heterozygosity level isn't
isn't is way down what does that mean it
means that
um they have a very high likelihood of
having two identical pieces of dna
from their mother and their father which
means their mother and their father are
closely related
and that means they could also inherit
the same mutation from mothers
exactly oops see that's not very good
exactly so they were getting um
really hammered by this mutation
accumulation problem
that we're seeing in people today even
though there's seven billion of us
it's been a long time for mutations to
accumulate in the human population and
across the world we're actually laboring
under this problem
oh yeah yeah but it wasn't a problem
in the garden right so the inbreeding
question with kane
is irrelevant the word cain get his wife
question
has easily answered scripturally it's
actually
not a problem it's just when you just
take a
you know ten thousand foot view and just
skim through genesis really quickly
oh wait a minute how this happened how
this worked but the the answer is
trivial
i'm struck by how often these atheists
or critics
bring up a problem and think the
christians have never even thought about
it but then you can go back
um hundreds and even over a thousand
years and find that christian
experts have actually already thought
about this problem but there's a sort of
lack of of
respect for historical precedence um
around
sadly some parts of the church but also
a lot of the atheist attackers
yeah but that's how it works isn't it
you threw out an
easy question if the person doesn't know
it it looks like a hard question
that's true so the lesson is to be very
well prepared as much as he can be
yes study this show thy self-approved
right there you go
and presumably god has produced this law
against
incest to actually protect us yes to
some extent
yes it's a it's a good protection also
because
if we were allowed to marry people very
closely related there's some cultures in
the world today where
first cousin marriages are very common
right um it would actually have
an impact on our health and well-being
and our pocketbooks
because it would be impacting the health
systems
in fact darwin married her first cousin
if i recall too and every one of her
brothers and
every one of her sisters also married
first cousins
oh good really very much the wedgewood
and darwin families
oh my goodness yes and does that produce
any problems that you know of
um darwin lamented the fact that he
shouldn't have married his cousin
oh even he talked about um
in animal breeding how close uh matings
are are
very often bad okay so this problem was
known before they even worked out
genetics with
gregor mendel that she knew there was
still a problem with the close
yeah but they did it anyway one of the
reasons to do this by the way is just to
keep money in the family
yeah two brothers sit down hey your
daughter marries my son
and you know their kids inherit the
estate so
financially and practically it makes a
lot of sense
but it's just a really bad idea and
hence the brave
with royals as well doing the same sort
of thing keeping it in the family
yeah so yeah darwin had a lot of kids
some of them died young though yeah
many of them died young i think only out
of ten kids i think only
three went on to have kids of their own
so there is
there is a darwin descendant family but
there are a few casualties along the way
it sounds like
yes so the summary answer to this
is that kane married his sister that's
unavoidable but it wasn't
easy but the niece where the knees come
from you think
brother sister right yeah yeah one of
his brothers married
one of his sisters and he could have
married a niece that makes sense too
yeah that's possible but you can't
escape the brother sister into marriage
must have been an issue
absolutely has to be true and as you
pointed out it wasn't an issue
morally because god hadn't prohibited it
that's right
and also not an issue biologically
because the mutation
load was very low at the time but it's
an issue
now so and god has said don't do it
yeah well thank you everyone
and make sure to tune in for uh future
podcasts but also
look at the related resources that we
recommend for further reading there's
also
a related podcast on this issue by dr
carter on the on the genetics of adam
and eve
but also look at some of the related
articles below
this video thank you very much for
[Music]
watching