Some say the age of the earth is
irrelevant to Christianity because
it's not a salvation issue. That's partially true.
But a wrong view on the age of the
earth does have Gospel implications
and we'll explain how today
on Creation Magazine LIVE
Welcome to Creation Magazine
LIVE, I'm Alexander Osborne
and I'm Richard Fangrad. Today
we're looking into questions like:
Do you need to be a young earth
creationist to be a Christian?
Does the age of the earth impact Gospel doctrines,
like how Jesus's physical death paid for sin?
And, if it does, should 6-day, recent creation
be a part of your church's Statement of Faith?
If the age of the earth doesn't impact essential
doctrines then why on earth
are we doing these shows?
What's the point of this entire
ministry? Is the question
about when God created really a
hill to die on for Christians?
Our experience has been that these questions
provoke a lot of, sometimes heated discussions.
So in the next half hour we're going to
carefully work through each of these questions.
Not sure this will help. It will likely cause a
bit of confusion, but the direction we're heading
here today is that the age of the earth issue is
not a salvation issue, but it is a Gospel issue.
Now we're going to spend the
rest of our time explaining that.
Let’s begin by repeating what we've said
many times: you do not have to be a young
earth creationist to be a Christian.
So there's the first question answered.
Now for you die hard creationists out
there who are shocked at our answer,
please be patient we'll add more explanation in a
minute. Meanwhile others might be thinking: Hey!
If CMI admits that people don't need to
believe that God created recently to be
saved then it's not a salvation issue, right?
It doesn't matter. It's a side issue. It
doesn't matter period. So why do young earth
creationists make such a big deal about it?
Because it's a Gospel issue.
Right. It does matter. It is a big deal. Now it's
going to take some time to explain why it actually
is a Gospel issue. Let's start with this question:
what do you need to believe to be saved? Well,
you need to believe that there's one true God.
That God is holy. That our sin separates us from a
holy God. That God sent Jesus to die for our sins
that He raised Jesus from the dead. If you ask for
forgiveness for your sins and put your faith in
Jesus as Saviour and Lord you will be saved. Amen.
Notice creation isn't on that list. That's
right. What else isn't on that list? Your
view on abortion. Your view on how many genders
there are. Your view on racism and what should be
done to overcome racist attitudes. Whether
Hell means eternal conscious punishment or
simply annihilation. What you believe about
the sequence and character of end times events
and the return of Christ and the nature
of the New Heavens and the New Earth
your views on Calvinism versus Armenianism and
how one reconciles man’s responsibility with
God's sovereignty in salvation. Your views on
the role of the Holy Spirit in a believer's life
and whether certain miraculous gifts ceased with
the apostolic age or whether they continue today.
Whether the kenotic theory or the hypostatic union
more accurately describes the incarnation. Your
views on the inerrancy of Scripture. Your
view on the Trinity. Your view on whether
Jesus physically died and physically rose from
the dead as opposed to just a spiritual death.
Okay. Slow down there buddy. I'm sorry.
But some of those are important doctrines. Very
important. The point is is that there are many
many issues along with the age of the earth
issue that people don't need to have a solid
understanding of in order to be saved, right?
Or let's just say to get into the kingdom.
Just like the thief on the cross.
Right that's a good example
like he didn't understand
core Christian doctrines and yet he was saved.
That's right. However some of you
might be saying: now wait a minute,
those are important issues and some of them have
a huge impact on how we understand the Gospel.
That's true. Some of those things, if
you have an unbiblical view of them,
it will lead to the destruction of
the Gospel. But is it necessary to
fully understand the biblical description
of any of those issues in order to be saved?
Well, no. For example, you don't need to fully
understand that there is one God who manifests
himself in three persons in order to be saved,
right? Right. But the doctrine of the Trinity
is vital to the Gospel. If Jesus were only a
man, and not also at the same time fully God,
no matter how good he was then he was incapable
of taking the sins of the world on himself, right?
That's right. So, you can be confused about the
Trinity and still be saved. But the doctrine of
the Trinity is so vital that if you take the
position, so moving beyond confusion here,
that Jesus isn't God, it puts you outside
of orthodox Christianity. Like Mormons,
Jehovah’s Witnesses, Unitarians and others.
So, while a confused understanding
of the doctrine of the Trinity,
for example, may not prevent someone from
being truly saved it is vital to the Gospel.
And we'll add more details in just a minute.
What sort of catastrophe would be required to
entomb over 120 species of marine invertebrates in
fine-grained rock? This is not just a hypothetical
question. In the Canadian Rockies over 120 species
of marine invertebrates have been found preserved
in a famous formation known as the Burgess Shale.
Most of these animals were soft-bodied and many
are so exquisitely preserved that you can still
see the food in their stomachs. It appeared they
were buried and preserved almost instantaneously.
Moreover, the creatures were apparently buried in
turbulent conditions because the fossils are found
dumped at a variety of angles relative to the
bedding. Fossil graveyards like this are found
all over the world collectively they point
to catastrophic flooding occurring on a
worldwide scale because the global flood
recorded in the Bible actually occurred.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Okay, let's clarify how understanding
a certain doctrine would not be needed
for salvation yet is needed for the Gospel.
It may help if we think of a timeline here. For
all those of you who have been Christians for
a while think of your own life and your own walk
with Christ. At the point you were saved you had,
let's say, a basic understanding of
what salvation was all about. Maybe you
weren't sure about the Trinity and didn't have an
understanding of what Jesus ‘emptied himself’ of,
but as you grew spiritually through reading God's
Word and fellowshipping with other believers,
your understanding of the nuances
of the Gospel doctrines deepened.
Think of the kenosis of Christ for example.
Kenosis comes from a Greek word that is
often translated ‘to empty’ like in Philippians
2:7, where it says that Jesus “emptied himself
by taking the form of a servant,
being born in the likeness of men.”
Early in your Christian life you may
have thought that this meant that Jesus
gave up his divine attributes like omniscience,
omnipotence, omnipresence, but he didn't.
He certainly kept those veiled, most of the time,
but it's clear throughout the New Testament that
Jesus had those attributes. And also, the people
at the time understood that he claimed to be God,
equal with God the father, and they
were ready to kill him because of it.
Exactly. And the true identity of
Christ is critical to the Gospel,
but, can you see how not fully understanding
it doesn't prevent you from being saved.
Most people only come to know important
doctrines, like the hypostatic union,
for example, after they're saved. As
believers continue to be transformed
by the renewing of their mind the
details of the Gospel become clearer.
And in the same way, you can believe that the
earth is millions of years old and be saved,
but it's massively inconsistent with
the Gospel, and we'll show you how.
We're going to list now four key points that
connect the age of the earth issue to the Gospel.
Point number one is: in genesis 1:31
God pronounced his creation “very good”.
And in the two verses before that we read
that in the very good world both people and
animals ate plants. So, before sin there was
no death, no disease, no bloodshed, you didn't
need to worry about being violently attacked by
wild animals, or bitten by poisonous animals,
or getting pricked by thorns even, or accidentally
eating poisonous plants. It was a very good world.
And there's a lot more detail that can be deduced
from Scripture to support the conclusion that the
‘very good’ world, before sin, did not
include the death of people or animals.
There's a Hebrew phrase ‘nephesh chayyah’ that
is translated ‘living being’. This phrase is
applied to both people, and let's say vertebrate
animals, but does not apply to things like insects
or plants. So the biblical picture is that there
was no death of ‘nephesh chayyah’ life before sin.
So the first point: there was no
death in the very good world. But
that didn't last in Genesis 2:16 and
17 God told Adam, “You may surely eat
of every tree of the garden, but of the tree of
the knowledge of good and evil you shall not eat
for in the day that you eat of it you shall surely
die.” Now, this indicates that there had been no
death in the world up to that point. But once Adam
ate the fruit of that tree he would ‘surely die’.
And that's point number two: Adam's sin ended the
‘very good’ world. It brought in physical death,
disease, pain, suffering,
and the curse on creation.
This is such a key event to
the history of the universe.
Adam and Eve did exactly what God said not to do.
Disobeying God is sin, and the result transitioned
the original ‘very good’ world to a world that
we see around us today that is not very good.
Not very good to say the least. Note that both
spiritual death and physical death were involved.
Spiritual death: sinful man was now separated
from a holy God. And physical death now became
a reality. For example, in Genesis 3:19 God
tells Adam, “By the sweat of your face you
shall eat bread, till you return to the ground,
for out of it you are taken; for you are dust,
and to dust you shall return.” Now that's
obviously talking about physical death, right?
So that's two of the four points
connecting the age of the earth issue
to the Gospel
Now point three follows directly from
point two and it is: there is a connection
between sin and death. That should be obvious.
And a concept that is vital to the Gospel
is the link between sin and death. You've
probably all heard that Jesus died to pay for
sin right? Most people have heard that. There's
a link between sin and death. Romans 6:23 says,
"The wages of sin is death." There's a link,
and that link was established back
in Genesis at the very first sin.
Now notice the connection here between sin and
death. Again, very important, Adam sinned and that
transitioned the world from 'very good', no death,
to the world we have today, not very good and all
die, as it says in Romans 5:12, "Therefore just
as sin came into the world through one man and,
here it is, and death through sin so death
spread to all men because all sinned."
Notice it says all men. Of course, this is
the generic men that includes women as well,
just in case you ladies thought you were
safe. And if anyone's hoping to be saved
by being a good person, Romans 3:23 says,
"for all have sinned and fall short of the
glory of God." And Isaiah 64:6 says, "all our
righteous deeds are like a polluted garment."
And that means we're all in
trouble, right? There's no amount of
good that we can do to earn our salvation.
So what's the solution? If there's no amount
of good you can do to get to heaven,
then how do we get our sins forgiven?
Hebrews 9:22 says, "Without the shedding
of blood there's no forgiveness of sins."
Now again, notice the connection here
between sin and here it's clearly talking
about physical death, isn't it? Physical death is
the payment required for the forgiveness of sins.
We can die to pay for our sins which would involve
being separated from God's goodness forever and
punished for eternity in Hell. But fortunately God
provided a substitute so that the price of death
could be paid on our behalf by someone else and we
could spend forever with a holy God in a sinless
very good world. Jesus, who is God Himself, is
that substitute. Romans 6:23 says, "For the wages
of sin is death but, [here's the good news[, but
the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ
Jesus our Lord." The bad news is that we all
sin and are all destined for eternal punishment,
the good news is that Jesus lived a sinless life
and died in the place of all those who would
believe. Believers’ sins were transferred to him
and his righteous life was transferred to them,
so that when God the Father looks at the
Christian He sees Christ's sinless life. We
get to heaven not because we're good but because
Christ is good. Our righteousness is from God.
Philippians 3:9 says, "and be found in him [now
here it is], not having a righteousness of my
own that comes from the law [in other words not
my own good works in following all of God's law,
His commandments, that no one can keep anyways],
but that which comes through faith in Christ the
righteousness from God that depends on faith."
That's how we're saved. When we turn to
Christ by faith that means believing that
He died for our sins and following Him as Lord
over our lives. When we confess our sins he is
faithful and just to forgive us our sins
and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
And that's amazingly great. But it doesn't end
there. Having paid for our sins by his death
Jesus then defeated death by rising from the dead,
and we can be saved through faith in him alone.
And the Gospel is good news for everyone. If you
haven't turned to Christ we plead with you do that
now. Turn to Christ and be saved. So the final
point, point number four is: Jesus dies to pay for
sins. We've said what you believe about creation
and the age of the earth is not a salvation issue,
but it is a Gospel issue. It connects to the
Gospel specifically to the points we just
summarized in such a way that if the earth really
is millions of years old, the Gospel collapses.
How? Good question. Here it
is: by adding millions of years
into the Bible it breaks the link between sin
and death which was established back in Genesis
And if there's no connection between sin and
death then Jesus didn't die to pay for our
sins. All four of these points come crashing down.
How does adding millions of years into Genesis,
in other words, adopting the history of evolution,
even if you don't believe in evolution, how does
the millions of years break the link between sin
and death? The bible's time scale is critical.
Yes it is. The time scale can be deduced from
Scripture. It's not real hard to do because
of the chrono-genealogies found
in Genesis 5 and Genesis 11, as
well as other time markers laid out in the
Old Testament there, we know it's been only
about 6000 years or so since creation week.
Now that means, if we are tempted to add
in millions or billions of years, they have
to go in before the end of creation week.
And that's a great temptation you know, we get it.
The 'millions of years' are all over the place,
in documentaries, textbooks, movies. It's
everywhere. And because it's so popular,
for Christians, there's a little voice
suggesting: well maybe you could uh fit
it in there. I don't know how but maybe. And
there's no big deal, right? Good Christians I
know believe in an old earth. Great men of
God in the past thought the earth was old.
So there's a big temptation to cast doubt on the
time markers in Scripture. People suggest that,
well, maybe the creation days aren't literal
days. Or maybe Genesis 1 is poetry. Maybe
there was a gap of billions of years just before
creation week began. Maybe Genesis 1 is allegory
for the big bang and the evolutionary
timeline of 13.7, 13.8 billion years.
And we've dealt with all of these suggestions
before on this show. They all fail.
If you're wondering about any of those just
look them up on our website at creation.com
Or look through previous shows
We'll add the next piece of
the puzzle after the break
Many people think that Charles Darwin first
thought of the idea of natural selection. However,
others, prior to Darwin described the concept
although they sometimes used slightly different
terminology. For instance, Carl Linnaeus,
the creationist father of taxonomy, wrote
of a struggle for survival in nature. Similarly
James Hutton wrote about the concept of natural
selection. Probably the most influential
character was Edward Blythe, an English
chemist and zoologist who wrote major articles
on natural selection two decades before Darwin
published "On the Origin of Species". Darwin
differed in trying to use the concept of natural
selection to promote the idea of unlimited change.
However, modern studies of natural selection have
revealed that it is limited it can only select
between variations that already exists. It is
incapable of producing the new genetic information
required for true evolutionary change to occur,
such as growing feathers on a reptile.
Natural selection is not evolution.
To find out more from Creation Ministries
International visit our website creation.com
Okay, let's add the next piece to the puzzle.
The long time scale, the millions of years,
comes from geology. Those layers
of rock that we see in many places
around the world were laid down, well
we're told, slowly over eons of time.
And within those rock layers are dead things,
dead plants and animals preserved as fossils.
But that's not all. There's pain, and diseases,
and extinction, and carnivorous activity, violent
death, there are even fossil thorns there.
Here's a picture of a fossil thorn that's
supposedly millions of years old. Thorns
came after sin, right? And here's a picture
of a hadrosaur vertebrae with a t-rex tooth
embedded between two of its vertebrae,
and the bone is healed over a little bit.
That must mean that the poor hadrosaur
lived for some time after the attack,
right? Likely in terrible pain.
So could God have called all of
this very good? That's the point.
Remember that if the fossil record really is a
record of the burial of life over eons of time
the only place it could really fit in...
Well it doesn't fit anywhere.
...it doesn't fit in anywhere,
but the only place where people attempt
to fit it in is before Adam sinned.
So that places all these terrible things that
scientists have found in the fossil record,
along with all the obviously dead things before
sin. In other words the baggage that comes with
the millions of years history is death before
sin. Death is not the result of sin then.
In that case death has nothing to do with sin.
There's no connection between sin and death.
And if there's no connection between
them, if death is not the result of sin...
We don't need a saviour.
...then we don't need a saviour. So that took a
while to unpack, but if you work the logic through
like we've done these last 20 minutes or so,
the baggage that comes with the millions of
years is death, pain, thorns, disease, etc.
So by attempting to add millions of years into
the Bible you're really adding death before sin,
something that the Bible doesn't
support, and it undermines the Gospel.
And CMI has heard many accounts
of people with a church background
who became convinced of the millions of years, it
starts them on a slippery slope away from Christ.
Consider Charles Templeton he's a famous
example. He was a Canadian evangelist that,
at one point, was more famous than Billy
Graham. He traveled around the world with
Billy Graham's team. Here's a picture of him
in Fredericton, New Brunswick in the 50s.
Later in life he wrote. "Farewell to God - My
Reasons for Rejecting the Christian Faith".
And in that book a big factor at the
start of his rejecting Christianity
was that he became convinced that the history in
the Bible regarding a recent creation was wrong.
He records in his book how he told
Billy Graham about it. He said,
"But Billy, it's simply not possible any longer
to believe for instance the biblical account of
creation. The world wasn't created over a period
of days a few thousand years ago; it has evolved
over millions of years. It's not a matter of
speculation it's demonstrable fact." He wrote.
And eventually he would swallow evolution
along with the millions of years,
but it began with millions of years, and that
led him away from the Gospel. He was taught to
just add millions of years into Genesis
while taking Old Testament courses at
Princeton University. That's ironic. In his book
he complains about how God is so cruel. He wrote,
"Why does God's grand design require creatures
with teeth designed to crush spines or rend flesh,
claws fashion to seize and tear, venom to
paralyze, mouths to suck blood, coils to constrict
and smother--even expandable jaws so that prey
may be swallowed whole and alive... Nature is,
in Tennyson’s vivid phrase, "red in tooth
and claw, and life is a carnival of blood."
So he's looking at life today and seeing these
things, and then assuming that this has gone
on for millions of years, including long before
Adam, when the world was supposed to be very good.
He thought God called all these things very good.
We understand that these things aren't consistent
with what God calls good, but Templeton
was wrong about the millions of years.
He then concludes, "How could a
loving and omnipotent God create
such horrors as we have been contemplating?"
The answer is: He didn't. God
created the world that didn't
include things that scientists
find in the fossil record.
So some of you might be freaking out right now,
right? If there's no millions of years then
how can we explain things like the
layers of rock, the fossil record,
and other things that we're told take a long time.
Understanding Noah’s flood is the solution. The
flood is the key to making sense
of the age of the earth debate,
because a flood would do things very quickly
that without a flood would take a long time.
Yes, like erosion, sedimentation,
mountain building, continental drift. The
flood accelerated all those processes. Yes.
So, back to the questions we posed
at the start. Do you need to be a
young earth creationist to be a
Christian? We already said, no.
Does the age of the earth impact gospel doctrines
such as how Jesus's physical death paid for sins?
Yes it does. Adding millions of years to the
Bible breaks the link between sin and death.
Next one, "Should 6-day, recent creation be
a part of your church's Statement of Faith?
That's for your church leaders to
decide, but here's some food for thought:
is the Trinity part of your church's
statement of faith? It probably is.
The age of the earth issue is different than
the Trinity. You can go your entire Christian
life believing that the earth is old and still
be saved. They're similar in that denying the
Trinity and accepting millions of years are hugely
inconsistent with the Gospel. But believing the
millions of years is not heresy, while believing
that Jesus isn't God is definitely heresy.
Okay, so maybe not a direct apples to apples
comparison there, but the point is, in both
cases if someone wanted to join your church and
they had wrong views in either of those areas
the right thing to do would be to sit down with
them and help them work through those issues,
those inconsistencies, so that they have a
more solid understanding of the Gospel, right?
Sure. And that should happen continually
as believers fellowship, growing together
as a normal part of a healthy church.
Last question. Is the question about when God
created really a hill to die on for Christians?
Well, we believe it is. Charles
Templeton, he was logically consistent,
he was wrong about the age of the earth, but he
was consistent. If there's death, pain, diseases,
etc. before sin, it is inconsistent with the
nature of God, and incompatible with the bible,
and it undermines the Gospel. The question
about when God created really is important.
It's very important. We hope that was helpful. Our
time is gone. Many more details could be added.
If you have any questions about this,
or anything regarding creation and the
flood, just do a search at creation.com.
We'll see you next week and remember Christianity
is an evidence-based faith and
science supports Scripture.
Thanks for watching. So now
can you see how important
the age of the earth issue is to Christianity?
If the earth really is old, as we often hear
it is, it seriously undermines the Gospel.
And if you are leaning toward the earth and
the fossil record being millions of years old,
but now see the biblical problems with that you
are probably asking where you can find
scientific evidence for a young earth.
Yes. A great place to start is creation.com/age
That will take you to an article with 101
evidences for a young age for
the earth and the universe.
Enjoy! And we'll see you next week.